<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2014-2018 Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
-->

<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="kea-config">
  <title>Kea Configuration</title>

  <para>Kea is using JSON structures to handle configuration. Previously
  we there was a concept of other configuration backends, but that never was
  implemented and the idea was abandoned.</para>

  <section xml:id="json">
    <title>JSON Configuration</title>
    <para>JSON is notation used throughout the Kea project. The most obvious
    usage is for configuration file, but it is also used for sending commands
    over Management API (see <xref linkend="ctrl-channel"/>) and for
    communicating between DHCP servers and DDNS update daemon.</para>

    <para>Typical usage assumes that the servers are started from the command line
    (either directly or using a script, e.g. <filename>keactrl</filename>).
    The JSON backend uses certain signals to influence Kea. The
    configuration file is specified upon startup using the -c parameter.</para>

    <section xml:id="json-format">
      <title>JSON Syntax</title>

      <para>Configuration files for DHCPv4, DHCPv6, DDNS, Control
      Agent and Netconf modules are defined in an extended JSON
      format. Basic JSON is defined
      in <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7159">RFC 7159</link> and
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
            xlink:href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-404.htm">ECMA 404</link>.
      Note that Kea 1.2.0 introduced a new parser which better adheres to
      the JSON specification.  In particular, the only values allowed
      for boolean are true or false (all lowercase). The capitalized
      versions (True or False) are not accepted.
      </para>

      <para>Kea components use an extended JSON with additional features
      allowed:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>shell comments: any text after the hash (#)
          character is ignored.</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>C comments: any text after the double slashes (//)
          character is ignored.</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Multiline comments: any text between /* and */ is
          ignored. This commenting can span multiple lines.</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>File inclusion: JSON files can include other JSON
          files. This can be done by using &lt;?include
          "file.json"?&gt;.</simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>The configuration file consists of a single object (often
      colloquially called a map) started with a curly bracket. It
      comprises one of the "Dhcp4", "Dhcp6", "DhcpDdns", "Control-agent",
      "Netconf" object and the "Logging" object. It is possible to define
      additional elements, but they will be ignored and rejected in the
      future releases of Kea. It is also possible to include several
      supported objects in a single configuration file. For example,
      it is possible to include "Dhcp4", "Dhcp6" and "Logging" in a
      single configuration file which can be used to start both the
      DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 servers. Combining configurations of multiple
      Kea modules within a single file can be confusing and works badly
      with the commands that fetch and write new configuration. Therefore,
      support for it will be removed in the future releases of Kea.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          The "loggers" object will be moved inside the configuration
          objects (maps) for respective Kea modules in the Kea 1.6.0 release.
          For example: the "Dhcp4" map will contain the "loggers" object
          specifying logging configuration for the DHCPv4 server. Backward
          compatibility will be maintained until at least Kea 1.7.0 release.
          It will be possible to specify "Logging" object (comprising
          "loggers") at the top configuration level and "loggers"
          object at module configuration level. Ultimately, it
          will only be allowed to specify "loggers" at the module
          configuration level and "Logging" object will be removed.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>A very simple configuration for DHCPv4 could look like this:
<screen>
# The whole configuration starts here.
{

# DHCPv4 specific configuration starts here.
"Dhcp4": {
    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ "eth0" ],
        "dhcp-socket-type": "raw"
    },
    "valid-lifetime": 4000,
    "renew-timer": 1000,
    "rebind-timer": 2000,
    "subnet4": [{
       "pools": [ { "pool": "192.0.2.1-192.0.2.200" } ],
       "subnet": "192.0.2.0/24"
    }]
},
# DHCPv4 specific configuration ends here.

# Logger parameters start here.
"Logging": {
   "loggers": [{
        "name": "*",
        "severity": "DEBUG"
    }]
}

# The whole configuration structure ends here.
}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para>More examples are available in the installed
        <filename>share/doc/kea/examples</filename> directory.</para>

        <para>To avoid repetition of mostly similar structures,
        examples in the rest of this guide will showcase only the
        subset of parameters appropriate for a given context. For
        example, when discussing the IPv6 subnets configuration in
        DHCPv6, only subnet6 parameters will be mentioned. It is
        implied that the remaining elements (the global map that holds
        Dhcp6 and Logging) are present, but they are omitted for
        clarity. Usually, locations where extra parameters may appear
        are denoted by an ellipsis.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Simplified Notation</title>

        <para>It is sometimes convenient to refer to a specific
        element in the configuration hierarchy. Each hierarchy level
        is separated by a slash.  If there is an array, a specific
        instance within that array is referenced by a number in square
        brackets (with numbering starting at zero). For example, in
        the above configuration the valid-lifetime in the Dhcp4
        component can be referred to as Dhcp4/valid-lifetime and the
        pool in the first subnet defined in the DHCPv4 configuration
        as Dhcp4/subnet4[0]/pool.</para>

    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>
