<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2019 Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, you can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
-->

<section xml:id="config-backend">
  <title>Kea Configuration Backend</title>

  <section xml:id="cb-applicability">
    <title>Applicability</title>

    <para>
      Kea Configuration Backend (abbreviated as CB) is a feature first
      introduced in 1.6.0 release, which provides Kea servers with the
      ability to manage and fetch their configuration from one or more
      databases. In the documentation, the term "Configuration Backend"
      may also refer to the particular Kea module providing support
      to manage and fetch the configuration information from the particular
      database type. For example: MySQL Configuration Backend is the logic
      implemented within the "mysql_cb" hooks library which provides a
      complete set of functions to manage and fetch the configuration
      information from the MySQL database.
    </para>

    <para>
      In small deployments, e.g. those comprising a single DHCP server instance
      with limited and infrequently changing number of subnets, it may
      be impractical to use the CB as a configuration repository because
      it requires additional third party software to be installed and
      configured - in particular the  MySQL server and MySQL client.
      Once the number of DHCP servers and/or the number of managed
      subnets in the network grows, the usefulness of the CB becomes
      obvious.
    </para>

    <para>
      A good example is a pair of the Kea DHCP servers which can be
      configured to support High Availability as described in
      <xref linkend="high-availability-library"/>.
      The configurations of both servers are almost exactly the same.
      They may differ by the server identifier and designation of the
      server as a primary or standby (or secondary). They may also
      differ by the interfaces configuration. Typically, the subnets,
      shared networks, option definitions, global parameters are
      the same for both servers and can be sourced from a single
      database instance to both Kea servers.
    </para>

    <para>
      Using the database as a single source of configuration for subnets
      and/or other configuration information supported by the CB has
      the advantage that any modifications to the configuration in
      the database is automatically applied to both servers.
    </para>

    <para>
      Another case when the centralized configuration repository is desired
      is in deployments including large number of the DHCP servers, possibly
      using a common lease database to provide redundancy. The new servers
      can be added to the pool frequently to fulfil growing scalability
      requirements. Adding the new server does not require replicating
      the entire configuration to the new server when common database is
      used.
    </para>

    <para>
      Using the database as a configuration repository for Kea servers also
      brings other benefits, such as:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><simpara>an ability to use database specific tools to access
        the configuration information,</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>an ability to create customized statistics based
        on the information stored in the database,</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>an ability to backup the configuration information
        using the database builtin replication mechanisms.</simpara></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

  </section>

  <section xml:id="cb-limitations">
    <title>CB Capabilities and Limitations</title>
    <para>
      Kea CB has been introduced in the 1.6.0 release, but this
      implementation comes with a number of limitations being the
      result of the overall complexity of this feature and the development
      time constraints. This feature will evolve over time and the new
      capabilities will be added in subsequent releases. In this
      section we present the limitations of the CB, present in the
      current Kea 1.6.0 release:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><simpara>
        Kea CB is currently supported for the MySQL database only.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
        Kea CB is only supported for DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 servers.
        Neither Control Agent nor D2 deamon can be configured via the database.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
        Configuration to be stored for the DHCP servers includes: global parameters,
        option definitions, global options, shared networks and subnets. Other
        configuration parameters are not stored in the database at the moment.
        They have to be configured via the JSON configuration file.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
        It is not supported to differentiate configurations of multiple
        DHCP servers within the same database. All servers conected to the
        particular database instance share the configuration stored in this
        database. This limitation will be removed in Kea 1.6.0 final release.
      </simpara></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="cb-components">
    <title>CB Components</title>
    <para>
      In order to use the Kea CB feature, the Kea 1.6.0 version or later is
      required. The <command>mysql_cb</command> open source hooks library
      implementing the Configuration Backend for MySQL must be compiled and
      loaded by the DHCP servers. This hooks library is compiled when the
      <filename>--with-mysql</filename> configuration switch is used during
      Kea build. The MySQL C client libraries must be installed
      as explained in the <xref linkend="dhcp-install-configure"/>.
    </para>

    <note>
      <simpara>Any existing MySQL schema must be upgraded to the latest schema
      required by the particular Kea version using <command>kea-admin</command>
      tool described in <xref linkend="kea-admin"/>.</simpara>
    </note>

    <para>
      The <command>cb_cmds</command> premium hooks library is available to
      ISC paid supported customers, which provides a complete set of commands
      to manage the servers' configuration information within the database.
      This library can be attached to both DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 server instance.
      It is still possible to manage the configuration information without the
      <command>cb_cmds</command> hooks library with commonly available tools
      such as MySQL Workbench or command line MySQL client, by directly working
      with the database.
    </para>

    <para>
      Refer to the <xref linkend="cb-cmds-library"/> for the details regarding
      the <command>cb_cmds</command> hooks library.
    </para>

    <para>
      The DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 server specific configuration of the CB as well as
      the list of supported configuration parameters can be found in the
      <xref linkend="dhcp4-cb"/> and <xref linkend="dhcp6-cb"/>
      respectively.
    </para>

  </section>

</section>
