<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2014-2019 Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, you can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
-->
<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="dhcp6">
    <title>The DHCPv6 Server</title>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-start-stop">
      <title>Starting and Stopping the DHCPv6 Server</title>

      <para>
        It is recommended that the Kea DHCPv6 server be started and stopped
        using <command>keactrl</command> (described in <xref linkend="keactrl"/>);
        however, it is also possible to run the server directly. It accepts
        the following command-line switches:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
            <command>-c <replaceable>file</replaceable></command> -
            specifies the configuration file. This is the only mandatory
            switch.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
            <command>-d</command> - specifies whether the server
            logging should be switched to verbose mode. In verbose mode,
            the logging severity and debuglevel specified in the configuration
            file are ignored and "debug" severity and the maximum debuglevel
            (99) are assumed. The flag is convenient for temporarily
            switching the server into maximum verbosity, e.g. when
            debugging.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
            <command>-p <replaceable>server-port</replaceable></command> -
            specifies the local UDP port on which the server will listen.
            This is only useful during testing, as a DHCPv6 server
            listening on ports other than the standard ones will not
            be able to handle regular DHCPv6 queries.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
            <command>-P <replaceable>client-port</replaceable></command> -
            specifies the remote UDP port to which the server will send
            all responses. This is only useful during testing, as a
            DHCPv6 server sending responses to ports other than the
            standard ones will not be able to handle regular DHCPv6
            queries.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
            <command>-t <replaceable>file</replaceable></command> - specifies a
            configuration file to be tested. Kea-dhcp6 will load it, check it, and
            exit. During the test, log messages are printed to standard output and
            error messages to standard error. The result of the test is reported
            through the exit code (0 = configuration looks ok, 1 = error
            encountered). The check is not comprehensive; certain checks are
            possible only when running the server.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              <command>-v</command> - displays the Kea version and exits.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              <command>-V</command> - displays the Kea extended version with
              additional parameters and exits. The listing includes the versions
              of the libraries dynamically linked to Kea.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              <command>-W</command> - displays the Kea configuration report
              and exits. The report is a copy of the
              <filename>config.report</filename> file produced by
              <userinput>./configure</userinput>; it is embedded in the
              executable binary.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        On startup, the server will detect available network interfaces
        and will attempt to open UDP sockets on all interfaces
        mentioned in the configuration file.
        Since the DHCPv6 server opens privileged ports, it requires root
        access. Make sure you run this daemon as root.
      </para>

      <para>
        During startup, the server will attempt to create a PID file of the
        form: localstatedir]/[conf name].kea-dhcp6.pid where:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
            <simpara><command>localstatedir</command>: The value as passed into the
            build configure script; it defaults to "/usr/local/var". Note
            that this value may be overridden at runtime by setting the environment
            variable KEA_PIDFILE_DIR, although this is intended primarily for testing purposes.
            </simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <simpara><command>conf name</command>: The configuration file name
            used to start the server, minus all preceding paths and the file extension.
            For example, given a pathname of "/usr/local/etc/kea/myconf.txt", the
            portion used would be "myconf".
            </simpara>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        If the file already exists and contains the PID of a live process,
        the server will issue a DHCP6_ALREADY_RUNNING log message and exit. It
        is possible, though unlikely, that the file is a remnant of a system crash
        and the process to which the PID belongs is unrelated to Kea. In such a
        case it would be necessary to manually delete the PID file.
      </para>

      <para>
        The server can be stopped using the <command>kill</command> command.
        When running in a console, the server can also be shut down by
        pressing ctrl-c. It detects the key combination and shuts
        down gracefully.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-configuration">
      <title>DHCPv6 Server Configuration</title>
<section>
  <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>
        This section explains how to configure the DHCPv6 server using a
        configuration file. Before DHCPv6 is started, its configuration
        file has to be created. The basic configuration is as follows:
<screen>
{
# DHCPv6 configuration starts on the next line
"Dhcp6": {

# First we set up global values
    "valid-lifetime": 4000,
    "renew-timer": 1000,
    "rebind-timer": 2000,
    "preferred-lifetime": 3000,

# Next we setup the interfaces to be used by the server.
    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ "eth0" ]
    },

# And we specify the type of lease database
    "lease-database": {
        "type": "memfile",
        "persist": true,
        "name": "/var/kea/dhcp6.leases"
    },

# Finally, we list the subnets from which we will be leasing addresses.
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
            "pools": [
                 {
                     "pool": "2001:db8:1::1-2001:db8:1::ffff"
                 }
             ]
        }
    ]
# DHCPv6 configuration ends with the next line
}

} </screen>
</para>

<para>The following paragraphs provide a brief overview of the parameters in
the above example, along with
their format. Subsequent sections of this chapter go into much greater detail
for these and other parameters.</para>

<para>The lines starting with a hash (#) are comments and are ignored by
the server; they do not impact its
operation in any way.</para>

<para>The configuration starts in the first line with the initial
opening curly bracket (or brace). Each configuration must contain an
object specifying the configuration of the Kea module using it.
In the example above this object is called <command>Dhcp6</command>.
</para>

<note>
  <para>In the current Kea release it is possible to specify configurations
  of multiple modules within a single configuration file, but this is not
  recommended. The
  only object, besides the one specifying module configuration, which can be
  (and usually is) included in the same file, is the <command>Logging</command> object.
  However, we don't include this object in the example above for clarity.
  </para>
</note>

<para>The Dhcp6 configuration starts with the <command>"Dhcp6": {</command> line
and ends with the corresponding closing brace (in the above example,
the brace after the last comment). Everything defined between those
lines is considered to be the Dhcp6 configuration.</para>

<para>In the general case, the order in which those parameters appear does not
matter, but there are two caveats. The first one is to remember that
the configuration file must be well-formed JSON. That means that the parameters
for any given scope must be separated by a comma and there must not be a comma
after the last parameter. When reordering a configuration file, keep in mind that
moving a parameter to or from the last position in a given scope may also require
moving the comma. The second caveat is that it is uncommon — although
legal JSON — to
repeat the same parameter multiple times. If that happens, the last occurrence of a
given parameter in a given scope is used, while all previous instances are
ignored. This is unlikely to cause any confusion as there are no real-life
reasons to keep multiple copies of the same parameter in your configuration
file.</para>

<para>Moving onto the DHCPv6 configuration elements, the first few elements
define some global parameters. <command>valid-lifetime</command>
defines how long the addresses (leases) given out by the server are valid. If
nothing changes, a client that got an address is allowed to use it for 4000
seconds. (Note that integer numbers are specified as is, without any quotes
around them.) The address will become deprecated in 3000 seconds, i.e. clients are
allowed to keep old connections, but can't use this address for creating new
connections. <command>renew-timer</command> and
<command> rebind-timer</command> are values that define T1 and T2 timers that
govern when the client will begin the renewal and rebind procedures.</para>

<para>The <command>interfaces-config</command> map specifies the server
configuration concerning the network interfaces, on which the server should
listen to the DHCP messages. The <command>interfaces</command> parameter
specifies a list of network interfaces on which the server should listen.
Lists are opened and closed with square brackets, with elements separated
by commas. To listen on two interfaces, the
<command>interfaces-config</command> should look like this:
<screen>
"interfaces-config": {
    "interfaces": [ "eth0", "eth1" ]
},
</screen>
</para>

<para>The next couple of lines define the lease database, the place where the server
stores its lease information. This particular example tells the server to use
<command>memfile</command>, which is the simplest (and fastest) database
backend. It uses an in-memory database and stores leases on disk in a CSV
file. This is a very simple configuration; usually the lease database configuration
is more extensive and contains additional parameters.  Note that
<command>lease-database</command>
is an object and opens up a new scope, using an opening brace.
Its parameters (just one in this example - <command>type</command>)
follow. If there were more than one, they would be separated by commas. This
scope is closed with a closing brace. As more parameters for the Dhcp6 definition
follow, a trailing comma is present.</para>

<para>Finally, we need to define a list of IPv6 subnets. This is the
most important DHCPv6 configuration structure as the server uses that
information to process clients' requests. It defines all subnets from
which the server is expected to receive DHCP requests. The subnets are
specified with the <command>subnet6</command> parameter. It is a list,
so it starts and ends with square brackets.  Each subnet definition in
the list has several attributes associated with it, so it is a structure
and is opened and closed with braces. At a minimum, a subnet definition
has to have at least two parameters: <command>subnet</command> (which
defines the whole subnet) and <command>pools</command> (which is a list of
dynamically allocated pools that are governed by the DHCP server).</para>

<para>The example contains a single subnet. If more than one were defined,
additional elements
in the <command>subnet6</command> parameter would be specified and
separated by commas. For example, to define two subnets, the following
syntax would be used:
<screen>
"subnet6": [
    {
        "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1::/112" } ],
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64"
    },
    {
        "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:2::1-2001:db8:2::ffff" } ],
        "subnet": "2001:db8:2::/64"
    }
]
</screen>
Note that indentation is optional and is used for aesthetic purposes only.
In some cases in may be preferable to use more compact notation.
</para>

<para>After all parameters are specified, we have two contexts open:
global and Dhcp6, so we need two closing curly brackets to close them.
In a real-life configuration file there most likely would be additional
components defined such as Logging, so the first closing brace would be followed
by a comma and another object definition.</para>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Lease Storage</title>
  <para>All leases issued by the server are stored in the lease database.
  Currently there are four database backends available:  memfile (which is the
  default backend), MySQL, PostgreSQL, and Cassandra.</para>
<section>
  <title>Memfile - Basic Storage for Leases</title>

  <para>The server is able to store lease data in different repositories. Larger
  deployments may elect to store leases in a database. <xref linkend="database-configuration6"/> describes this option. In typical
  smaller deployments though, the server will store lease information in a CSV file rather
  than a database. As well as requiring less administration, an
  advantage of using a file for storage is that it
  eliminates a dependency on third-party database software.</para>

  <para>The configuration of the file backend (Memfile) is controlled through
  the Dhcp6/lease-database parameters. The <command>type</command> parameter
  is mandatory and it specifies which storage for leases the server should use.
  The value of <userinput>"memfile"</userinput> indicates that the file should
  be used as the storage. The following list gives additional optional
  parameters that can be used to configure the Memfile backend.

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara><command>persist</command>: controls whether the new leases and
      updates to existing leases are written to the file. It is strongly
      recommended that the value of this parameter is set to
      <userinput>true</userinput> at all times, during the server's normal
      operation. Not writing leases to disk means that if a server is restarted
      (e.g. after a power failure), it will not know what addresses have been
      assigned. As a result, it may hand out addresses to new clients that are
      already in use. The value of <userinput>false</userinput> is mostly useful
      for performance-testing purposes. The default value of the
      <command>persist</command> parameter is <userinput>true</userinput>,
      which enables writing lease updates
      to the lease file.
      </simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara><command>name</command>: specifies an absolute location of the lease
      file in which new leases and lease updates will be recorded. The default value
      for this parameter is <userinput>"[kea-install-dir]/var/kea/kea-leases6.csv"
      </userinput>.</simpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <simpara><command>lfc-interval</command>: specifies the interval, in seconds, at
      which the server will perform a lease file cleanup (LFC).  This
      removes redundant (historical) information from the lease file
      and effectively reduces the lease file size. The cleanup process is described
      in more detailed fashion further in this section. The default value of the
      <command>lfc-interval</command> is <userinput>3600</userinput>. A value of 0
      disables the LFC.</simpara>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>An example configuration of the Memfile backend is presented below:

<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "lease-database": {
        <userinput>"type": "memfile"</userinput>,
        <userinput>"persist": true</userinput>,
        <userinput>"name": "/tmp/kea-leases6.csv"</userinput>,
        <userinput>"lfc-interval": 1800</userinput>
    }
}
</screen>

    This configuration selects the <filename>/tmp/kea-leases6.csv</filename> as
    the storage for lease information and enables persistence (writing lease updates
    to this file). It also configures the backend to perform a periodic cleanup
    of the lease file every 30 minutes.
  </para>

  <para>It is important to know how the lease file contents are organized
  to understand why the periodic lease file cleanup is needed. Every time
  the server updates a lease or creates a new lease for the client, the new
  lease information must be recorded in the lease file. For performance reasons,
  the server does not update the existing client's lease in the file, as this would
  potentially require rewriting the entire file. Instead, it simply appends the new lease
  information to the end of the file; the previous lease entries for the
  client are not removed. When the server loads leases from the lease file, e.g.
  at the server startup, it assumes that the latest lease entry for the client
  is the valid one. The previous entries are discarded, meaning that the
  server can re-construct the accurate information about the leases even though
  there may be many lease entries for each client. However, storing many entries
  for each client results in a bloated lease file and impairs the performance of
  the server's startup and reconfiguration, as it needs to process a larger number
  of lease entries.
  </para>

  <para>Lease file cleanup (LFC) removes all previous entries for each client and
  leaves only the latest ones. The interval at which the cleanup is performed
  is configurable, and it should be selected according to the frequency of lease
  renewals initiated by the clients. The more frequent the renewals, the smaller
  the value of <command>lfc-interval</command> should be. Note, however, that the
  LFC takes time and thus it is possible (although unlikely) that, if the
  <command>lfc-interval</command> is too short, a new cleanup
  may be started while the previous one is still running. The server would recover from
  this by skipping the new cleanup when it detects that the previous cleanup
  is still in progress. But it implies that the actual cleanups will be
  triggered more rarely than configured. Moreover, triggering a new cleanup
  adds overhead to the server, which will not be able to respond to new
  requests for a short period of time when the new cleanup process is spawned.
  Therefore, it is recommended that the <command>lfc-interval</command> value
  is selected in a way that would allow for the LFC to complete the cleanup before a
  new cleanup is triggered.
  </para>

  <para>Lease file cleanup is performed by a separate process (in the background) to avoid
  a performance impact on the server process. To avoid the conflicts
  between two processes both using the same lease files, the LFC process
  starts with Kea opening new lease file and the actual LFC process
  operates on the lease file that is no longer used by the server. There are also other files
  created as a side effect of the lease file cleanup. The detailed
  description of the LFC is located later in this Kea Administrator's Reference Manual:
  <xref linkend="kea-lfc" />.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="database-configuration6">
  <title>Lease Database Configuration</title>

  <note>
    <para>Lease database access information must be configured for the DHCPv6 server,
    even if it has already been configured for the DHCPv4 server. The servers
    store their information independently, so each server can use a separate
    database or both servers can use the same database.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Lease database configuration is controlled through the
  Dhcp6/lease-database parameters. The type of the database must be set to
  "memfile", "mysql", "postgresql", or "cql", e.g.:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"type": "mysql"</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  Next, the name of the database to hold the leases must be set; this is the
  name used when the database was created
  (see <xref linkend="mysql-database-create"/>,
  <xref linkend="pgsql-database-create"/>,
  or <xref linkend="cql-database-create"/>).
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"name": "<replaceable>database-name</replaceable>" </userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  For Cassandra:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"keyspace": "<replaceable>database-name</replaceable>" </userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  If the database is located on a different system from the DHCPv6 server, the
  database host name must also be specified. (It should be noted that this
  configuration may have a severe impact on server performance.):
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"host": "<replaceable>remote-host-name</replaceable>"</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  For Cassandra, multiple contact points can be provided:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"contact-points": "<replaceable>remote-host-name[, ...]</replaceable>" </userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  Normally, the database will be on the same machine as
  the DHCPv6 server. In this case, set the value to the empty string:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"host" : ""</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  For Cassandra:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"contact-points": ""</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  Should the database use a port different than the default, it may be
  specified as well:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"port" : 12345</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  Should the database be located on a different system, you may need to specify a longer interval
  for the connection timeout:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"connect-timeout" : <replaceable>timeout-in-seconds</replaceable></userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
The default value of five seconds should be more than adequate for local connections.
If a timeout is given, though, it should be an integer greater than zero.
  </para>
  <para>
The maxiumum number of times the server will automatically attempt to reconnect to
the lease database after connectivity has been lost may be specified:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"max-reconnect-tries" : <replaceable>number-of-tries</replaceable></userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
If the server is unable to reconnect to the database after making the maximum number
of attempts the server will exit. A value of zero (the default) disables automatic
recovery and the server will exit immediately upon detecting a loss of connectivity
(MySQL and Postgres only).
  </para>
  <para>
The number of milliseconds the server will wait in between attempts to reconnect to the
lease database after connectivity has been lost may also be specified:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"reconnect-wait-time" : <replaceable>number-of-milliseconds</replaceable></userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
The default value for MySQL and Postgres is 0, which disables automatic recovery and
causes the server to exit immediately upon detecting the loss of connectivity.
The default value for Cassandra is 2000 ms.
  </para>

  <note>
    <para>
      Automatic reconnection to database backends is configured individually per backend.
      This allows you to tailor the recovery parameters to each backend you use.
      We do suggest that you enable it either for all backends or no backends so you
      have consistent behavior.  Losing connectivity to a backend for which reconnect
      is disabled will result in the server shutting itself down. This includes
      cases when the lease database backend and the hosts database backend are connected to
      the same database instance.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para>
    <note>Note that host parameter is used by MySQL and PostgreSQL
    backends. Cassandra has a concept of contact points that could be
    used to contact the cluster, instead of a single IP or
    hostname. It takes a list of comma-separated IP addresses, which may be specified as:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"contact-points" : "192.0.2.1,192.0.2.2"</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  </note></para>

  <para>Finally, the credentials of the account under which the server will
  access the database should be set:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "lease-database": { <userinput>"user": "<replaceable>user-name</replaceable>"</userinput>,
                               <userinput>"password": "<replaceable>password</replaceable>"</userinput>,
                              ... },
           ... }
</screen>
  If there is no password to the account, set the password to the empty string
  "". (This is also the default.)</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="cassandra-database-configuration6">
    <title>Cassandra-Specific Parameters</title>
<para>The parameters are the same for DHCPv4 and DHCPv6. See <xref
linkend="cassandra-database-configuration4"/> for details.</para>
</section>

</section>

<section xml:id="hosts6-storage">
  <title>Hosts Storage</title>
    <para>Kea is also able to store information about host reservations in the
    database. The hosts database configuration uses the same syntax as the lease
    database. In fact, a Kea server opens independent connections for each
    purpose, be it lease or hosts information. This arrangement gives the most
    flexibility. Kea can keep leases and host reservations
    separately, but can also point to the same database. Currently the
    supported hosts database types are MySQL, PostgreSQL and Cassandra.</para>

    <para>For example, the following configuration can be used to
    configure connection to MySQL:
    <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    <userinput>"hosts-database": {
        "type": "mysql",
        "name": "kea",
        "user": "kea",
        "password": "secret123",
        "host": "localhost",
        "port": 3306
    }</userinput>
}</screen> Note that depending on your database configuration, many of
    the parameters may be optional.</para>


    <para>Please note that usage of hosts storage is optional. A user can define
    all host reservations in the configuration file, and that is the recommended way
    if the number of reservations is small. However, when the number of
    reservations grows, it is more convenient to use host storage. Please note
    that both storage methods (configuration file and one of the supported databases)
    can be used together. If hosts are defined in both places, the definitions
    from the configuration file are checked first and external storage is checked
    later, if necessary.</para>

    <para>In fact, host information can be placed in multiple stores. Operations
    are performed on the stores in the order they are defined in the configuration
    file, although this leads to a restriction in ordering in the case of a host
    reservation addition; read-only stores must be configured after a (required)
    read-write store, or the addition will fail.</para>

<section xml:id="hosts-databases-configuration6">
  <title>DHCPv6 Hosts Database Configuration</title>

  <para>Hosts database configuration is controlled through the Dhcp6/hosts-database
  parameters. If enabled, the type of database must be set to "mysql" or
  "postgresql".
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "hosts-database": { <userinput>"type": "mysql"</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  Next, the name of the database to hold the reservations must be set; this is the
  name used when the database was created  (see <xref linkend="supported-databases"/>
  for instructions on how to set up the desired database type).
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "hosts-database": { <userinput>"name": "<replaceable>database-name</replaceable>" </userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  If the database is located on a different system than the DHCPv6 server, the
  database host name must also be specified. (Again it should be noted that this
  configuration may have a severe impact on server performance.)
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "hosts-database": { <userinput>"host": <replaceable>remote-host-name</replaceable></userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  Normally, the database will be on the same machine as
  the DHCPv6 server. In this case, set the value to the empty string:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "hosts-database": { <userinput>"host" : ""</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "hosts-database": { <userinput>"port" : 12345</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
  </para>
  <para>
The maximum number of times the server will automatically attempt to reconnect to
the host database after connectivity has been lost may be specified:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "host-database": { <userinput>"max-reconnect-tries" : <replaceable>number-of-tries</replaceable></userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
If the server is unable to reconnect to the database after making the maximum number
of attempts the server will exit. A value of zero (the default) disables automatic
recovery and the server will exit immediately upon detecting a loss of connectivity
(MySQL and Postgres only). For Cassandra, Kea uses a Cassandra interface that
connects to all nodes in a cluster at the same time. Any connectivity
issues should be handled by internal Cassandra mechanisms.
  </para>
  <para>
The number of milliseconds the server will wait between attempts to reconnect to the
host database after connectivity has been lost may also be specified:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "hosts-database": { <userinput>"reconnect-wait-time" : <replaceable>number-of-milliseconds</replaceable></userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
The default value for MySQL and Postgres is 0, which disables automatic recovery and
causes the server to exit immediately upon detecting the loss of connectivity.
The default value for Cassandra is 2000 ms.
  </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        Automatic reconnection to database backends is configured individually per backend.
        This allows you to tailor the recovery parameters to each backend you use.
        We do suggest that you enable it either for all backends or no backends so you
        have consistent behavior. Losing connectivity to a backend for which reconnect
        is disabled will result in the server shutting itself down. This includes
        cases when the lease database backend and the hosts database backend are connected to
        the same database instance.
      </para>
    </note>

  <para>Finally, the credentials of the account under which the server will
  access the database should be set:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "hosts-database": { <userinput>"user": "<replaceable>user-name</replaceable>"</userinput>,
                               <userinput>"password": "<replaceable>password</replaceable>"</userinput>,
                              ... },
           ... }
</screen>
  If there is no password to the account, set the password to the empty string
  "". (This is also the default.)</para>

  <para>The multiple store extension uses a similar syntax; a configuration
  is placed into a "hosts-databases" list instead of into a "hosts-database"
  entry as in:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "hosts-databases": [ { <userinput>"type": "mysql"</userinput>, ... }, ... ], ... }
</screen>
  </para>

  <para>
    For additional Cassandra-specific parameters, see <xref
    linkend="cassandra-database-configuration4"/>.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="read-only-database-configuration6">
<title>Using Read-Only Databases for Host Reservations</title>
<para>
In some deployments the database user whose name is specified in the database backend
configuration may not have write privileges to the database. This is often
required by the policy within a given network to secure the data from being
unintentionally modified. In many cases administrators have deployed inventory databases,
which contain substantially more information about the hosts than just the
static reservations assigned to them. The inventory database can be used to create
a view of a Kea hosts database and such a view is often read-only.
</para>
<para>
Kea host database backends operate with an implicit configuration to both
read from and write to the database. If the database user does not have
write access to the host database, the backend will fail to start and the
server will refuse to start (or reconfigure). However, if access to a read-
only host database is required for retrieving reservations for clients
and/or assigning specific addresses and options, it is possible to explicitly
configure Kea to start in "read-only" mode. This is controlled by the
<command>readonly</command> boolean parameter as follows:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { "hosts-database": { <userinput>"readonly": true</userinput>, ... }, ... }
</screen>
Setting this parameter to <userinput>false</userinput> configures the
database backend to operate in "read-write" mode, which is also the default
configuration if the parameter is not specified.
</para>
<note><para>The <command>readonly</command> parameter is currently only supported
for MySQL and PostgreSQL databases.</para></note>
</section>

</section>

<section xml:id="dhcp6-interface-configuration">
  <title>Interface Configuration</title>
  <para>The DHCPv6 server has to be configured to listen on specific network
  interfaces.  The simplest network interface configuration instructs the server to
  listen on all available interfaces:
  <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ <userinput>"*"</userinput> ]
    }
    ...
}
</screen>
  The asterisk plays the role of a wildcard and means "listen on all interfaces."
  However, it is usually a good idea to explicitly specify interface names:
  <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ <userinput>"eth1", "eth3"</userinput> ]
    },
    ...
}
  </screen>
</para>
  <para>It is possible to use a wildcard interface name (asterisk) concurrently
  with explicit interface names:
  <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ <userinput>"eth1", "eth3", "*"</userinput> ]
    },
    ...
}
  </screen>
It is anticipated that this form of usage will only be used when it is desired to
temporarily override a list of interface names and listen on all interfaces.
  </para>

  <para>As with the DHCPv4 server, binding to specific addresses and
  disabling re-detection of interfaces are supported. But
  <command>dhcp-socket-type</command> is not because DHCPv6 uses
  UDP/IPv6 sockets only. The following example shows how to disable the
  interface detection:
  </para>

  <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ <userinput>"eth1", "eth3"</userinput> ],
        "re-detect": <userinput>false</userinput>
    },
    ...
}
  </screen>

  <para>The loopback interfaces (i.e. the "lo" or "lo0" interface)
  are not configured by default, unless explicitely mentioned in
  the configuration. Note that Kea requires a link-local address (which does
  not exist on all systems), or a specified unicast address as in:
  </para>

  <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ <userinput>"enp0s2/2001:db8::1234:abcd"</userinput> ]
    },
    ...
}
  </screen>

</section>

    <section xml:id="ipv6-subnet-id">
      <title>IPv6 Subnet Identifier</title>
      <para>
        The subnet identifier is a unique number associated with a particular subnet.
        In principle, it is used to associate clients' leases with their respective subnets.
        When a subnet identifier is not specified for a subnet being configured, it will
        be automatically assigned by the configuration mechanism. The identifiers
        are assigned from 1 and are monotonically increased for each subsequent
        subnet: 1, 2, 3 ....
      </para>
      <para>
        If there are multiple subnets configured with auto-generated identifiers and
        one of them is removed, the subnet identifiers may be renumbered. For example:
        if there are four subnets and the third is removed, the last subnet will be assigned
        the identifier that the third subnet had before removal. As a result, the leases
        stored in the lease database for subnet 3 are now associated with
        subnet 4, something that may have unexpected consequences. The only remedy for this issue
        at present is to
        manually specify a unique identifier for each subnet.
      </para>
      <note>
        Subnet IDs must be greater than zero and less than 4294967295.
      </note>
      <para>
        The following configuration will assign the specified subnet
        identifier to the newly configured subnet:

        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
            <userinput>"id": 1024</userinput>,
            ...
        }
    ]
}
</screen>
        This identifier will not change for this subnet unless the "id" parameter is
        removed or set to 0. The value of 0 forces auto-generation of the subnet
        identifier.
      </para>
      <!-- @todo: describe whether database needs to be updated after changing
      id -->
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-unicast">
      <title>Unicast Traffic Support</title>
      <para>
        When the DHCPv6 server starts, by default it listens to the DHCP traffic
        sent to multicast address ff02::1:2 on each interface that it is
        configured to listen on (see <xref linkend="dhcp6-interface-configuration"/>).
        In some cases it is useful to configure a server to handle incoming
        traffic sent to global unicast addresses as well. The most common
        reason for this is to have relays send their traffic to the server
        directly. To configure the server to listen on a specific unicast address,
        the interface name can be
        optionally followed by a slash, followed by the global unicast address on which
        the server should listen. The server listens to this address in addition to normal
        link-local binding and listening on the ff02::1:2 address. The sample configuration
        below shows how to listen on 2001:db8::1 (a global address)
        configured on the eth1 interface.
      </para>
      <para>
 <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ <userinput>"eth1/2001:db8::1"</userinput> ]
    },
    ...
    "option-data": [
        {
            "name": "unicast",
            "data": "2001:db8::1"
        } ],
    ...
}
 </screen>

        This configuration will cause the server to listen on
        eth1 on the link-local address, the multicast group (ff02::1:2), and 2001:db8::1.
      </para>
      <para>
        Usually unicast support is associated with a server unicast option
        which allows clients to send unicast messages to the server.
        The example above includes a server unicast option specification
        which will cause the client to send messages to the specified
        unicast address.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is possible to mix interface names, wildcards, and interface names/addresses
        in the list of interfaces. It is not possible, however, to specify more than one
        unicast address on a given interface.
      </para>
      <para>
        Care should be taken to specify proper unicast addresses. The server will
        attempt to bind to the addresses specified without any additional checks.
        This approach was selected on purpose to allow the software to
        communicate over uncommon addresses if so desired.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-address-config">
      <title>Subnet and Address Pool</title>
      <para>
        The main role of a DHCPv6 server is address assignment. For this,
        the server must be configured with at least one subnet and one pool of dynamic
        addresses to be managed. For example, assume that the server
        is connected to a network segment that uses the 2001:db8:1::/64
        prefix. The administrator of that network decides that addresses from range
        2001:db8:1::1 to 2001:db8:1::ffff are going to be managed by the Dhcp6
        server. Such a configuration can be achieved in the following way:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    <userinput>"subnet6": [
       {
           "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
           "pools": [
               {
                   "pool": "2001:db8:1::1-2001:db8:1::ffff"
               }
           ],
           ...
       }
    ]</userinput>
}</screen>

        Note that <command>subnet</command> is defined as a simple string, but
        the <command>pools</command> parameter is actually a list of pools; for
        this reason, the pool definition is enclosed in square brackets, even
        though only one range of addresses is specified.</para>

        <para>Each <command>pool</command> is a structure that contains the
        parameters that describe a single pool. Currently there is only one
        parameter, <command>pool</command>, which gives the range of addresses
        in the pool.</para>

        <para>It is possible to define more than one pool in a
        subnet; continuing the previous example, further assume that
        2001:db8:1:0:5::/80 should also be managed by the server. It could be written as
        2001:db8:1:0:5:: to 2001:db8:1::5:ffff:ffff:ffff, but typing so many 'f's
        is cumbersome. It can be expressed more simply as 2001:db8:1:0:5::/80. Both
        formats are supported by Dhcp6 and can be mixed in the pool list.
        For example, one could define the following pools:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    <userinput>"subnet6": [
    {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
        "pools": [
            { "pool": "2001:db8:1::1-2001:db8:1::ffff" },
            { "pool": "2001:db8:1:05::/80" }
        ]</userinput>,
        ...
    }
    ]
}</screen>
        White space in pool definitions is ignored, so spaces before and after the hyphen are optional.
        They can be used to improve readability.
      </para>
      <para>
        The number of pools is not limited, but for performance reasons it is recommended to
        use as few as possible.
      </para>
      <para>
         The server may be configured to serve more than one subnet. To add a second subnet,
         use a command similar to the following:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    <userinput>"subnet6": [
    {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
        "pools": [
            { "pool": "2001:db8:1::1-2001:db8:1::ffff" }
        ]
    },
    {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:2::/64",
        "pools": [
            { "pool": "2001:db8:2::/64" }
        ]
    },
</userinput>
        ...
    ]
}</screen>
        In this example, we allow the server to
        dynamically assign all addresses available in the whole subnet. Although
        rather wasteful, it is certainly a valid configuration to dedicate the
        whole /64 subnet for that purpose. Note that the Kea server does not preallocate
        the leases, so there is no danger in using gigantic address pools.
      </para>
      <para>
        When configuring a DHCPv6 server using prefix/length notation, please pay
        attention to the boundary values. When specifying that the server can use
        a given pool, it will also be able to allocate the first (typically a network
        address) address from that pool. For example, for pool 2001:db8:2::/64 the
        2001:db8:2:: address may be assigned as well. To avoid this,
        use the "min-max" notation.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Subnet and Prefix Delegation Pools</title>
      <para>
        Subnets may also be configured to delegate prefixes, as defined in
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link>,
        section 6.3. A subnet may have one or more prefix delegation pools.
        Each pool has a prefixed address, which is specified as a prefix
        (<command>prefix</command>) and a prefix length
        (<command>prefix-len</command>), as well as a delegated prefix length
        (<command>delegated-len</command>). The delegated length must not be
        shorter than (that is, it must be numerically greater than or equal to) the
        prefix length. If both the delegated and prefix lengths are equal, the
        server will be able to delegate only one prefix. The delegated prefix
        does not have to match the subnet prefix.
      </para>
      <para> Below is a sample subnet configuration which enables prefix
      delegation for the subnet:
      <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:d8b:1::/64",
            <userinput>"pd-pools": [
                {
                    "prefix": "3000:1::",
                    "prefix-len": 64,
                    "delegated-len": 96
                }
            ]</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}</screen>
      </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="pd-exclude-option">
        <title>Prefix Exclude Option</title>
        <para>
          For each delegated prefix, the delegating router may choose to exclude
          a single prefix out of the delegated prefix as specified in 
          <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6603">RFC 6603</link>.
          The requesting router must not assign the excluded prefix to any
          of its downstream interfaces, and it is intended to be used on a
          link through which the delegating router exchanges DHCPv6 messages with
          the requesting router. The configuration example below demonstrates how
          to specify an excluded prefix within a prefix pool definition. The
          excluded prefix "2001:db8:1:babe:cafe:80::/72" will be sent to a
          requesting router which includes the Prefix Exclude option in the ORO, and
          which is delegated a prefix from this pool.
        </para>
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/48",
            "pd-pools": [
                {
                    "prefix": "2001:db8:1:8000::",
                    "prefix-len": 48,
                    "delegated-len": 64,
                    "excluded-prefix": "2001:db8:1:babe:cafe:80::",
                    "excluded-prefix-len": 72
                }
            ]
        }
    ]
}
</screen>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-std-options">
      <title>Standard DHCPv6 Options</title>
      <para>
        One of the major features of a DHCPv6 server is the ability to provide configuration
        options to clients. Although there are several options that require
        special behavior, most options are sent by the server only if the client
        explicitly requests them. The following example shows how to
        configure one of the most frequently used options, which supplies the
        address of DNS servers. Options specified in this way are considered
        global and apply to all configured subnets.

        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        {
           <userinput>"name": "dns-servers",
           "code": 23,
           "space": "dhcp6",
           "csv-format": true,
           "data": "2001:db8::cafe, 2001:db8::babe"</userinput>
        },
        ...
    ]
}
</screen>
      </para>

    <para>
      The <command>option-data</command> line creates a new entry in
      the option-data table. This table contains
      information on all global options that the server is supposed to configure
      in all subnets. The <command>name</command> line specifies the option name.
      (For a complete list
      of currently supported names, see <xref linkend="dhcp6-std-options-list"/>.) The next line specifies the option code,
      which must match one of the values from that list. The line beginning with
      <command>space</command> specifies the option space, which must always be set
      to "dhcp6" as these are standard DHCPv6 options. For other name spaces,
      including custom option spaces, see <xref linkend="dhcp6-option-spaces"/>. The following line specifies the format in
      which the data will be entered; use of CSV (comma-separated values) is
      recommended. Finally, the <command>data</command> line gives the actual value to be sent to
      clients. Data is specified as normal text, with values separated by
      commas if more than one value is allowed.
    </para>

    <para>
      Options can also be configured as hexadecimal values. If "csv-format" is
      set to false, the option data must be specified as a hexadecimal string.
      The following commands configure the DNS-SERVERS option for all
      subnets with the following addresses: 2001:db8:1::cafe and
      2001:db8:1::babe.
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        {
           <userinput>"name": "dns-servers",
           "code": 23,
           "space": "dhcp6",
           "csv-format": false,
           "data": "2001 0DB8 0001 0000 0000 0000 0000 CAFE
                    2001 0DB8 0001 0000 0000 0000 0000 BABE"</userinput>
        },
        ...
    ]
}
        </screen>
       </para>
       <note><para>
       The value for the setting of the "data" element is split across two
       lines in this example for clarity; when entering the command, the
       whole string should be entered on the same line.
       </para></note>
       <para>
       Care should be taken
       to use proper encoding when using hexadecimal format as Kea's ability
       to validate data correctness in hexadecimal is limited.
      </para>

      <para>
        Most of the parameters in the "option-data" structure are
        optional and can be omitted in some circumstances as discussed
        in <xref linkend="dhcp6-option-data-defaults"/>. Only one
        of name or code is required; you don't need to specify
        both. Space has a default value of "dhcp6", so you can skip
        this as well if you define a regular (not encapsulated) DHCPv6
        option. Finally, csv-format defaults to true, so it too can
        be skipped, unless you want to specify the option value as
        hexstring. Therefore the above example can be simplified to:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        {
           <userinput>"name": "dns-servers",
           "data": "2001:db8::cafe, 2001:db8::babe"</userinput>
        },
        ...
    ]
}
        </screen>
        Defined options are added to the response when the client requests them,
        as well as any options required by a protocol. An administrator
        can also specify that an option is always sent, even if a
        client did not specifically request it. To enforce the addition
        of a particular option, set the "always-send" flag to true as in:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        {
           <userinput>"name": "dns-servers",
           "data": "2001:db8::cafe, 2001:db8::babe",
           "always-send": true</userinput>
        },
        ...
    ]
}
        </screen>
        The effect is the same as if the client added the option code in the
        Option Request Option (or its equivalent for vendor options) so in:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        {
           <userinput>"name": "dns-servers",
           "data": "2001:db8::cafe, 2001:db8::babe",
           "always-send": true</userinput>
        },
        ...
    ],
    "subnet6": [
        {
           "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
           "option-data": [
               {
                   <userinput>"name": "dns-servers",
                   "data": "2001:db8:1::cafe, 2001:db8:1::babe"</userinput>
               },
               ...
           ],
           ...
        },
        ...
    ],
    ...
}
        </screen>
        The DNS servers option is always added to responses
        (the always-send is "sticky") but the value is the subnet one
        when the client is localized in the subnet.
      </para>

    <para>
      It is possible to override options on a per-subnet basis. If
      clients connected to most of your subnets are expected to get the
      same values of a given option, you should use global options; you
      can then override specific values for a small number of subnets.
      On the other hand, if you use different values in each subnet,
      it does not make sense to specify global option values; rather, you should
      set only subnet-specific ones.
     </para>

     <para>
      The following commands override the global
      DNS servers option for a particular subnet, setting a single DNS
      server with address 2001:db8:1::3.
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            <userinput>"option-data": [
                {
                    "name": "dns-servers",
                    "code": 23,
                    "space": "dhcp6",
                    "csv-format": true,
                    "data": "2001:db8:1::3"
                },
                ...
            ]</userinput>,
            ...
        },
        ...
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
    </para>

     <para>
       In some cases it is useful to associate some options with an
       address or prefix pool from which a client is assigned a lease. Pool-
       specific option values override subnet-specific and global option
       values. If the client is assigned multiple leases from different
       pools, the server will assign options from all pools from which the
       leases have been obtained. However, if the particular option is specified
       in multiple pools from which the client obtains the leases, only one
       instance of this option will be handed out to the client. The server's
       administrator must not try to prioritize assignment of pool-specific
       options by trying to order pools declarations in the server
       configuration.
     </para>

     <para>
       The following configuration snippet demonstrates how to specify the
       DNS servers option, which will be assigned to a client only if the
       client obtains an address from the given pool:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "pools": [
                {
                    "pool": "2001:db8:1::100-2001:db8:1::300",
                    <userinput>"option-data": [
                        {
                            "name": "dns-servers",
                            "data": "2001:db8:1::10"
                        }
                    ]</userinput>
                }
            ]
        },
        ...
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
     </para>
    <para>
      Options can also be specified in a class of host reservation scope.
      The current Kea options precedence order is (from most important):
      host reservation, pool, subnet, shared network, class, global.
    </para>
    <para>
      The currently supported standard DHCPv6 options are
      listed in <xref linkend="dhcp6-std-options-list"/>.
      "Name" and "Code"
      are the values that should be used as a name/code in the option-data
      structures. "Type" designates the format of the data; the meanings of
      the various types is given in <xref linkend="dhcp-types"/>.
    </para>
    <para>When a data field is a string, and that string contains
    the comma (,; U+002C) character, the comma must be escaped with double
    backslashes (\; U+005C). This double escape is
    required, because both the routine splitting CSV data into fields
    and JSON use the same escape character; a single escape (\,) would
    make the JSON invalid. For example, the string
    "EST5EDT4,M3.2.0/02:00,M11.1.0/02:00" would be
    represented as:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "pools": [
                {
                    <userinput>"option-data": [
                        {
                            "name": "new-posix-timezone",
                            "data": "EST5EDT4\\,M3.2.0/02:00\\,M11.1.0/02:00"
                        }
                    ]</userinput>
                },
                ...
            ],
            ...
        },
        ...
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Some options are designated as arrays, which means that more than one
      value is allowed in such an option. For example, the option dns-servers
      allows the specification of more than one IPv6 address, enabling
      clients to obtain the addresses of multiple DNS servers.
    </para>

<!-- @todo: describe record types -->
<!-- @todo: describe array in record types -->

      <para>
        <xref linkend="dhcp6-custom-options"/> describes the configuration
        syntax to create custom option definitions (formats). Creation of custom
        definitions for standard options is generally not permitted, even if the
        definition being created matches the actual option format defined in the
        RFCs. There is an exception to this rule for standard options for which
        Kea currently does not provide a definition. In order to use such options,
        a server administrator must create a definition as described in
        <xref linkend="dhcp6-custom-options"/> in the 'dhcp6' option space. This
        definition should match the option format described in the relevant
        RFC, but the configuration mechanism would allow any option format as it
        currently has no means to validate it.
      </para>

    <para>
      <table frame="all" xml:id="dhcp6-std-options-list">
        <title>List of Standard DHCPv6 Options</title>
        <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec colname="name"/>
        <colspec colname="code" align="center"/>
        <colspec colname="type" align="center"/>
        <colspec colname="array" align="center"/>
        <thead>
          <row><entry>Name</entry><entry>Code</entry><entry>Type</entry><entry>Array?</entry></row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
<!-- Our engine uses those options on its own, admins must not configure them on their own.
<row><entry>clientid</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>serverid</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>ia-na</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>record</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>ia-ta</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>uint32</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>iaaddr</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>record</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>oro</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>uint16</entry><entry>true</entry></row> -->
<row><entry>preference</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>uint8</entry><entry>false</entry></row>

<!-- Our engine uses those options on its own, admins must not configure them on their own.
<row><entry>elapsed-time</entry><entry>8</entry><entry>uint16</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>relay-msg</entry><entry>9</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>auth</entry><entry>11</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
-->
<row><entry>unicast</entry><entry>12</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<!--
<row><entry>status-code</entry><entry>13</entry><entry>record</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>rapid-commit</entry><entry>14</entry><entry>empty</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>user-class</entry><entry>15</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>vendor-class</entry><entry>16</entry><entry>record</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
-->
<!-- Vendor-specific information is configurable by the administrator. -->
<row><entry>vendor-opts</entry><entry>17</entry><entry>uint32</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<!--
<row><entry>interface-id</entry><entry>18</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>reconf-msg</entry><entry>19</entry><entry>uint8</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>reconf-accept</entry><entry>20</entry><entry>empty</entry><entry>false</entry></row> -->
--&gt;
<row><entry>sip-server-dns</entry><entry>21</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>sip-server-addr</entry><entry>22</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>dns-servers</entry><entry>23</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>domain-search</entry><entry>24</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<!-- <row><entry>ia-pd</entry><entry>25</entry><entry>record</entry><entry>false</entry></row> -->
<!-- <row><entry>iaprefix</entry><entry>26</entry><entry>record</entry><entry>false</entry></row> -->
<row><entry>nis-servers</entry><entry>27</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>nisp-servers</entry><entry>28</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>nis-domain-name</entry><entry>29</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>nisp-domain-name</entry><entry>30</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>sntp-servers</entry><entry>31</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>information-refresh-time</entry><entry>32</entry><entry>uint32</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>bcmcs-server-dns</entry><entry>33</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>bcmcs-server-addr</entry><entry>34</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>geoconf-civic</entry><entry>36</entry><entry>record (uint8, uint16, binary)</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>remote-id</entry><entry>37</entry><entry>record (uint32, binary)</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>subscriber-id</entry><entry>38</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>client-fqdn</entry><entry>39</entry><entry>record (uint8, fqdn)</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>pana-agent</entry><entry>40</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>new-posix-timezone</entry><entry>41</entry><entry>string</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>new-tzdb-timezone</entry><entry>42</entry><entry>string</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>ero</entry><entry>43</entry><entry>uint16</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>lq-query (1)</entry><entry>44</entry><entry>record (uint8, ipv6-address)</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>client-data (1)</entry><entry>45</entry><entry>empty</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>clt-time (1)</entry><entry>46</entry><entry>uint32</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>lq-relay-data (1)</entry><entry>47</entry><entry>record (ipv6-address, binary)</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>lq-client-link (1)</entry><entry>48</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>v6-lost</entry><entry>51</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>capwap-ac-v6</entry><entry>52</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>relay-id</entry><entry>53</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>v6-access-domain</entry><entry>57</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>sip-ua-cs-list</entry><entry>58</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>bootfile-url</entry><entry>59</entry><entry>string</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>bootfile-param</entry><entry>60</entry><entry>tuple</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>client-arch-type</entry><entry>61</entry><entry>uint16</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>nii</entry><entry>62</entry><entry>record (uint8, uint8, uint8)</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>aftr-name</entry><entry>64</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>erp-local-domain-name</entry><entry>65</entry><entry>fqdn</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>rsoo</entry><entry>66</entry><entry>empty</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>pd-exclude</entry><entry>67</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>rdnss-selection</entry><entry>74</entry><entry>record (ipv6-address, uint8, fqdn)</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>client-linklayer-addr</entry><entry>79</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>link-address</entry><entry>80</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>solmax-rt</entry><entry>82</entry><entry>uint32</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>inf-max-rt</entry><entry>83</entry><entry>uint32</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<!-- <row><entry>dhcpv4-message</entry><entry>87</entry><entry>binary</entry><entry>false</entry></row> -->
<row><entry>dhcp4o6-server-addr</entry><entry>88</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
<row><entry>s46-rule</entry><entry>89</entry><entry>record (uint8, uint8, uint8, ipv4-address, ipv6-prefix)</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>s46-br</entry><entry>90</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>s46-dmr</entry><entry>91</entry><entry>ipv6-prefix</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>s46-v4v6bind</entry><entry>92</entry><entry>record (ipv4-address, ipv6-prefix)</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>s46-portparams</entry><entry>93</entry><entry>record(uint8, psid)</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>s46-cont-mape</entry><entry>94</entry><entry>empty</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>s46-cont-mapt</entry><entry>95</entry><entry>empty</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>s46-cont-lw</entry><entry>96</entry><entry>empty</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>v6-captive-portal</entry><entry>103</entry><entry>string</entry><entry>false</entry></row>
<row><entry>ipv6-address-andsf</entry><entry>143</entry><entry>ipv6-address</entry><entry>true</entry></row>
        </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      Options marked with (1) have option definitions, but the logic
      behind them is not implemented. That means that technically Kea
      knows how to parse them in incoming messages or how to send them
      if configured to do so, but not what to do with them. Since the
      related RFCs require certain processing, the support for those
      options is non-functional. However, it may be useful in some
      limited lab testing; hence the definition formats are listed here.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section id="s46-options">
      <title>Common Softwire46 Options</title>
      <para>
        Softwire46 options are involved in IPv4 over IPv6 provisioning by
        means of tunneling or translation as specified in
        <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7598">RFC 7598</ulink>.
        The following sections provide configuration examples of these
        options.
      </para>

      <section id="s46-containers">
      <title>Softwire46 Container Options</title>
      <para>
        S46 container options group rules and optional port parameters
        for a specified domain. There are three container options specified
        in the "dhcp6" (top-level) option space: the MAP-E Container option,
        the MAP-T Container option, and the S46 Lightweight 4over6 Container option.
        These options only contain encapsulated options specified below;
        they do not include any data fields.
      </para>

      <para>
        To configure the server to send a specific container option
        along with all encapsulated options, the container option must be
        included in the server configuration as shown below:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    ...
    "option-data": [
        {
            "name": "s46-cont-mape"
        } ],
    ...
}
</screen>

        This configuration will cause the server to include the MAP-E Container
        option to the client. Use "s46-cont-mapt" or "s46-cont-lw" for the
        MAP-T Container and S46 Lightweight 4over6 Container options,
        respectively.
      </para>

      <para>
        All remaining Softwire options described below are included in one
        of the container options. Thus, they have to be included in appropriate
        option spaces by selecting a "space" name, which specifies in which
        option they are supposed to be included.
      </para>
    </section>

      <section>
        <title>S46 Rule Option</title>
        <para>
          The S46 Rule option is used for conveying the Basic Mapping Rule (BMR)
          and Forwarding Mapping Rule (FMR).
<screen>
{
    "space": "s46-cont-mape-options",
    "name": "s46-rule",
    "data": "128, 0, 24, 192.0.2.0, 2001:db8:1::/64"
}
</screen>
         Another possible "space" value is "s46-cont-mapt-options".
        </para>

        <para>
          The S46 Rule option conveys a number of parameters:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>flags</command>, an unsigned 8-bit integer, with
          currently only the most-significant bit specified. It denotes whether
          the rule can be used for forwarding (128) or not (0).
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>ea-len</command>, an 8-bit-long Embedded Address length. Allowed values
          range from 0 to 48.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>IPv4 prefix length</command>, 8 bits long; expresses the prefix length of the
          Rule IPv4 prefix specified in the ipv4-prefix field. Allowed
          values range from 0 to 32.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>IPv4 prefix</command>, a fixed-length 32-bit field that specifies the IPv4
          prefix for the S46 rule. The bits in the prefix after prefix4-len
          number of bits are reserved, and MUST be initialized to zero by the
          sender and ignored by the receiver.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>IPv6 prefix</command>, in prefix/length notation that specifies the IPv6 domain
          prefix for the S46 rule. The field is padded on the right with zero
          bits up to the nearest octet boundary, when prefix6-len is not evenly
          divisible by 8.</simpara>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
        <section>
            <title>S46 BR Option</title>
            <para>
              The S46 BR option is used to convey the IPv6 address of the
              Border Relay. This option is mandatory in the MAP-E
              Container option and is not permitted in the MAP-T and
              S46 Lightweight 4over6 Container options.
<screen>
{
    "space": "s46-cont-mape-options",
    "name": "s46-br",
    "data": "2001:db8:cafe::1",
}
</screen>
           Another possible "space" value is "s46-cont-lw-options".
          </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>S46 DMR Option</title>
            <para>
              The S46 DMR option is used to convey values for the Default
              Mapping Rule (DMR). This option is mandatory in the MAP-T
              container option and is not permitted in the MAP-E and S46
              Lightweight 4over6 Container options.
<screen>
{
    "space": "s46-cont-mapt-options",
    "name": "s46-dmr",
    "data": "2001:db8:cafe::/64",
}
</screen>
              This option must not be included in other containers.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>S46 IPv4/IPv6 Address Binding option.</title>
            <para>
              The S46 IPv4/IPv6 Address Binding option may be used to specify
              the full or shared IPv4 address of the Customer Edge (CE).
              The IPv6 prefix field is used by the CE to identify the
              correct prefix to use for the tunnel source.
<screen>
{
    "space": "s46-cont-lw",
    "name": "s46-v4v6bind",
    "data": "192.0.2.3, 2001:db8:1:cafe::/64"
}
</screen>
            This option must not be included in other containers.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>S46 Port Parameters</title>
            <para>
              The S46 Port Parameters option specifies optional port-set
              information that MAY be provided to CEs.
<screen>
{
    "space": "s46-rule-options",
    "name": "s46-portparams",
    "data": "2, 3/4",
}
</screen>
              Another possible "space" value is "s46-v4v6bind", to include
              this option in the S46 IPv4/IPv6 Address Binding option.
            </para>
            <para>
              Note that the second value in the example above specifies the
              PSID and PSID-length fields in the format of PSID/PSID length.
              This is equivalent to the values of PSID-len=4 and
              PSID=12288 conveyed in the S46 Port Parameters option.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-custom-options">
      <title>Custom DHCPv6 Options</title>
      <para>It is possible to define options in addition to the standard ones.
      Assume that we want to define a new DHCPv6 option called "foo" which will have
      code 100 and which will convey a single, unsigned, 32-bit integer value. We can define
      such an option by using the following commands:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-def": [
        {
            <userinput>"name": "foo",
            "code": 100,
            "type": "uint32",
            "array": false,
            "record-types": "",
            "space": "dhcp6",
            "encapsulate": ""</userinput>
        }, ...
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
      The "false" value of the <command>array</command> parameter determines that the option does
      NOT comprise an array of "uint32" values but is, instead, a single value. Two
      other parameters have been left blank: <command>record-types</command> and
      <command>encapsulate</command>.
      The former specifies the comma-separated list of option data fields, if the
      option comprises a record of data fields. The <command>record-types</command> value should
      be non-empty if <command>type</command> is set to "record"; otherwise it must be left
      blank. The latter parameter specifies the name of the option space being
      encapsulated by the particular option. If the particular option does not
      encapsulate any option space, it should be left blank.  Note that the above
      example only defines the format of the new option and does not set its
      value(s).
      </para>

      <para>Only the <command>name</command>, <command>code</command>, and
      <command>type</command> parameters are required; all others are
      optional. The <command>array</command> default value is
      <command>false</command>. The <command>record-types</command>
      and <command>encapsulate</command> default values are blank
      (i.e. ""). The default <command>space</command> is "dhcp6".
      </para>

      <para>Once the new option format is defined, its value is set
      in the same way as for a standard option. For example, the following
      commands set a global value that applies to all subnets.
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        {
            <userinput>"name": "foo",
            "code": 100,
            "space": "dhcp6",
            "csv-format": true,
            "data": "12345"</userinput>
        }, ...
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
      </para>

      <para>New options can take more complex forms than simple use of
      primitives (uint8, string, ipv6-address, etc); it is possible to
      define an option comprising a number of existing primitives.
      </para>
      <para>
      For example, assume we want to define a new option that will consist of an IPv6
      address, followed by an unsigned 16-bit integer, followed by a
      boolean value, followed by a text string. Such an option could
      be defined in the following way:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-def": [
        {
            <userinput>"name": "bar",
            "code": 101,
            "space": "dhcp6",
            "type": "record",
            "array": false,
            "record-types": "ipv6-address, uint16, boolean, string",
            "encapsulate": ""</userinput>
        }, ...
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
      The "type" is set to "record" to indicate that the option contains
      multiple values of different types. These types are given as a comma-separated
      list in the <command>record-types</command> field and should be ones from those listed in <xref linkend="dhcp-types"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
      The values of the options are set in a <command>option-data</command> statement as follows:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        {
            <userinput>"name": "bar",
            "space": "dhcp6",
            "code": 101,
            "csv-format": true,
            "data": "2001:db8:1::10, 123, false, Hello World"</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}</screen>

      <command>csv-format</command> is set to <command>true</command> to indicate
      that the <command>data</command> field comprises a command-separated list
      of values. The values in <command>data</command> must correspond to the types set in
      the <command>record-types</command> field of the option definition.
      </para>

      <para>
      When <command>array</command> is set to <command>true</command>
      and <command>type</command> is set to "record", the last field
      is an array, i.e. it can contain more than one value, as in:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-def": [
        {
            <userinput>"name": "bar",
            "code": 101,
            "space": "dhcp6",
            "type": "record",
            "array": true,
            "record-types": "ipv6-address, uint16",
            "encapsulate": ""</userinput>
        }, ...
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
      The new option content is one IPv6 address followed by one or more 16-
      bit unsigned integers.
      </para>

      <note>
       <para>In general, boolean values are specified as <command>true</command> or
       <command>false</command>, without quotes. Some specific boolean parameters may
       accept also <command>"true"</command>, <command>"false"</command>,
       <command>0</command>, <command>1</command>, <command>"0"</command>, and
       <command>"1"</command>.</para>
      </note>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-vendor-opts">
      <title>DHCPv6 Vendor-Specific Options</title>
      <para>
      Currently there are two option spaces defined for the DHCPv6
      daemon: "dhcp6" (for top-level DHCPv6 options) and "vendor-opts-space",
      which is empty by default, but in which options can be defined.
      Those options are carried in the Vendor-Specific
      Information option (code 17). The following examples show how to
      define an option "foo" with code 1 that consists of an IPv6 address,
      an unsigned 16-bit integer, and a string. The "foo" option is
      conveyed in a Vendor-Specific Information option, which
      comprises a single uint32 value that is set to "12345".
      The sub-option "foo" follows the data field holding this value.
      <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-def": [
        {
            <userinput>"name": "foo",
            "code": 1,
            "space": "vendor-opts-space",
            "type": "record",
            "array": false,
            "record-types": "ipv6-address, uint16, string",
            "encapsulate": ""</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}</screen>
     (Note that the option space is set to <command>vendor-opts-space</command>.)
     Once the option format is defined, the next step is to define actual values
     for that option:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        {
            <userinput>"name": "foo",
            "space": "vendor-opts-space",
            "data": "2001:db8:1::10, 123, Hello World"</userinput>
        },
        ...
    ],
    ...
}</screen>
    We should also define a value (enterprise-number) for the
    Vendor-Specific Information option, that conveys our option "foo".
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        ...,
        {
            <userinput>"name": "vendor-opts",
            "data": "12345"</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}</screen>
    Alternatively, the option can be specified using its code.
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        ...,
        {
            <userinput>"code": 17,
            "data": "12345"</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}</screen>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-option-spaces">
      <title>Nested DHCPv6 Options (Custom Option Spaces)</title>
      <para>It is sometimes useful to define completely new option
      spaces. This is the case when a user wants their new option to
      convey sub-options that use a separate numbering scheme, for
      example sub-options with codes 1 and 2. Those option codes
      conflict with standard DHCPv6 options, so a separate option
      space must be defined.
      </para>
      <para>Note that the creation of a new option space is not required when
      defining sub-options for a standard option, because it is
      created by default if the standard option is meant to convey
      any sub-options (see <xref linkend="dhcp6-vendor-opts"/>).
      </para>
      <para>
      Assume that we want to have a DHCPv6 option called "container"
      with code 102 that conveys two sub-options with codes 1 and 2.
      First we need to define the new sub-options:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-def": [
        {
            <userinput>"name": "subopt1",
            "code": 1,
            "space": "isc",
            "type": "ipv6-address",
            "record-types": "",
            "array": false,
            "encapsulate": ""</userinput>
        },
        {
            <userinput>"name": "subopt2",
            "code": 2,
            "space": "isc",
            "type": "string",
            "record-types": "",
            "array": false
            "encapsulate": ""</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}</screen>
    Note that we have defined the options to belong to a new option space
    (in this case, "isc").
    </para>
    <para>
The next step is to define a regular DHCPv6 option and specify that it
should include options from the new option space:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-def": [
        ...,
        {
            <userinput>"name": "container",
            "code": 102,
            "space": "dhcp6",
            "type": "empty",
            "array": false,
            "record-types": "",
            "encapsulate": "isc"</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}</screen>

    The name of the option space in which the sub-options are defined is set in
    the <command>encapsulate</command> field. The <command>type</command> field
    is set to <command>empty</command>, which limits this option to only carrying
    data in sub-options.
    </para>
    <para>
    Finally, we can set values for the new options:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "option-data": [
        {
            <userinput>"name": "subopt1",
            "code": 1,
            "space": "isc",
            "data": "2001:db8::abcd"</userinput>
        },
        }
            <userinput>"name": "subopt2",
            "code": 2,
            "space": "isc",
            "data": "Hello world"</userinput>
        },
        {
            <userinput>"name": "container",
            "code": 102,
            "space": "dhcp6"</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
    </para>

    <para>Note that it is possible to create an option which carries some data
    in addition to the sub-options defined in the encapsulated option space.
    For example, if the "container" option from the previous example were
    required to carry a uint16 value as well as the sub-options, the <command>type</command>
    value would have to be set to "uint16" in the option definition. (Such an
    option would then have the following data structure: DHCP header, uint16
    value, sub-options.) The value specified with the <command>data</command> parameter — which
    should be a valid integer enclosed in quotes, e.g. "123" — would then be
    assigned to the uint16 field in the "container" option.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-option-data-defaults">
      <title>Unspecified Parameters for DHCPv6 Option Configuration</title>
      <para>In many cases it is not required to specify all parameters for
      an option configuration and the default values can be used. However, it is
      important to understand the implications of not specifying some of them,
      as it may result in configuration errors. The list below explains
      the behavior of the server when a particular parameter is not explicitly
      specified:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>name</command> - the server requires an option name or
          option code to identify an option. If this parameter is unspecified, the
          option code must be specified.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>code</command> - the server requires an option name or
          option code to identify an option. This parameter may be left unspecified if
          the <command>name</command> parameter is specified. However, this also
          requires that the particular option have a definition (either as a
          standard option or an administrator-created definition for the option
          using an 'option-def' structure), as the option definition associates an
          option with a particular name. It is possible to configure an option
          for which there is no definition (unspecified option format).
          Configuration of such options requires the use of the option code.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>space</command> - if the option space is unspecified it
          will default to 'dhcp6', which is an option space holding standard DHCPv6
          options.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>data</command> - if the option data is unspecified it
          defaults to an empty value. The empty value is mostly used for the
          options which have no payload (boolean options), but it is legal to specify
          empty values for some options which carry variable-length data and which
          the specification allows a length of 0. For such options, the data parameter
          may be omitted in the configuration.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><command>csv-format</command> - if this value is not
          specified the server will assume that the option data is specified as
          a list of comma-separated values to be assigned to individual fields
          of the DHCP option.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-config-subnets">
      <title>IPv6 Subnet Selection</title>
      <para>
        The DHCPv6 server may receive requests from local (connected to the
        same subnet as the server) and remote (connected via relays) clients.
        As the server may have many subnet configurations defined, it must select
        an appropriate subnet for a given request.
      </para>
      <para>
        In IPv4, the server can determine which of the configured subnets are local, 
        as there is a reasonable expectation that the
        server will have a (global) IPv4 address configured on the interface,
        and it can use that information to detect whether a subnet is local.
        That assumption is not true in IPv6; the DHCPv6 server must be able
        to operate while only using link-local addresses. Therefore, an optional
        <command>interface</command> parameter is available within a subnet definition
        to designate that a given subnet is local, i.e. reachable directly over
        the specified interface. For example, the server that is intended to serve
        a local subnet over eth0 may be configured as follows:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:beef::/48",
            "pools": [
                 {
                     "pool": "2001:db8:beef::/48"
                 }
             ],
            <userinput>"interface": "eth0"</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
        </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dhcp6-rapid-commit">
        <title>Rapid Commit</title>
        <para>The Rapid Commit option, described in
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link>, is supported
        by the Kea DHCPv6 server. However, support is disabled by default. It can be enabled on a per-subnet basis using the
        <command>rapid-commit</command> parameter as shown below:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:beef::/48",
            <userinput>"rapid-commit": true</userinput>,
            "pools": [
                 {
                     "pool": "2001:db8:beef::1-2001:db8:beef::10"
                 }
             ],
        }
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
          This setting only affects the subnet for which the
          <command>rapid-commit</command> is set to <command>true</command>.
          For clients connected to other subnets, the server will ignore the
          Rapid Commit option sent by the client and will follow the 4-way
          exchange procedure, i.e. respond with an Advertise for a Solicit
          containing a Rapid Commit option.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dhcp6-relays">
        <title>DHCPv6 Relays</title>
        <para>
          A DHCPv6 server with multiple subnets defined must select the
          appropriate subnet when it receives a request from a client. For clients
          connected via relays, two mechanisms are used:
        </para>
        <para>
          The first uses the linkaddr field in the RELAY_FORW message. The name
          of this field is somewhat misleading in that it does not contain a link-layer
          address; instead, it holds an address (typically a global address) that is
          used to identify a link. The DHCPv6 server checks to see whether the address belongs
          to a defined subnet and, if it does, that subnet is selected for the client's
          request.
        </para>
        <para>
          The second mechanism is based on interface-id options. While forwarding a client's
          message, relays may insert an interface-id option into the message that
          identifies the interface on the relay that received the message. (Some
          relays allow configuration of that parameter, but it is sometimes
          hardcoded and may range from the very simple (e.g. "vlan100") to the very cryptic;
          one example seen on real hardware was "ISAM144|299|ipv6|nt:vp:1:110"). The
          server can use this information to select the appropriate subnet.
          The information is also returned to the relay, which then knows the
          interface to use to transmit the response to the client. For
          this to work successfully, the relay interface IDs must be unique within
          the network and the server configuration must match those values.
        </para>
        <para>
          When configuring the DHCPv6 server, it should be noted that two
          similarly named parameters can be configured for a subnet:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><simpara>
              <command>interface</command> defines which local network interface can be used
              to access a given subnet.
            </simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>
              <command>interface-id</command> specifies the content of the interface-id option
              used by relays to identify the interface on the relay to which
              the response packet is sent.
            </simpara></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          The two are mutually exclusive; a subnet cannot be reachable both locally
          (direct traffic) and via relays (remote traffic). Specifying both is a
          configuration error and the DHCPv6 server will refuse such a configuration.
        </para>

        <para>
          The following example configuration shows how to specify an interface-id with
          a value of "vlan123":
          <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:beef::/48",
            "pools": [
                 {
                     "pool": "2001:db8:beef::/48"
                 }
             ],
            <userinput>"interface-id": "vlan123"</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
        </para>
      </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-rsoo">
      <title>Relay-Supplied Options</title>
      <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6422">RFC 6422</link>
      defines a mechanism called Relay-Supplied DHCP Options. In certain cases relay
      agents are the only entities that may have specific information, and they can
      insert options when relaying messages from the client to the server. The
      server will then do certain checks and copy those options to the response
      sent to the client.</para>

      <para>There are certain conditions that must be met for the option to be
      included. First, the server must not provide the option itself; in
      other words, if both relay and server provide an option, the server always
      takes precedence. Second, the option must be RSOO-enabled. (RSOO is the "Relay Supplied Options option.") IANA maintains a
      list of RSOO-enabled options <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/dhcpv6-parameters/dhcpv6-parameters.xhtml#options-relay-supplied">here</link>.
      However, there may be cases when system administrators want to echo other
      options. Kea can be instructed to treat other options as RSOO-enabled.
      For example, to mark options 110, 120, and 130 as RSOO-enabled, the following
      syntax should be used:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    <userinput>"relay-supplied-options": [ "110", "120", "130" ],</userinput>
    ...
}
</screen>
      </para>
      <para>As of February 2019, only option 65 is RSOO-enabled by IANA. This
      option will always be treated as such, so there is no need to explicitly
      mark it. Also, when enabling standard options, it is possible to use their
      names, rather than option code, e.g. use
      <command>dns-servers</command> instead of <command>23</command>. See
      <xref linkend="dhcp6-std-options-list"/> for the names. In certain cases
      it could also work for custom options, but due to the nature of the parser
      code this may be unreliable and should be avoided.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-client-classifier">
      <title>Client Classification in DHCPv6</title>
      <para>
      The DHCPv6 server includes support for client classification.  For a deeper
      discussion of the classification process see <xref linkend="classify"/>.
      </para>

      <para>
      In certain cases it is useful to configure the server to differentiate between
      DHCP client types and treat them accordingly. Client
      classification can be used to modify the behavior of almost any part of
      the DHCP message processing. In the current release of Kea, there are three
      mechanisms that take advantage of client classification in DHCPv6: subnet
      selection, address pool selection, and DHCP options assignment.
      </para>

      <para>
      Kea can be instructed to limit access to given subnets based on class information.
      This is particularly useful for cases where two types of devices share the
      same link and are expected to be served from two different subnets. The
      primary use case for such a scenario is cable networks, where there are two
      classes of devices: the cable modem itself, which should be handed a lease
      from subnet A; and all other devices behind the modem, which should get a lease
      from subnet B. That segregation is essential to prevent overly curious
      users from playing with their cable modems. For details on how to set up
      class restrictions on subnets, see <xref linkend="classification-subnets"/>.
      </para>

      <para>
      When subnets belong to a shared network, the classification applies
      to subnet selection but not to pools, e.g., a pool in a subnet
      limited to a particular class can still be used by clients which do not
      belong to the class, if the pool they are expected to use is exhausted.
      So the limit on access based on class information is also available
      at the address/prefix pool level; see <xref
      linkend="classification-pools"/>, within a subnet.
      This is useful when segregating clients belonging to the same subnet
      into different address ranges.
      </para>

      <para>
      In a similar way, a pool can be constrained to serve only known
      clients, i.e. clients which have a reservation, using the
      built-in "KNOWN" or "UNKNOWN" classes. One can assign addresses
      to registered clients without giving a different address per
      reservation, for instance when there are not enough available
      addresses. The determination whether there is a reservation
      for a given client is made after a subnet is selected, so it
      is not possible to use KNOWN/UNKNOWN classes to select a shared
      network or a subnet.
      </para>

      <para>
      The process of classification is conducted in five steps.
      The first step is to assess an incoming packet and assign it to
      zero or more classes.
      Next, a subnet is chosen, possibly based on the
      class information.
      After that, class expressions are evaluated depending on the
      built-in "KNOWN"/"UNKNOWN" classes after host reservation lookup,
      using them for pool/pd-pool selection and assigning classes from host
      reservations.
      The list of required classes is then built and each class of the list
      has its expression evaluated; when it returns "true" the packet is added
      as a member of the class.
      Finally, options are assigned, again possibly based on the class
      information.
      More complete and detailed information is available in
      <xref linkend="classify"/>.
      </para>

      <para>
      There are two main methods of classification. The first is automatic and relies
      on examining the values in the vendor class options or the existence of a
      host reservation. Information from these
      options is extracted, and a class name is constructed from it and added to
      the class list for the packet. The second specifies an expression
      that is evaluated for each packet. If the result is "true", the packet is
      a member of the class.
      </para>

      <note><para>
        Care should be taken with client classification, as it is easy for
        clients that do not meet class criteria to be denied all service.
      </para></note>

      <section>
        <title>Defining and Using Custom Classes</title>
        <para>
        The following example shows how to configure a class using an expression
        and a subnet using that class. This configuration defines the
        class named "Client_enterprise". It is comprised
        of all clients whose client identifiers start with the given hex string (which
        would indicate a DUID based on an enterprise id of 0xAABBCCDD).
        They will be given an address from 2001:db8:1::0 to 2001:db8:1::FFFF and
        the addresses of their DNS servers set to 2001:db8:0::1 and 2001:db8:2::1.

        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "client-classes": [
        {<userinput>
            "name": "Client_enterprise",
            "test": "substring(option[1].hex,0,6) == 0x0002AABBCCDD'",
            "option-data": [
                {
                    "name": "dns-servers",
                    "code": 23,
                    "space": "dhcp6",
                    "csv-format": true,
                    "data": "2001:db8:0::1, 2001:db8:2::1"
                }
            ]</userinput>
        },
        ...
    ],
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
            "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1::-2001:db8:1::ffff" } ],
            <userinput>"client-class": "Client_enterprise"</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}</screen>
      </para>

      <para>
      This example shows a configuration using an automatically generated
      "VENDOR_CLASS_" class. The administrator of the network has
      decided that addresses in the range 2001:db8:1::1 to 2001:db8:1::ffff are
      to be managed by the DHCP6 server and that only clients belonging to the
      eRouter1.0 client class are allowed to use that pool.

        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
            "pools": [
                 {
                     "pool": "2001:db8:1::-2001:db8:1::ffff"
                 }
             ],
            <userinput>"client-class": "VENDOR_CLASS_eRouter1.0"</userinput>
        }
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="dhcp6-required-class">
        <title>Required Classification</title>
        <para>
        In some cases it is useful to limit the scope of a class to
        a shared-network, subnet, or pool. There are two parameters
        which are used to limit the scope of the class by instructing
        the server to perform evaluation of test expressions when
        required.
        </para>

        <para>
        The first one is the per-class <command>only-if-required</command>
        flag which is false by default. When it is set to
        <command>true</command>, the test expression of the class is not
        evaluated at the reception of the incoming packet but later, and
        only if the class evaluation is required.
        </para>

        <para>
        The second is <command>require-client-classes</command>, which
        takes a list of class names and is valid in shared-network,
        subnet, and pool scope. Classes in these lists are marked as
        required and evaluated after selection of this specific
        shared-network/subnet/pool and before output option processing.
        </para>

        <para>
        In this example, a class is assigned to the incoming packet
        when the specified subnet is used:

        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "client-classes": [
       {<userinput>
           "name": "Client_foo",
           "test": "member('ALL')",
           "only-if-required": true</userinput>
       },
       ...
    ],
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64"
            "pools": [
                 {
                     "pool": "2001:db8:1::-2001:db8:1::ffff"
                 }
             ],
            <userinput>"require-client-classes": [ "Client_foo" ],</userinput>
            ...
        },
        ...
    ],
    ...
}</screen>
         </para>

         <para>
         Required evaluation can be used to express complex dependencies,
         for example, subnet membership. It can also be used to reverse the
         precedence; if you set an option-data in a subnet it takes
         precedence over an option-data in a class. When you move the
         option-data to a required class and require it in
         the subnet, a class evaluated earlier may take precedence.
         </para>

         <para>
         Required evaluation is also available at shared-network and
         pool/pd-pool levels. The order in which required classes are
         considered is: shared-network, subnet, and (pd-)pool, i.e.
         the opposite order that option-data is processed.
         </para>

       </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-ddns-config">
      <title>DDNS for DHCPv6</title>
      <para>
      As mentioned earlier, kea-dhcp6 can be configured to generate requests to
      the DHCP-DDNS server (referred to here as "D2") to update
      DNS entries. These requests are known as Name Change Requests or NCRs.
      Each NCR contains the following information:
      <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>
      Whether it is a request to add (update) or remove DNS entries
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
      Whether the change requests forward DNS updates (AAAA records), reverse
      DNS updates (PTR records), or both
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
      The Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN), lease address, and DHCID (information identifying the client associated with the FQDN)
      </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      The parameters controlling the generation of NCRs for submission to D2
      are contained in the <command>dhcp-ddns</command> section of the kea-dhcp6 server
      configuration. The mandatory parameters for the DHCP DDNS configuration
      are <command>enable-updates</command>, which is unconditionally
      required, and <command>qualifying-suffix</command>, which has no
      default value and is required when <command>enable-updates</command>
      is set to <command>true</command>.

      The two (disabled and enabled) minimal DHCP DDNS configurations are:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "dhcp-ddns": {
        <userinput>"enable-updates": false</userinput>
    },
    ...
}
</screen>
      and for example:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "dhcp-ddns": {
        <userinput>"enable-updates": true,
        "qualifying-suffix": "example."</userinput>
    },
    ...
}
</screen>

      The default values for the "dhcp-ddns" section are as follows:
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"server-ip": "127.0.0.1"</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"server-port": 53001</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"sender-ip": ""</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"sender-port": 0</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"max-queue-size": 1024</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"ncr-protocol": "UDP"</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"ncr-format": "JSON"</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"override-no-update": false</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"override-client-update": false</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"replace-client-name": "never"</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"generated-prefix": "myhost"</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"hostname-char-set": ""</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>"hostname-char-replacement": ""</command>
      </simpara></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <section xml:id="dhcpv6-d2-io-config">
      <title>DHCP-DDNS Server Connectivity</title>
      <para>
      For NCRs to reach the D2 server, kea-dhcp6 must be able
      to communicate with it. kea-dhcp6 uses the following configuration
      parameters to control this communication:
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>enable-updates</command> - determines whether kea-dhcp6 will
      generate NCRs. If missing, this value is assumed to be false, so DDNS updates
      are disabled. To enable DDNS updates set this value to true.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>server-ip</command> - IP address on which D2 listens for requests. The default is
      the local loopback interface at address 127.0.0.1. You may specify
      either an IPv4 or IPv6 address.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>server-port</command> - port on which D2 listens for requests. The default value
      is 53001.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>sender-ip</command> - IP address which kea-dhcp6 uses to send requests to D2.
      The default value is blank, which instructs kea-dhcp6 to select a suitable
      address.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>sender-port</command> - port which kea-dhcp6 uses to send requests to D2. The
      default value of 0 instructs kea-dhcp6 to select a suitable port.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>max-queue-size</command> - maximum number of requests allowed to queue waiting to
      be sent to D2. This value guards against requests accumulating
      uncontrollably if they are being generated faster than they can be
      delivered. If the number of requests queued for transmission reaches
      this value, DDNS updating will be turned off until the queue backlog has
      been sufficiently reduced. The intent is to allow kea-dhcp6 to
      continue lease operations without running the risk that its memory usage
      grows without limit. The default value is 1024.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>ncr-protocol</command> - socket protocol to use when sending requests to D2. Currently
      only UDP is supported.
      </simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara>
      <command>ncr-format</command> - packet format to use when sending requests to D2.
      Currently only JSON format is supported.
      </simpara></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      By default, kea-dhcp-ddns is assumed to be running on the same machine as kea-dhcp6, and
      all of the default values mentioned above should be sufficient.
      If, however, D2 has been configured to listen on a different address or
      port, these values must altered accordingly. For example, if D2 has been
      configured to listen on 2001:db8::5 port 900, the following configuration
      is required:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "dhcp-ddns": {
        <userinput>"server-ip": "2001:db8::5",
        "server-port": 900</userinput>,
        ...
    },
    ...
}
</screen>
      </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="dhcpv6-d2-rules-config">
      <title>When Does the kea-dhcp6 Server Generate a DDNS Request?</title>
      <para>kea-dhcp6 follows the behavior prescribed for DHCP servers in
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4704">RFC 4704</link>.
      It is important to keep in mind that kea-dhcp6 makes the initial
      decision of when and what to update and forwards that
      information to D2 in the form of NCRs. Carrying out the actual
      DNS updates and dealing with such things as conflict resolution
      are within the purview of D2 itself (<xref linkend="dhcp-ddns-server"/>).
      This section describes when kea-dhcp6 will generate NCRs and the
      configuration parameters that can be used to influence this decision.
      It assumes that the <command>enable-updates</command> parameter is true.
      </para>
      <note>
        <para>
        Currently the interface between kea-dhcp6 and D2 only supports requests
        which update DNS entries for a single IP address. If a lease grants
        more than one address, kea-dhcp6 will create the DDNS update request for
        only the first of these addresses.
        </para>
      </note>
      <para>
      In general, kea-dhcp6 will generate DDNS update requests when:
      <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>
      A new lease is granted in response to a DHCPREQUEST
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
      An existing lease is renewed but the FQDN associated with it has
      changed
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
      An existing lease is released in response to a DHCPRELEASE
      </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      In the second case, lease renewal, two DDNS requests will be issued: one
      request to remove entries for the previous FQDN, and a second request to
      add entries for the new FQDN. In the last case, a lease release, a
      single DDNS request to remove its entries will be made.
      </para>
      <para>
      The decisions involved when granting a new lease the first case) are more
      complex. When a new lease is granted, kea-dhcp6 will generate a DDNS
      update request only if the DHCPREQUEST contains the FQDN option (code 39).
      By default, kea-dhcp6 will respect the FQDN N and S flags specified by the client
      as shown in the following table:
      </para>
        <table xml:id="dhcp6-fqdn-flag-table">
          <title>Default FQDN Flag Behavior</title>
          <tgroup cols="4" align="left">
          <colspec colname="cflags"/>
          <colspec colname="meaning"/>
          <colspec colname="response"/>
          <colspec colname="sflags"/>
          <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Client Flags:N-S</entry>
                <entry>Client Intent</entry>
                <entry>Server Response</entry>
                <entry>Server Flags:N-S-O</entry>
              </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
                <entry>0-0</entry>
                <entry>
                Client wants to do forward updates, server should do reverse updates
                </entry>
                <entry>Server generates reverse-only request</entry>
                <entry>1-0-0</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry>0-1</entry>
                <entry>Server should do both forward and reverse updates</entry>
                <entry>Server generates request to update both directions</entry>
                <entry>0-1-0</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry>1-0</entry>
                <entry>Client wants no updates done</entry>
                <entry>Server does not generate a request</entry>
                <entry>1-0-0</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      <para>
      The first row in the table above represents "client delegation". Here
      the DHCP client states that it intends to do the forward DNS updates and
      the server should do the reverse updates. By default, kea-dhcp6 will honor
      the client's wishes and generate a DDNS request to D2 to update only
      reverse DNS data. The parameter <command>override-client-update</command> can be used
      to instruct the server to override client delegation requests. When
      this parameter is true, kea-dhcp6 will disregard requests for client
      delegation and generate a DDNS request to update both forward and
      reverse DNS data. In this case, the N-S-O flags in the server's
      response to the client will be 0-1-1 respectively.
      </para>
      <para>
      (Note that the flag combination N=1, S=1 is prohibited according to
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4702">RFC 4702</link>. If such a
      combination is received from the client, the packet will be dropped by kea-dhcp6.)
      </para>
      <para>
      To override client delegation, set the following values in the configuration file:
      </para>
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "dhcp-ddns": {
        <userinput>"override-client-update": true</userinput>,
        ...
    },
    ...
}
</screen>
      <para>
      The third row in the table above describes the case in which the client
      requests that no DNS updates be done. The parameter, <command>override-no-update</command>,
      can be used to instruct the server to disregard the client's wishes. When
      this parameter is true, kea-dhcp6 will generate DDNS update requests to
      kea-dhcp-ddns even if the client requests no updates be done. The N-S-O
      flags in the server's response to the client will be 0-1-1.
      </para>
      <para>
      To override client delegation, issue the following commands:
      </para>
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "dhcp-ddns": {
        <userinput>"override-no-update": true</userinput>,
        ...
    },
    ...
}
</screen>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="dhcpv6-fqdn-name-generation">
      <title>kea-dhcp6 Name Generation for DDNS Update Requests</title>
      <para>Each Name Change Request must of course include the fully qualified
      domain name whose DNS entries are to be affected. kea-dhcp6 can be
      configured to supply a portion or all of that name, based upon what it
      receives from the client in the DHCPREQUEST.</para>
      <para>
       The default rules for constructing the FQDN that will be used for DNS
       entries are:
      <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>
        If the DHCPREQUEST contains the client FQDN option, take the candidate name
        from there.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        If the candidate name is a partial (i.e. unqualified) name, then add a
        configurable suffix to the name and use the result as the FQDN.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        If the candidate name provided is empty, generate an FQDN using a
        configurable prefix and suffix.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        If the client provided neither option, then no DNS action will be taken.
      </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
        These rules can be amended by setting the
        <command>replace-client-name</command> parameter, which provides the
        following modes of behavior:
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>
        <command>never</command> - Use the name the client sent. If the client
        sent no name, do not generate one. This is the default mode.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        <command>always</command> - Replace the name the client sent. If the
        client sent no name, generate one for the client.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        <command>when-present</command> - Replace the name the client sent.
        If the client sent no name, do not generate one.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        <command>when-not-present</command> - Use the name the client sent.
        If the client sent no name, generate one for the client.
      </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    <note>
    Note that in early versions of Kea, this parameter was a boolean and permitted only values
    of <command>true</command> and <command>false</command>. Boolean values
    have been deprecated and are no longer accepted. If you are currently using
    booleans, you must replace them with the desired mode name. A value of
    <command>true</command> maps to <command>"when-present"</command>, while
    <command>false</command> maps to <command>"never"</command>.
    </note>

      For example, to instruct kea-dhcp6 to always generate the FQDN for a
      client, set the parameter <command>replace-client-name</command> to
      <command>always</command> as follows:
      </para>
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "dhcp-ddns": {
        <userinput>"replace-client-name": "always"</userinput>,
        ...
    },
    ...
}
</screen>
      <para>
      The prefix used in the generation of an FQDN is specified by the
      <command>generated-prefix</command> parameter. The default value is "myhost". To alter
      its value, simply set it to the desired string:
      </para>
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "dhcp-ddns": {
        <userinput>"generated-prefix": "another.host"</userinput>,
        ...
    },
    ...
}
</screen>
      <para>
      The suffix used when generating an FQDN, or when qualifying a
      partial name, is specified by
      the <command>qualifying-suffix</command> parameter. This
      parameter has no default value, thus it is mandatory when
      DDNS updates are enabled.
      To set its value simply set it to the desired string:
      </para>
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "dhcp-ddns": {
        <userinput>"qualifying-suffix": "foo.example.org"</userinput>,
        ...
    },
    ...
}
</screen>
      </section>
      <para>
      When qualifying a partial name, kea-dhcp6 will construct the name in the
      format:
      </para>
      <para>
        [candidate-name].[qualifying-suffix].
      </para>
      <para>
      where candidate-name is the partial name supplied in the DHCPREQUEST.
      For example, if the FQDN domain name value is "some-computer" and the
      qualifying-suffix "example.com", the generated FQDN is:
      </para>
      <para>
        some-computer.example.com.
      </para>
      <para>
      When generating the entire name, kea-dhcp6 will construct the name in the
      format:
      </para>
      <para>
        [generated-prefix]-[address-text].[qualifying-suffix].
      </para>
      <para>
      where address-text is simply the lease IP address converted to a
      hyphenated string. For example, if the lease address is 3001:1::70E,
      the qualifying suffix "example.com", and the default value is used for
      <command>generated-prefix</command>, the generated FQDN would be:
      </para>
      <para>
        myhost-3001-1--70E.example.com.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="host-name-sanitization">
        <title>Sanitizing Client FQDN Names</title>
        It may be that some of your DHCP clients provide values in the name
        component of the FQDN option (Option code 39) that contain undesirable
        characters. It is possible to configure kea-dhcp6 to sanitize these
        values. The most typical use case is ensuring that only
        characters that are permitted by RFC 1035 be included:
        A-Z,a-z,0-9, and '-'.
        
        This may be accomplished with the following two parameters:
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><simpara>
        <command>hostname-char-set</command> - a regular expression describing
        the invalid character set. This can be any valid, regular expression
        using POSIX extended expression syntax. For example, "[^A-Za-z0-9-]"
        would replace any character other than the letters A through z, digits
        0 through 9, and '-'. An empty string, the default value, disables
        sanitization.
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
        <command>hostname-char-replacement</command> - a string of zero or
        more characters with which to replace each invalid character in the
        client value. The default value is an empty string and will cause
        invalid characters to be OMITTED rather than replaced.
        </simpara></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        The following configuration will replace anything other than a
        letter, digit, hyphen, or dot with the letter 'x':
<screen>
"Dhcp4": {
    "dhcp-ddns": {
        "hostname-char-set": "[^A-Za-z0-9.-]",
        "hostname-char-replacement": "x",
        ...
    },
    ...
}
</screen>
        Thus, a client supplied value of "myhost-$[123.org" would become
        "myhost-xx123.org". Sanitizing is performed only on the portion of
        the name supplied by the client, and it is performed before applying
        a qualifying suffix (if one is defined and needed).
        <note>
        The following are some considerations to keep in mind:
        <para>
        Name sanitizing is meant to catch the more common cases of invalid
        characters through a relatively simple character-replacement scheme.
        It is difficult to devise a scheme that works well in all cases.
        If you find you have clients that are using odd corner cases of
        character combinations that cannot be readily handled with this
        mechanism, you should consider writing a hook that can carry out
        sufficiently complex logic to address your needs.
        </para>
        <para>
        Do not include dots in your hostname-char-set expression.
        When scrubbing FQDNs, dots are treated as delimiters and used to
        separate the option value into individual domain labels that are
        scrubbed and then re-assembled.
        </para>
        <para>
        If your clients are sending values that differ only by characters
        considered as invalid by your hostname-char-set, be aware that scrubbing
        them will yield identical values. In such cases, DDNS conflict rules
        will permit only one of them to register the name.
        </para>
        <para>
        Finally, given the latitude clients have in the values they send, it is
        virtually impossible to guarantee that a combination of these two
        parameters will always yield a name that is valid for use in DNS. For
        example, using an empty value for hostname-char-replacement could yield
        an empty domain label within a name, if that label consists only of
        invalid characters.
        </para>
        </note>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-dhcp4o6-config">
      <title>DHCPv4-over-DHCPv6: DHCPv6 Side</title>
      <para>
      The support of DHCPv4-over-DHCPv6 transport is described in
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7341">RFC 7341</link>
      and is implemented using cooperating DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 servers.
      This section is about the configuration of the DHCPv6 side
      (the DHCPv4 side is described in <xref linkend="dhcp4-dhcp4o6-config"/>).
      </para>
      <note>
      DHCPv4-over-DHCPv6 support is experimental and the details of
      the inter-process communication may change; both the
      DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 sides should be running the same version of Kea.
      For instance, the support of port relay (RFC 8357) introduced
      an incompatible change.
      </note>
      <para>
      There is only one specific parameter for the DHCPv6 side:
      <command>dhcp4o6-port</command>, which specifies the first of the
      two consecutive ports of the UDP sockets used for the communication
      between the DHCPv6 and DHCPv4 servers (the DHCPv6 server is bound
      to ::1 on <command>port</command> and connected to ::1 on
      <command>port</command> + 1).
      </para>
      <para>
      Two other configuration entries are generally required: unicast traffic
      support (see <xref linkend="dhcp6-unicast"/>) and DHCP 4o6 server
      address option (name "dhcp4o6-server-addr", code  88).
      </para>
      <para>
      The following configuration was used during some tests:
<screen>
{

# DHCPv6 conf
"Dhcp6": {

    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ "eno33554984/2001:db8:1:1::1" ]
    },

    "lease-database": {
        "type": "memfile",
        "name": "leases6"
    },

    "preferred-lifetime": 3000,
    "valid-lifetime": 4000,
    "renew-timer": 1000,
    "rebind-timer": 2000,

    "subnet6": [ {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1:1::/64",
        "interface": "eno33554984",
        "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1:1::1:0/112" } ]
    } ],

    <userinput>"dhcp4o6-port": 6767,

    "option-data": [ {
        "name": "dhcp4o6-server-addr",
        "code": 88,
        "space": "dhcp6",
        "csv-format": true,
        "data": "2001:db8:1:1::1"
    } ]
</userinput>
},

"Logging": {
    "loggers": [ {
        "name": "kea-dhcp6",
        "output_options": [ {
            "output": "/tmp/kea-dhcp6.log"
        } ],
        "severity": "DEBUG",
        "debuglevel": 0
    } ]
}

}
</screen>
      </para>
      <note>
      Relayed DHCPv4-QUERY DHCPv6 messages are not supported.
      </note>
    </section>

     <section xml:id="sanity-checks6">
       <title>Sanity Checks in DHCPv6</title>

       <para>
         An important aspect of a well-running DHCP system is an assurance that
         the data remains consistent. However, in some cases it may be convenient
         to tolerate certain inconsistent data. For example, a network
         administrator that temporarily removed a subnet from a configuration
         wouldn't want all the leases associated with it disappear from the
         lease database. Kea has a mechanism to control sanity
         checks for situations such as this.
       </para>

       <para>
         Kea supports a configuration scope called
         <command>sanity-checks</command>. It currently allows only a
         single parameter called <command>lease-checks</command>, which
         governs the verification carried out when a new lease is
         loaded from a lease file. This mechanism permits Kea to
         attempt to correct inconsistent data.
       </para>

       <para>
         Every subnet has a subnet-id value; this is how Kea internally
         identifies subnets. Each lease has a subnet-id parameter as well, which
         identifies which subnet it belongs to. However, if the configuration has
         changed, it is possible that a lease could exist with a subnet-id, but
         without any subnet that matches it. Also, it may be possible that the
         subnet's configuration has changed and the subnet-id now belongs to a
         subnet that does not match the lease. Kea's corrective algorithm first
         checks to see if there is a subnet with the subnet-id specified by the lease. If
         there is, it verifies whether the lease belongs to that subnet. If not,
         depending on the lease-checks setting, the lease is discarded, a
         warning is displayed, or a new subnet is selected for the lease that
         matches it topologically.
       </para>

       <para>
         Since delegated prefixes do not have to belong to a subnet in which
         they're offered, there is no way to implement such a mechanism for IPv6
         prefixes. As such, the mechanism works for IPv6 addresses only.
       </para>

       <para>
         There are five levels which are supported:
       </para>

       <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
           <simpara><command>none</command> - do no special checks; accept the
           lease as is</simpara>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <simpara><command>warn</command> - if problems are detected, a
           warning will be displayed, but the lease data will be accepted
           anyway. This is the default value.</simpara>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <simpara><command>fix</command> - If data inconsistency is
           discovered, Kea will try to correct it. If the correction is
           not successful, the incorrect data will be inserted anyway.</simpara>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <simpara><command>fix-del</command> - If a data inconsistency is
           discovered, Kea will try to correct it. If the correction is not
           succesful, the lease will be rejected. This setting ensures the data's
           correctness, but some incorrect data may be lost. Use with
           care.</simpara>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <simpara><command>del</command> - This is the strictest mode. If any
           inconsistency is detected, the lease is rejected. Use with care.
           </simpara>
         </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>

       <para>This feature is currently implemented for the memfile backend.</para>

       <para>
         An example configuration that sets this parameter looks as follows:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "sanity-checks": {
        <userinput>"lease-checks": "fix-del"</userinput>
    },
    ...
}</screen>
              </para>

       </section>

   </section>

  <!-- Host reservation is a large topic. There will be many subsections,
   so it should be a section on its own. -->
  <section xml:id="host-reservation-v6">
    <title>Host Reservation in DHCPv6</title>

    <para>There are many cases where it is useful to provide a configuration on
    a per-host basis. The most obvious one is to reserve a specific, static IPv6
    address or/and prefix for exclusive use by a given client (host); the returning
    client will get the same address or/and prefix every time, and other clients will
    never get that address. Another example when host reservations are applicable is when a host
    has specific requirements, e.g. a printer that needs additional DHCP options
    or a cable modem that needs specific parameters. Yet another possible use case
    is to define unique names for hosts.</para>

    <para>Note that there may be cases when a
    new reservation has been made for a client for the address or prefix
    currently in use by another client. We call this situation a "conflict." The
    conflicts get resolved automatically over time as described in subsequent
    sections. Once the conflict is resolved, the client will keep receiving the reserved
    configuration when it renews.</para>

    <para>Host reservations are defined as parameters for each subnet. Each host
    must be identified by either DUID or its hardware/MAC address. See
    <xref linkend="mac-in-dhcpv6"/> for details. There is an optional
    <command>reservations</command> array in the
    <command>subnet6</command> structure. Each element in that array
    is a structure that holds information about a single host. In
    particular, the structure has an identifier that
    uniquely identifies a host. In the DHCPv6 context, such an identifier
    is usually a DUID, but can also be a hardware or MAC address.
    One or more addresses or prefixes may also be specified, and it is
    possible to specify a hostname and DHCPv6 options for a given host.</para>

    <para>The following example shows how to reserve addresses and prefixes
    for specific hosts:

<screen>
"subnet6": [
    {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/48",
        "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1::/80" } ],
        "pd-pools": [
            {
                "prefix": "2001:db8:1:8000::",
                "prefix-len": 48,
                "delegated-len": 64
            }
        ],
        <userinput>"reservations": [
            {
                "duid": "01:02:03:04:05:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E",
                "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:1::100" ]
            },
            {
                "hw-address": "00:01:02:03:04:05",
                "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:1::101", "2001:db8:1::102" ]
            },
            {
                "duid": "01:02:03:04:05:06:07:08:09:0A",
                "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:1::103" ],
                "prefixes": [ "2001:db8:2:abcd::/64" ],
                "hostname": "foo.example.com"
            }
        ]</userinput>
    }
]
</screen>

    This example includes reservations for three different clients. The first reservation
    is for the address 2001:db8:1::100 for a client using DUID
    01:02:03:04:05:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E. The second reservation is for two addresses
    2001:db8:1::101 and 2001:db8:1::102, for a client using MAC address
    00:01:02:03:04:05. Lastly, address 2001:db8:1::103 and prefix 2001:db8:2:abcd::/64
    are reserved for a client using DUID 01:02:03:04:05:06:07:08:09:0A. The
    last reservation also assigns a hostname to this client.
    </para>

    <para>Note that DHCPv6 allows a single client to lease multiple addresses
    and multiple prefixes at the same time. Therefore <command>ip-addresses</command>
    and <command>prefixes</command> are plural and are actually arrays.
    When the client sends multiple IA options (IA_NA or IA_PD), each reserved
    address or prefix is assigned to an individual IA of the appropriate type. If
    the number of IAs of a specific type is lower than the number of reservations
    of that type, the number of reserved addresses or prefixes assigned to the
    client is equal to the number of IA_NAs or IA_PDs sent by the client; that is,
    some reserved addresses or prefixes are not assigned. However,
    they still remain reserved for this client and the server will not assign
    them to any other client. If the number of IAs of a specific type sent by the
    client is greater than the number of reserved addresses or prefixes, the
    server will try to assign all reserved addresses or prefixes to the individual
    IAs and dynamically allocate addresses or prefixes to the remaining IAs. If the
    server cannot assign a reserved address or prefix because it is in use,
    the server will select the next reserved address or prefix and try to assign it to
    the client. If the server subsequently finds that there are no more reservations
    that can be assigned to the client at that moment, the server will try to
    assign leases dynamically.
    </para>

    <para>Making a reservation for a mobile host that may visit multiple subnets
    requires a separate host definition in each subnet it is expected to visit.
    It is not possible to define multiple host definitions with the same hardware
    address in a single subnet. Multiple host definitions with the same hardware
    address are valid if each is in a different subnet. The reservation for a given host
    should include only one identifier, either DUID or hardware address. Defining
    both for the same host is considered a configuration error.
    </para>

    <para>Adding host reservations incurs a performance penalty. In principle,
    when a server that does not support host reservation responds to a query,
    it needs to check whether there is a lease for a given address being
    considered for allocation or renewal. The server that also supports host
    reservation has to perform additional checks: not only whether the address is
    currently used (i.e., if there is a lease for it), but also whether the address
    could be used by someone else (i.e., if there is a reservation for it). That
    additional check incurs extra overhead.</para>

    <section xml:id="reservation6-types">
      <title>Address/Prefix Reservation Types</title>

      <para>In a typical scenario there is an IPv6 subnet defined, with a certain
      part of it dedicated for dynamic address allocation by the DHCPv6
      server. There may be an additional address space defined for prefix
      delegation. Those dynamic parts are referred to as dynamic pools, address
      and prefix pools, or simply pools. In principle, a host reservation can
      reserve any address or prefix that belongs to the subnet. The reservations
      that specify addresses that belongs to configured pools are called
      "in-pool reservations." In contrast, those that do not
      belong to dynamic pools are called "out-of-pool
      reservations." There is no formal difference in the reservation
      syntax and both reservation types are handled
      uniformly.</para>

      <para>Kea supports global
      host reservations. These are reservations that are specified at the
      global level within the configuration and that do not belong to any
      specific subnet. Kea will still match inbound client packets to a
      subnet as before, but when the subnet's reservation mode is set to
      <command>"global"</command>, Kea will look for host reservations only
      among the global reservations defined. Typcially, such reservations would
      be used to reserve hostnames for clients which may move from one subnet
      to another.
      </para>

      <note>You can reserve any ip-address or prefix in a global reservation.
      Just keep in mind that Kea will not do any sanity checking on the address
      or prefix and that for Kea 1.5.0, support for global reservations should
      be considered experimental.
      </note>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="reservation6-conflict">
      <title>Conflicts in DHCPv6 Reservations</title>
      <para>As reservations and lease information are stored separately,
      conflicts may arise. Consider the following series of events: the server
      has configured the dynamic pool of addresses from the range of 2001:db8::10
      to 2001:db8::20. Host A requests an address and gets 2001:db8::10. Now the
      system administrator decides to reserve address 2001:db8::10 for Host B.
      In general, reserving an address
      that is currently assigned to someone else is not recommended, but there
      are valid use cases where such an operation is warranted.</para>

      <para>The server now has a conflict to resolve.
      If Host B boots up and requests an address, the server is
      not able to assign the reserved address 2001:db8::10. A naive approach
      would to be immediately remove the lease for Host A and create a new one
      for Host B. That would not solve the problem, though, because as soon as
      Host B gets the address, it will detect that the address is already in use
      by someone else (Host A) and will send a DHCPDECLINE message. Therefore, in this
      situation, the server has to temporarily assign a different address from the
      dynamic pool (not matching what has been reserved) to Host B.</para>

      <para>When Host A renews its address, the server will discover that
      the address being renewed is now reserved for someone else (Host
      B). Therefore, the server will remove the lease for 2001:db8::10, select
      a new address, and create a new lease for it. It will send two
      addresses in its response: the old address, with lifetime set to 0 to
      explicitly indicate that it is no longer valid; and the new address, with a
      non-zero lifetime. When Host B renews its temporarily assigned
      address, the server will detect that the existing lease does not match the
      reservation, so it will release the current address Host B has and will
      create a new lease matching the reservation. As before, the server
      will send two addresses: the temporarily assigned one with zeroed
      lifetimes, and the new one that matches the reservation with proper lifetimes
      set.</para>

      <para>This recovery will succeed, even if other hosts attempt to get
      the reserved address. If Host C requests the address 2001:db8::10 after
      the reservation is made, the server will propose a different address.</para>

      <para>This recovery mechanism allows the server to fully recover from a
      case where reservations conflict with existing leases. This procedure
      takes time and will roughly take as long as the value set for renew-timer.
      The best way to avoid such recovery is not to define new reservations that
      conflict with existing leases. Another recommendation is to use
      out-of-pool reservations. If the reserved address does not belong to a
      pool, there is no way that other clients can get this address.
      </para>

    <note>
     <para>The conflict-resolution mechanism does not work for global
     reservations. As of Kea 1.5.0, it is generally recommended not to use
     global reservations for addresses or prefixes. If you choose to use them
     anyway, you must manually ensure that the reserved values are not
     in the dynamic pools.</para>
    </note>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="reservation6-hostname">
      <title>Reserving a Hostname</title>
      <para>When the reservation for a client includes the <command>hostname</command>,
      the server will assign this hostname to the client and send
      it back in the Client FQDN, if the client sent the FQDN option to the
      server. The reserved hostname always takes precedence over the hostname
      supplied by the client (via the FQDN option) or the autogenerated
      (from the IPv6 address) hostname.</para>

      <para>The server qualifies the reserved hostname with the value
      of the <command>qualifying-suffix</command> parameter. For example, the
      following subnet configuration:
<screen>
"subnet6": [
    {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/48",
        "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1::/80" } ],
        "reservations": [
            {
                "duid": "01:02:03:04:05:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E",
                "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:1::100" ]
                "hostname": "alice-laptop"
            }
        ]
    }
],
"dhcp-ddns": {
    "enable-updates": true,
    "qualifying-suffix": "example.isc.org."
}
</screen>
      will result in assigning the "alice-laptop.example.isc.org." hostname to the
      client using the DUID "01:02:03:04:05:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E". If the <command>qualifying-suffix
      </command> is not specified, the default (empty) value will be used, and
      in this case the value specified as a <command>hostname</command> will
      be treated as a fully qualified name. Thus, by leaving the
      <command>qualifying-suffix</command> empty it is possible to qualify
      hostnames for different clients with different domain names:
<screen>
"subnet6": [
    {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/48",
        "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1::/80" } ],
        "reservations": [
            {
                "duid": "01:02:03:04:05:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E",
                "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:1::100" ]
                "hostname": "mark-desktop.example.org."
            }
        ]
    }
],
"dhcp-ddns": {
    "enable-updates": true,
}
</screen>
      The above example results in the assignment of the "mark-desktop.example.org." hostname to the
      client using the DUID "01:02:03:04:05:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E".
    </para>
</section>

    <section xml:id="reservation6-options">
      <title>Including Specific DHCPv6 Options in Reservations</title>
      <para>Kea offers the ability to specify options on a
      per-host basis. These options follow the same rules as any other
      options. These can be standard options (see <xref linkend="dhcp6-std-options"/>), custom options (see <xref linkend="dhcp6-custom-options"/>), or vendor-specific options
      (see <xref linkend="dhcp6-vendor-opts"/>). The following
      example demonstrates how standard options can be defined.</para>

      <screen>
"reservations": [
{
   "duid": "01:02:03:05:06:07:08",
   "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:1::2" ],
    <userinput>"option-data": [
    {
        "option-data": [ {
            "name": "dns-servers",
            "data": "3000:1::234"
        },
        {
            "name": "nis-servers",
            "data": "3000:1::234"
        }
    } ]</userinput>
} ]</screen>

    <para>Vendor-specific options can be reserved in a similar manner:</para>

    <screen>
"reservations": [
{
    "duid": "aa:bb:cc:dd:ee:ff",
    "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8::1" ],
    <userinput>"option-data": [
    {
        "name": "vendor-opts",
        "data": 4491
    },
    {
        "name": "tftp-servers",
        "space": "vendor-4491",
        "data": "3000:1::234"
    } ]</userinput>
} ]</screen>

<para>
 Options defined at host level have the highest priority. In other words,
 if there are options defined with the same type on global, subnet, class, and
 host level, the host-specific values will be used.
</para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="reservation6-client-classes">
      <title>Reserving Client Classes in DHCPv6</title>
      <para><xref linkend="classification-using-expressions"/> explains how
      to configure the server to assign classes to a client, based on the content
      of the options that this client sends to the server. Host reservations
      mechanisms also allow for the static assignment of classes to clients.
      The definitions of these classes are placed in the Kea
      configuration. The following configuration snippet shows how to specify
      that the client belongs to classes <command>reserved-class1</command>
      and <command>reserved-class2</command>. Those classes are associated with
      specific options being sent to the clients which belong to them.
      </para>
<screen>
{
    "client-classes": [
    {
       "name": "reserved-class1",
       "option-data": [
       {
           "name": "dns-servers",
           "data": "2001:db8:1::50"
       }
       ]
   },
   {
       "name": "reserved-class2",
       "option-data": [
       {
           "name": "nis-servers",
           "data": "2001:db8:1::100"
       }
       ]
    }
    ],
    "subnet6": [
    {   "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1::/64" } ],
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/48",
        "reservations": [
        {
            "duid": "01:02:03:04:05:06:07:08",
            <userinput>
            "client-classes": [ "reserved-class1", "reserved-class2" ]
            </userinput>
         } ]
     } ]
 }

</screen>
    <para>Static class assignments, as shown above, can be used in conjunction
    with classification, using expressions. The "KNOWN" or "UNKNOWN" builtin
    class is added to the packet and any class depending on it (directly or
    indirectly) and not only-if-required is evaluated.
    </para>

    <note>
     <para>If you want to force the evaluation of a class expression after
     the host reservation lookup, for instance because of a dependency on
     "reserved-class1" from the previous example, you should add a
     "member('KNOWN')" statement in the expression.</para>
    </note>

    </section>

    <section id="reservations6-mysql-pgsql-cql">
      <title>Storing Host Reservations in MySQL, PostgreSQL, or Cassandra</title>

      <para>
        It is possible to store host reservations in MySQL, PostgreSQL, or Cassandra. See
        <xref linkend="hosts6-storage"/> for information on how to configure Kea to use
        reservations stored in MySQL, PostgreSQL, or Cassandra. Kea provides a dedicated hook for
        managing reservations in a database; section <xref linkend="host-cmds"/> provides
        detailed information. The Kea wiki <uri
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
        xlink:href="https://gitlab.isc.org/isc-projects/kea/wikis/designs/commands#23-host-reservations-hr-management">https://gitlab.isc.org/isc-projects/kea/wikis/designs/commands#23-host-reservations-hr-management</uri>
        provides some examples of how to conduct common host reservations operations.
      </para>

      <note><simpara>In Kea, the maximum length of an option specified per-host is
      arbitrarily set to 4096 bytes.</simpara></note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="reservations6-tuning">
      <title>Fine Tuning DHCPv6 Host Reservation</title>

      <para>The host reservation capability introduces additional restrictions for the
      allocation engine (the component of Kea that selects an address for a client)
      during lease selection and renewal. In particular, three
      major checks are necessary. First, when selecting a new lease, it is not
      sufficient for a candidate lease to simply not be in use by another DHCP client; it
      also must not be reserved for another client. Second, when renewing a lease,
      an additional check must be performed to see whether the address being renewed is
      reserved for another client. Finally, when a host renews an address or a
      prefix, the server must check whether there is a reservation for this host,
      so the existing (dynamically allocated) address should be revoked and the
      reserved one be used instead.
      </para>
      <para>Some of those checks may be unnecessary in certain deployments and not
      performing them may improve performance. The Kea server provides the
      <command>reservation-mode</command> configuration parameter to select the
      types of reservations allowed for a particular subnet. Each reservation
      type has different constraints for the checks to be performed by the
      server when allocating or renewing a lease for the client.
      Allowed values are:

      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><simpara> <command>all</command> - enables both in-pool
      and out-of-pool host reservation types. This setting is the default value, and
      is the safest and most flexible. However, as all checks are conducted,
      it is also the slowest. It does not check against global reservations.
      </simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara> <command>out-of-pool</command> - allows only out of
      pool host reservations. With this setting in place, the server may assume
      that all host reservations are for addresses that do not belong to the
      dynamic pool. Therefore, it can skip the reservation checks when dealing
      with in-pool addresses, thus improving performance. Do not use this mode
      if any of your reservations use in-pool addresses. Caution is advised when
      using this setting; Kea does not sanity-check the reservations against
      <command>reservation-mode</command> and misconfiguration may cause
      problems.
      </simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara> <command>global</command> - allows only global
      host reservations. With this setting in place, the server searches for
      reservations for a client only among the defined global reservations.
      If an address is specified, the server will skip the reservation checks
      carried out when dealing in other modes, thus improving performance.
      Caution is advised when using this setting; Kea does not sanity-check
      the reservations when <command>global</command> and
      misconfiguration may cause problems.
      </simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara> <command>disabled</command> - host reservation support is disabled. As there
      are no reservations, the server will skip all checks. Any reservations defined
      will be completely ignored. As the checks are skipped, the server may
      operate faster in this mode.
      </simpara></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
      The parameter can be specified at global, subnet, and shared-network
      levels.
      </para>

      <para>
        An example configuration that disables reservation looks as follows:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
        <userinput>"reservation-mode": "disabled"</userinput>,
        ...
        }
    ]
}
       </screen>
      </para>

      <para>
        An example configuration using global reservations is shown below:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {

    <userinput>
    "reservation-mode": "global",
    "reservations": [
       {
        "duid": "00:03:00:01:11:22:33:44:55:66",
        "hostname": "host-one"
       },
       {
        "duid": "00:03:00:01:99:88:77:66:55:44",
        "hostname": "host-two"
       }
    ],
    </userinput>
    "subnet6": [
    {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
        ...
    }
    ]
}
</screen>
    For more details regarding global reservations, see
    <xref linkend="global-reservations6"/>.
    </para>

      <para>Another aspect of the host reservations is the different types of
      identifiers. Kea currently supports two types of identifiers
      in DHCPv6: hardware address and DUID. This is beneficial from a
      usability perspective; however, there is one drawback. For each incoming
      packet Kea has to to extract each identifier type and then query the
      database to see if there is a reservation by this particular
      identifier. If nothing is found, the next identifier is extracted and the next
      query is issued. This process continues until either a reservation is
      found or all identifier types have been checked. Over time, with an increasing
      number of supported identifier types, Kea would become slower and
      slower.</para>

      <para>To address this problem, a parameter called
      <command>host-reservation-identifiers</command> has been introduced. It
      takes a list of identifier types as a parameter. Kea will check only those
      identifier types enumerated in host-reservation-identifiers. From a
      performance perspective, the number of identifier types should be kept to a
      minimum, ideally one. If your deployment uses several
      reservation types, please enumerate them from most- to least-frequently
      used, as this increases the chances of Kea finding the reservation using the
      fewest queries. An example of host reservation identifiers looks
      as follows:

<screen>
<userinput>"host-reservation-identifiers": [ "duid", "hw-address" ],</userinput>
"subnet6": [
    {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
        ...
    }
]</screen>
</para>

<para>
If not specified, the default value is:
<screen>
<userinput>"host-reservation-identifiers": [ "hw-address", "duid" ]</userinput>
</screen>

</para>

</section>
  <section id="global-reservations6">
    <title>Global Reservations in DHCPv6</title>

    <para>In some deployments, such as mobile, clients can roam within the
    network and certain parameters must be specified regardless of
    the client's current location. To facilitate such a need, a global
    reservation mechanism has been implemented. The idea behind it is that
    regular host reservations are tied to specific subnets, by using a specific
    subnet-id. Kea can specify a global
    reservation that can be used in every subnet that has global reservations
    enabled.</para>

    <para>This feature can be used to assign certain parameters, such as
    hostname or other dedicated, host-specific options. It can also be used to
    assign addresses or prefixes. However, global reservations that assign
    either of these bypass the whole topology determination provided by DHCP
    logic implemented in Kea. It is very easy to misuse this feature and get a
    configuration that is inconsistent. To give a specific example, imagine a
    global reservation for an address 2001:db8:1111::1 and two subnets
    2001:db8:1111::/48 and 2001:db8:ffff::/48. If global reservations are used
    in both subnets and a device matching global host reservations visits part
    of the network that is covered by 2001:db8:ffff::/48, it will get an IP
    address 2001:db8:ffff::1, which will be outside of the prefix announced
    by its local router using Router Advertisements. Such a configuration
    would be unusable or, at the very least, riddled with issues, such as
    downlink traffic not reaching the device.</para>

    <para>
      To use global host reservations, a configuration similar to the following
      can be used:

<screen>
"Dhcp6:" {
    // This specifies global reservations. They will apply to all subnets that
    // have global reservations enabled.
    <userinput>
    "reservations": [
    {
       "hw-address": "aa:bb:cc:dd:ee:ff",
       "hostname": "hw-host-dynamic"
    },
    {
       "hw-address": "01:02:03:04:05:06",
       "hostname": "hw-host-fixed",

       // Use of IP address is global reservation is risky. If used outside of
       // matching subnet, such as 3001::/64, it will result in a broken
       // configuration being handled to the client.
       "ip-address": "2001:db8:ff::77"
    },
    {
       "duid": "01:02:03:04:05",
       "hostname": "duid-host"
    }
    ]</userinput>,
    "valid-lifetime": 600,
    "subnet4": [ {
        "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
        <userinput>"reservation-mode": "global",</userinput>
        "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1::-2001:db8:1::100" } ]
    } ]
}
</screen>
    </para>

    <para>When using database backends, the global host reservations are
    distinguished from regular reservations by using subnet-id value of
    zero.</para>
<!-- see CfgHostOperations::createConfig6() in
     src/lib/dhcpsrv/cfg_host_operations.cc -->

   </section>

    <!-- @todo: add support for per IA reservation (that specifies IAID in
                the ip-addresses and prefixes) -->
  </section>
  <!-- end of host reservations section -->

  <!-- shared networks starts here -->
  <section id="shared-network6">
    <title>Shared Networks in DHCPv6</title>

    <para>DHCP servers use subnet information in two ways. First, it is used
    to determine the point of attachment, or simply put, where the client is
    connected to the network. Second, the subnet information is used to group
    information pertaining to a specific location in the network. This approach
    works well in general cases, but there are scenarios where the boundaries are
    blurred. Sometimes it is useful to have more than one logical IP subnet
    being deployed on the same physical link. The need to understand
    that two or more subnets are used on the same link requires additional logic
    in the DHCP server. This capability is
    called "shared networks" in Kea and ISC DHCP configurations. It is sometimes also
    called "shared subnets." In Microsoft's nomenclature it is called "multinet."
    </para>

    <para>There are many use cases where the feature is useful. The most common
    example in the IPv4 case is when the server is running out of available
    addresses in a subnet. This is less common in IPv6, but shared networks
    are still useful in IPv6. One of the use cases is an exhaustion of IPv6-
    delegated prefixes within a subnet. Another IPv6-specific example
    is an experiment with an addressing scheme. With the advent of IPv6 deployment
    and a vast address space, many organizations split the address space into
    subnets, deploy it, and then after a while discover that they want to split it
    differently. In the transition period, they want both old and new addressing
    to be available. Thus the need for more than one subnet on the same physical
    link.</para>

    <para>Finally, the case of cable networks is directly applicable in
    IPv6. There are two types of devices in cable networks: cable modems and the
    end-user devices behind them. It is a common practice to use different
    subnets for cable modems to prevent users from tinkering with them.
    In this case, the distinction is based on the type of device, rather
    than address-space exhaustion.</para>

    <para>A client connected to a shared network may be assigned a lease (address
    or prefix) from any of the pools defined within the subnets belonging to the
    shared network. Internally, the server selects one of the subnets belonging to a
    shared network and tries to allocate a lease from this subnet. If the
    server is unable to allocate a lease from the selected subnet (e.g., due
    to pools exhaustion), it will use another subnet from the same shared
    network and try to allocate a lease from this subnet, etc. Therefore, in the
    typical case, the server will allocate all leases available in a given
    subnet before it starts allocating leases from other subnets belonging to
    the same shared network. However, in certain situations the client can be
    allocated a lease from the other subnets before the pools in the first
    subnet get exhausted, e.g. when the client provides a hint that belongs
    to another subnet or the client has reservations in a subnet other than
    the default.
    </para>

    <note>
    <para>Deployments should not assume that Kea waits until it has
    allocated all the addresses from the first subnet in a shared network
    before allocating addresses from other subnets.</para>
    </note>

    <para>In order to define a shared network an additional configuration scope
    is introduced:
<screen>
{
"Dhcp6": {
    <userinput>"shared-networks": [
        {
            // Name of the shared network. It may be an arbitrary string
            // and it must be unique among all shared networks.
            "name": "ipv6-lab-1",

            // The subnet selector can be specifed on the shared network level.
            // Subnets from this shared network will be selected for clients
            // communicating via relay agent having the specified IP address.
            "relay": {
                "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:2:34::1" ]
            },

            // This starts a list of subnets in this shared network.
            // There are two subnets in this example.
            "subnet6": [
                {
                    "subnet": "2001:db8::/48",
                    "pools": [ { "pool":  "2001:db8::1 - 2001:db8::ffff" } ]
                },
                {
                    "subnet": "3ffe:ffe::/64",
                    "pools": [ { "pool":  "3ffe:ffe::/64" } ]
                }
            ]
        } ]</userinput>, // end of shared-networks

    // It is likely that in your network you'll have a mix of regular,
    // "plain" subnets and shared networks. It is perfectly valid to mix
    // them in the same config file.
    //
    // This is regular subnet. It's not part of any shared-network.
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db9::/48",
            "pools": [ { "pool":  "2001:db9::/64" } ],
            "relay": {
                "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:1:2::1" ]
            }
        }
    ]

} // end of Dhcp6
}
</screen>
    </para>
    <para>As you see in the example, it is possible to mix shared and regular
    ("plain") subnets. Each shared network must have a unique name. This is
    similar to the ID for subnets, but gives administrators more flexibility. This is used
    for logging, but also internally for identifying shared networks.</para>

    <para>In principle it makes sense to define only shared networks that
    consist of two or more subnets. However, for testing purposes it is allowed
    to define a shared network with just one subnet or even an empty one. This
    is not a recommended practice in production networks, as the shared network
    logic requires additional processing and thus lowers the server's performance.
    To avoid unnecessary performance degradation, the shared subnets should only
    be defined when required by the deployment.
    </para>

    <para>Shared networks provide an ability to specify many parameters in
    the shared network scope that will apply to all subnets within it. If
    necessary, you can specify a parameter in the shared network scope and then
    override its value in the subnet scope. For example:
<screen>
"shared-networks": [
    {
        "name": "lab-network3",
        "relay": {
             "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:2:34::1" ]
        },

        // This applies to all subnets in this shared network, unless
        // values are overridden on subnet scope.
        <userinput>"valid-lifetime": 600</userinput>,

        // This option is made available to all subnets in this shared
        // network.
        <userinput>"option-data": [ {
            "name": "dns-servers",
            "data": "2001:db8::8888"
        } ]</userinput>,

        "subnet6": [
            {
                "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/48",
                "pools": [ { "pool":  "2001:db8:1::1 - 2001:db8:1::ffff" } ],

                // This particular subnet uses different values.
                <userinput>"valid-lifetime": 1200,
                "option-data": [
                {
                    "name": "dns-servers",
                    "data": "2001:db8::1:2"
                },
                {
                    "name": "unicast",
                    "data": "2001:abcd::1"
                } ]</userinput>
            },
            {
                 "subnet": "2001:db8:2::/48",
                 "pools": [ { "pool":  "2001:db8:2::1 - 2001:db8:2::ffff" } ],

                 // This subnet does not specify its own valid-lifetime value,
                 // so it is inherited from shared network scope.
                 <userinput>"option-data": [
                 {
                     "name": "dns-servers",
                     "data": "2001:db8:cafe::1"
                 } ]</userinput>
            }
        ],
    } ]</screen>

    In this example, there is a dns-servers option defined that is available to
    clients in both subnets in this shared network. Also, a valid lifetime is
    set to 10 minutes (600s). However, the first subnet overrides some of the values
    (valid lifetime is 20 minutes, different IP address for dns-servers), but
    also adds its own option (unicast address). Assuming a client asking for a
    server unicast and dns servers options is assigned a lease from this subnet,
    it will get a lease for 20 minutes and dns-servers, and be allowed to use
    server unicast at address 2001:abcd::1. If the same client is assigned to
    the second subnet, it will get a 10-minute lease, a dns-servers value of
    2001:db8:cafe::1, and no server unicast.
    </para>

    <para>Some parameters must be the same in all subnets in the same shared
    network. This restriction applies to the <command>interface</command> and
    <command>rapid-commit</command> settings. The most convenient way is to
    define them on the shared network scope, but you may specify them for each
    subnet. However, care should be taken for each subnet to have the same
    value.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Local and Relayed Traffic in Shared Networks</title>

    <para>It is possible to specify an interface name in the shared network scope to
    tell the server that this specific shared network is reachable directly (not
    via relays) using a local network interface. It is sufficient to specify
    it once at the shared network level. As all subnets in a shared network are
    expected to be used on the same physical link, it is a configuration error
    to attempt to define a shared network using subnets that are reachable over
    different interfaces. It is possible to specify the interface parameter on each
    subnet, although its value must be the same for each subnet. Thus it is
    usually more convenient to specify it once at the shared network level.
<screen>
"shared-networks": [
    {
        "name": "office-floor-2",

        // This tells Kea that the whole shared networks is reachable over
        // local interface. This applies to all subnets in this network.
        <userinput>"interface": "eth0"</userinput>,

        "subnet6": [
            {
                "subnet": "2001:db8::/64",
                "pools": [ { "pool":  "2001:db8::1 - 2001:db8::ffff" } ],
                <userinput>"interface": "eth0"</userinput>
            },
            {
                 "subnet": "3ffe:abcd::/64",
                 "pools": [ { "pool":  "3ffe:abcd::1 - 3ffe:abcd::ffff" } ]

                 // Specifying a different interface name is configuration
                 // error:
                 // "interface": "eth1"
            }
        ],
    } ]
</screen>
</para>

<para>Somewhat similar to interface names, relay IP addresses can also be
specified for the whole shared network. However, depending on your relay
configuration, it may use different IP addresses depending on which subnet
is being used. Thus there is no requirement to use the same IP relay address
for each subnet. Here's an example:

<screen>
"shared-networks": [
    {
        "name": "kakapo",
        <userinput>"relay": {
            "ip-addresses":  [ "2001:db8::abcd" ]
        }</userinput>,
        "subnet6": [
            {
                "subnet": "2001:db8::/64",
                <userinput>"relay": {
                    "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8::1234" ]
                }</userinput>,
                "pools": [ { "pool":  "2001:db8::1 - 2001:db8::ffff" } ]
            },
            {
                 "subnet": "3ffe:abcd::/64",
                 "pools": [ { "pool":  "3ffe:abcd::1 - 3ffe:abcd::ffff" } ],
                 <userinput>"relay": {
                    "ip-addresses": [ "3ffe:abcd::cafe" ]
                 }</userinput>
            }
        ]
    }
]</screen>
In this particular case the relay IP address specified at the network level doesn't
have much sense, as it is overridden in both subnets, but it was left there
as an example of how one could be defined at the network level. Note that the
relay agent IP address typically belongs to the subnet it relays packets from,
but this is not a strict requirement. Kea accepts any value here
as long as it is a valid IPv6 address.</para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Client Classification in Shared Networks</title>

      <para>Sometimes it is desirable to segregate clients into specific subnets
      based on certain properties. This mechanism is called client classification
      and is described in <xref linkend="classify"/>. Client classification
      can be applied to subnets belonging to shared networks in the same way
      as it is used for subnets specified outside of shared networks.
      It is important to understand how the server selects subnets for
      clients when client classification is in use, to ensure that the
      desired subnet is selected for a given client type.</para>

      <para>If a subnet is associated with a class, only the clients
      belonging to this class can use this subnet. If there are no
      classes specified for a subnet, any client connected to a given shared
      network can use this subnet. A common mistake is to assume that the
      subnet including a client class is preferred over subnets without
      client classes. Consider the following example:

<screen>
{
    "client-classes": [
        {
            "name": "b-devices",
            "test": "option[1234].hex == 0x0002"
        }
    ],
    "shared-networks": [
        {
            "name": "galah",
            "relay": {
                "ip-address": [ "2001:db8:2:34::1" ]
            },
            "subnet6": [
                {
                    "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
                    "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1::20 - 2001:db8:1::ff" } ],
                },
                {
                    "subnet": "2001:db8:3::/64",
                    "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:3::20 - 2001:db8:3::ff" } ],
                    <userinput>"client-class": "b-devices"</userinput>
                }
            ]
        }
    ]
}
</screen>

        If the client belongs to the "b-devices" class (because it includes option
        1234 with a value of 0x0002), that doesn't guarantee that the subnet 2001:db8:3::/64
        will be used (or preferred) for this client. The server can use either of
        the two subnets because the subnet 2001:db8:1::/64 is also allowed for
        this client. The client classification used in this case should be perceived
        as a way to restrict access to certain subnets, rather than a way to express
        subnet preference. For example, if the client doesn't belong to the
        "b-devices" class it may only use the subnet 2001:db8:1::/64 and will
        never use the subnet 2001:db8:3::/64.
      </para>

      <para>A typical use case for client classification is in a cable network,
      where cable modems should use one subnet and other devices should use
      another subnet within the same shared network. In this case it is necessary
      to apply classification on all subnets. The following example defines two
      classes of devices, and the subnet selection is made based on option 1234 values.
<screen>
{
    "client-classes": [
        {

            "name": "a-devices",
            "test": "option[1234].hex == 0x0001"
        },
        {
            "name": "b-devices",
            "test": "option[1234].hex == 0x0002"
        }
    ],
    "shared-networks": [
        {
            "name": "galah",
            "relay": {
                "ip-addresses":  [ "2001:db8:2:34::1" ]
            },
            "subnet6": [
                {
                    "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
                    "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:1::20 - 2001:db8:1::ff" } ],
                    <userinput>"client-class": "a-devices"</userinput>
                },
                {
                    "subnet": "2001:db8:3::/64",
                    "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:3::20 - 2001:db8:3::ff" } ],
                    <userinput>"client-class": "b-devices"</userinput>
                }
            ]
        }
    ]
}
</screen>
In this example each class has its own restriction. Only clients that belong to
class "a-devices" will be able to use subnet 2001:db8:1::/64 and only clients
belonging to "b-devices" will be able to use subnet 2001:db8:3::/64. Care should
be taken not to define too-restrictive classification rules, as clients that are
unable to use any subnets will be refused service. However, this may be a
desired outcome if one wishes to provide service only to clients with known properties
(e.g. only VoIP phones allowed on a given link).</para>

    <para>
      Note that it is possible to achieve an effect similar to the one presented in this
      section without the use of shared networks. If the subnets are placed in
      the global subnets scope, rather than in the shared network, the server
      will still use classification rules to pick the right subnet for a given
      class of devices. The major benefit of placing subnets within the
      shared network is that common parameters for the logically grouped
      subnets can be specified once, in the shared network scope, e.g. the
      "interface" or "relay" parameter. All subnets belonging to this shared
      network will inherit those parameters.
    </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Host Reservations in Shared Networks</title>

<para>
  Subnets that are part of a shared network allow host reservations, similar to
  regular subnets:
  <screen>
{
    "shared-networks": [
    {
        "name": "frog",
        "relay": {
            "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:2:34::1" ]
        },
        "subnet6": [
            {
                "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
                "id": 100,
                "pools": [ { "2001:db8:1::1 - 2001:db8:1::64" } ],
                <userinput>"reservations": [
                {
                    "duid": "00:03:00:01:11:22:33:44:55:66",
                    "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:1::28" ]
                }
                ]</userinput>
            },
            {
                "subnet": "2001:db8:3::/64",
                "id": 101,
                "pools": [ { "pool": "2001:db8:3::1 - 2001:db8:3::64" } ],
                <userinput>"reservations": [
                    {
                        "duid": "00:03:00:01:aa:bb:cc:dd:ee:ff",
                        "ip-addresses": [ "2001:db8:2::28" ]
                    }
                ]</userinput>
            }
        ]
    }
    ]
}
  </screen>
</para>
<para>It is worth noting that Kea conducts additional checks when processing a
packet if shared networks are defined. Instead of simply checking whether
there's a reservation for a given client in its initially selected subnet, it
looks through all subnets in a shared network for a reservation. This is
one of the reasons why defining a shared network may impact performance. If
there is a reservation for a client in any subnet, that particular subnet will
be picked for the client. Although it's technically not an error, it is
considered a bad practice to define reservations for the same host in multiple
subnets belonging to the same shared network.</para>

<para>While not strictly mandatory, it is strongly recommended to use explicit
"id" values for subnets if you plan to use database storage for host
reservations. If ID is not specified, the values for it are autogenerated,
i.e. it assigns increasing integer values starting from 1. Thus, the
autogenerated IDs are not stable across configuration changes.
</para>
    </section>

  </section>

  <!-- end of shared networks -->

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-serverid">
      <title>Server Identifier in DHCPv6</title>
      <para>The DHCPv6 protocol uses a "server identifier" (also known
      as a DUID) to allow clients to discriminate between several
      servers present on the same link.
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link>
      currently defines four DUID types: DUID-LLT, DUID-EN, DUID-LL, and DUID-UUID.
      </para>

      <para>The Kea DHCPv6 server generates a server identifier once, upon
      the first startup, and stores it in a file. This identifier is not
      modified across restarts of the server and so is a stable identifier.</para>

      <para>Kea follows the recommendation from
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link>
      to use DUID-LLT as the default server identifier. However, we have
      received reports that some deployments require different DUID
      types, and there is a need to administratively select both DUID
      type and/or its contents.</para>

      <para>The server identifier can be configured using parameters
      within the <command>server-id</command> map element in the global
      scope of the Kea configuration file. The following example
      demonstrates how to select DUID-EN as a server identifier:

<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "server-id": {
        "type": "EN"
    },
    ...
}
</screen>

      </para>

      <para>Currently supported values for <command>type</command>
      parameter are: "LLT", "EN", and "LL", for DUID-LLT, DUID-EN, and
      DUID-LL respectively.</para>

      <para>When a new DUID type is selected the server generates its
      value and replaces any existing DUID in the file. The server then
      uses the new server identifier in all future interactions with the
      clients.</para>

      <note><para>If the new server identifier is created after some clients
      have obtained their leases, the clients using the old identifier are not
      able to renew the leases; the server will ignore messages
      containing the old server identifier. Clients will continue sending
      Renew until they transition to the rebinding state. In this state, they
      will start sending Rebind messages to the multicast address without
      a server identifier. The server will respond to the Rebind messages
      with a new server identifier, and the clients will associate the
      new server identifier with their leases. Although the clients will
      be able to keep their leases and will eventually learn the new server
      identifier, this will be at the cost of an increased number of renewals
      and multicast traffic due to a need to rebind. Therefore, it is
      recommended that modification of the server identifier type
      and value is avoided if the server has already assigned leases and these
      leases are still valid.</para></note>

      <para>There are cases when an administrator needs to explicitly
      specify a DUID value rather than allow the server to generate it.
      The following example demonstrates how to explicitly set all
      components of a DUID-LLT.

<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "server-id": {
        "type": "LLT",
        "htype": 8,
        "identifier": "A65DC7410F05",
        "time": 2518920166
    },
    ...
}
</screen>

      where:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><simpara><command>htype</command> is a 16-bit unsigned value
        specifying hardware type,</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><command>identifier</command> is a link-layer
        address, specified as a string of hexadecimal digits, and</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><command>time</command> is a 32-bit unsigned
        time value.</simpara></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>The hexadecimal representation of the DUID generated as a result
      of the configuration specified above will be:
<screen>
 00:01:00:08:96:23:AB:E6:A6:5D:C7:41:0F:05
|type |htype|   time    |   identifier    |
</screen>
      </para>

      <para>A special value of 0 for "htype" and "time" is allowed,
      which indicates that the server should use ANY value for these
      components. If the server already uses a DUID-LLT it will use the
      values from this DUID; if the server uses a DUID of a different type
      or doesn't yet use any DUID, it will generate these values.
      Similarly, if the "identifier" is assigned an empty string, the
      value of the identifier will be generated. Omitting any of these
      parameters is equivalent to setting them to those special values.
      </para>

      <para>For example, the following configuration:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "server-id": {
        "type": "LLT",
        "htype": 0,
        "identifier": "",
        "time": 2518920166
    },
    ...
}
</screen>

      indicates that the server should use ANY link-layer address and
      hardware type. If the server is already using DUID-LLT, it will
      use the link-layer address and hardware type from the existing DUID.
      If the server is not yet using any DUID, it will use the link-layer
      address and hardware type from one of the available network
      interfaces. The server will use an explicit value of time; if it
      is different than a time value present in the currently used
      DUID, that value will be replaced, effectively
      modifying the current server identifier.
      </para>

      <para>
        The following example demonstrates an explicit configuration of
        a DUID-EN:

<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "server-id": {
        "type": "EN",
        "enterprise-id": 2495,
        "identifier": "87ABEF7A5BB545"
    },
    ...
}
</screen>

      where:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><simpara><command>enterprise-id</command> is a 32-bit
        unsigned value holding an enterprise number, and </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><command>identifier</command> is a variable-
        length identifier within DUID-EN.</simpara></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
        The hexadecimal representation of the DUID-EN created according to
        the configuration above is:
<screen>
 00:02:00:00:09:BF:87:AB:EF:7A:5B:B5:45
|type |  ent-id   |     identifier     |
</screen>
      </para>

      <para>As in the case of the DUID-LLT, special values can be used for the
      configuration of the DUID-EN. If the <command>enterprise-id</command> is 0, the server
      will use a value from the existing DUID-EN. If the server is not using
      any DUID or the existing DUID has a different type, the ISC enterprise
      id will be used. When an empty string is entered for <command>identifier</command>, the
      identifier from the existing DUID-EN will be used. If the server is
      not using any DUID-EN, a new 6-byte-long identifier will be generated.
      </para>

      <para>DUID-LL is configured in the same way as DUID-LLT except
      that the <command>time</command> parameter has no effect for DUID-LL,
      because this DUID type only comprises a hardware type and link-layer
      address. The following example demonstrates how to configure DUID-LL:

<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "server-id": {
        "type": "LL",
        "htype": 8,
        "identifier": "A65DC7410F05"
    },
    ...
}
</screen>

      </para>

      <para>
      which will result in the following server identifier:

<screen>
 00:03:00:08:A6:5D:C7:41:0F:05
|type |htype|   identifier    |
</screen>
      </para>

      <para>The server stores the generated server identifier in the following
      location: [kea-install-dir]/var/kea/kea-dhcp6-serverid.
      </para>

      <para>In some uncommon deployments where no stable storage is
      available, the server should be configured not to try to
      store the server identifier. This choice is controlled
      by the value of the <command>persist</command> boolean parameter:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "server-id": {
        "type": "EN",
        "enterprise-id": 2495,
        "identifier": "87ABEF7A5BB545",
        "persist": false
    },
    ...
}
</screen>
      </para>
      <para>The default value of the "persist" parameter is
      <command>true</command>, which configures the server to store the
      server identifier on a disk.</para>

      <para>In the example above, the server is configured not to store
      the generated server identifier on a disk. But if the server
      identifier is not modified in the configuration, the same value
      will be used after server restart, because the entire server
      identifier is explicitly specified in the configuration.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="data-directory">
      <title>DHCPv6 data directory</title>
      <para>The Kea DHCPv6 server puts the server identifier file and the
      default memory lease file into its data directory. By default
      this directory is <filename><userinput>prefix</userinput>/var/kea</filename>
      but this location can be changed using the
      <command>data-directory</command> global parameter as in:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    <userinput>"data-directory": "/var/tmp/kea-server6"</userinput>,
    ...
}
</screen>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="stateless-dhcp6">
      <title>Stateless DHCPv6 (Information-Request Message)</title>
      <para>Typically DHCPv6 is used to assign both addresses and options. These
      assignments (leases) have a state that changes over time, hence
      their name, stateful. DHCPv6 also supports a stateless mode,
      where clients request configuration options only. This mode is
      considered lightweight from the server perspective, as it does not require
      any state tracking, and carries the stateless name.</para>
      <para>The Kea server supports stateless mode. Clients can send
      Information-Request messages and the server sends back
      answers with the requested options (providing the options are
      available in the server configuration).  The server attempts to
      use per-subnet options first. If that fails - for whatever reason - it
      then tries to provide options defined in the global scope.</para>

      <para>Stateless and stateful mode can be used together. No special
      configuration directives are required to handle this; simply use the
      configuration for stateful clients and the stateless clients will get
      just the options they requested.</para>

      <para>This usage of global options allows for an interesting case.
      It is possible to run a server that provides only options and no
      addresses or prefixes. If the options have the same value in each
      subnet, the configuration can define required options in the global
      scope and skip subnet definitions altogether. Here's a simple example of
      such a configuration:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "interfaces-config": {
        "interfaces": [ "ethX" ]
    },
    <userinput>"option-data": [ {
        "name": "dns-servers",
        "data": "2001:db8::1, 2001:db8::2"
    } ]</userinput>,
    "lease-database": {
        "type": "memfile"
    }
 }
</screen>
      This very simple configuration will provide DNS server information
      to all clients in the network, regardless of their location. Note the
      specification of the memfile lease database; this is needed as
      Kea requires a lease database to be specified
      even if it is not used.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-rfc7550">
      <title>Support for RFC 7550 (now part of RFC 8415)</title>
      <para><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7550">RFC 7550</link>
      introduced some changes to the previous DHCPv6 specifications,
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3315">RFC 3315</link>
      and <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3633">RFC 3633</link>,
      to resolve a few issues with the coexistence of multiple stateful
      options in the messages sent between the clients and servers. Those
      changes were later included in the most recent DHCPv6 protocol specification,
      <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link>,
      which obsoleted <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7550">RFC 7550</link>.
      Kea supports <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link>
      along with these protocol changes, which are briefly described below.
      </para>

      <para>When a client, such as a requesting router, requests an allocation
      of both addresses and prefixes during the 4-way (SARR) exchange with the
      server, and the server is not configured to allocate any prefixes but it
      can allocate some addresses, it will respond with the IA_NA(s) containing
      allocated addresses and the IA_PD(s) containing the NoPrefixAvail status code.
      According to the updated specifications, if the client can operate without
      prefixes it should accept allocated addresses and transition to
      the "bound" state. When the client subsequently sends Renew/Rebind messages
      to the server, according to the T1 and T2 times, to extend the lifetimes of
      the allocated addresses, and if the client is still interested in obtaining
      prefixes from the server, it may also include an IA_PD in the Renew/Rebind
      to request allocation of the prefixes. If the server still cannot
      allocate the prefixes, it will respond with the IA_PD(s) containing the
      NoPrefixAvail status code. However, if the server can allocate the
      prefixes it will allocate and send them in the IA_PD(s) to the client.
      A similar situation occurs when the server is unable to allocate addresses
      for the client but can delegate prefixes. The client may request allocation
      of the addresses while renewing the delegated prefixes. Allocating leases for
      other IA types while renewing existing leases is by default supported by
      the Kea DHCPv6 server, and the server provides no configuration mechanisms
      to disable this behavior.</para>

      <para>
        The following are the other behaviors first introduced in
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7550">RFC 7550</link>
        (now part of
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link>)
        and supported by the Kea DHCPv6 server:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><simpara>Set T1/T2 timers to the same value for all
          stateful (IA_NA and IA_PD) options to facilitate renewal of all
          a client's leases at the same time (in a single message exchange),
          </simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Place NoAddrsAvail and NoPrefixAvail status codes
          in the IA_NA and IA_PD options in the Advertise message,
          rather than as the top-level options.</simpara></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-relay-override">
      <title>Using a Specific Relay Agent for a Subnet</title>
      <para>
        The relay must have an interface connected to the link on which
        the clients are being configured. Typically the relay has a global IPv6
        address configured on the interface that belongs to the subnet from which
        the server will assign addresses. Normally, the
        server is able to use the IPv6 address inserted by the relay (in the link-addr
        field in RELAY-FORW message) to select the appropriate subnet.
      </para>
      <para>
        However, that is not always the case. The relay
        address may not match the subnet in certain deployments. This
        usually means that there is more than one subnet allocated for a given
        link. The two most common examples where this is the case are long-lasting
        network renumbering (where both old and new address space is still being
        used) and a cable network. In a cable network, both cable modems and the
        devices behind them are physically connected to the same link, yet
        they use distinct addressing. In such a case, the DHCPv6 server needs
        additional information (like the value of the interface-id option or the IPv6
        address inserted in the link-addr field in the RELAY-FORW message) to
        properly select an appropriate subnet.
      </para>
      <para>
        The following example assumes that there is a subnet 2001:db8:1::/64
        that is accessible via a relay that uses 3000::1 as its IPv6 address.
        The server is able to select this subnet for any incoming packets
        that come from a relay with an address in 2001:db8:1::/64 subnet.
        It also selects that subnet for a relay with address 3000::1.
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
            "pools": [
                 {
                     "pool": "2001:db8:1::1-2001:db8:1::ffff"
                 }
             ],
             <userinput>"relay": {
                 "ip-addresses": [ "3000::1" ]
             }</userinput>
        }
    ]
}
</screen>
      </para>

      <para>If "relay" is specified, the "ip-addresses" parameter within
      it is mandatory.</para>

      <note>
      <para>
      The current version of Kea uses the "ip-addresses" parameter, which supports specifying a list of addresses.
      </para>
      </note>

    </section>

      <section xml:id="dhcp6-client-class-relay">
        <title>Segregating IPv6 Clients in a Cable Network</title>
        <para>
          In certain cases, it is useful to mix relay address information,
          introduced in <xref linkend="dhcp6-relay-override"/>, with client
          classification, explained in <xref linkend="classify"/>.
          One specific example is in a cable network, where typically modems
          get addresses from a different subnet than all devices connected
          behind them.
        </para>
        <para>
          Let us assume that there is one CMTS (Cable Modem Termination System)
          with one CM MAC (a physical link that modems are connected to).
          We want the modems to get addresses from the 3000::/64 subnet,
          while everything connected behind the modems should get addresses from
          another subnet (2001:db8:1::/64). The CMTS that acts as a relay
          uses address 3000::1. The following configuration can serve
          that configuration:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [
        {
            "subnet": "3000::/64",
            "pools": [
                { "pool": "3000::2 - 3000::ffff" }
            ],
            <userinput>"client-class": "VENDOR_CLASS_docsis3.0",
            "relay": {
                "ip-addresses": [ "3000::1" ]
            }</userinput>
        },

        {
            "subnet": "2001:db8:1::/64",
            "pools": [
                 {
                     "pool": "2001:db8:1::1-2001:db8:1::ffff"
                 }
             ],
             <userinput>"relay": {
                 "ip-addresses": [ "3000::1" ]
             }</userinput>
        }
    ]
}
</screen>
      </para>
      </section>

    <section xml:id="mac-in-dhcpv6">
      <title>MAC/Hardware Addresses in DHCPv6</title>
      <para>MAC/hardware addresses are available in DHCPv4 messages
      from the clients, and administrators
      frequently use that information to perform certain tasks like per-host
      configuration and address reservation for specific MAC addresses.
      Unfortunately, the DHCPv6 protocol does not provide any completely reliable way
      to retrieve that information. To mitigate that issue, a number of mechanisms
      have been implemented in Kea. Each
      of these mechanisms works in certain cases, but may fail in others.
      Whether the mechanism works in a particular deployment is
      somewhat dependent on the network topology and the technologies used.</para>

      <para>Kea allows specification of which of the supported methods should be
      used and in what order. This configuration may be considered a fine tuning
      of the DHCP deployment. In a typical deployment the default
      value of <command>"any"</command> is sufficient and there is no
      need to select specific methods. Changing the value of this parameter
      is the most useful in cases when an administrator wants to disable
      certain methods; for example, if the administrator trusts the network infrastructure
      more than the information provided by the clients themselves, they
      may prefer information provided by the relays over that
      provided by the clients.
      </para>
      <para>
      The configuration is controlled by the <command>mac-sources</command>
      parameter as follows:
        <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    <userinput>"mac-sources": [ "method1", "method2", "method3", ... ]</userinput>,

    "subnet6": [ ... ],

    ...
}
</screen>

    When not specified, a special value of "any" is used, which
    instructs the server to attempt to try all the methods in sequence and use the
    value returned by the first one that succeeds. If specified, it
    must have at least one value.</para>

    <para>Supported methods are:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><command>any</command> - Not an actual method, just a keyword that
        instructs Kea to try all other methods and use the first one that succeeds.
        This is the default operation if no <command>mac-sources</command> are defined.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><command>raw</command> - In principle, a DHCPv6 server could use raw
        sockets to receive incoming traffic and extract MAC/hardware address
        information. This is currently not implemented for DHCPv6 and this value has
        no effect.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><command>duid</command> - DHCPv6 uses DUID identifiers instead of
        MAC addresses. There are currently four DUID types defined, and two of them
        (DUID-LLT, which is the default, and DUID-LL) convey MAC address information.
        Although <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="" utl="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link> forbids
        it, it is possible to parse those DUIDs and extract
        necessary information from them. This method is not completely reliable, as
        clients may use other DUID types, namely DUID-EN or DUID-UUID.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><command>ipv6-link-local</command> - Another possible acquisition
        method comes from the source IPv6 address. In typical usage, clients are
        sending their packets from IPv6 link-local addresses. There is a good chance
        that those addresses are based on EUI-64, which contains a MAC address. This
        method is not completely reliable, as clients may use other link-local address
        types. In particular, privacy extensions, defined in
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4941">RFC 4941</link>, do not use
        MAC addresses. Also note that successful extraction requires that the
        address's u-bit must be set to 1 and its g-bit set to 0, indicating that it
        is an interface identifier as per
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2373#section-2.5.1">
        RFC 2373, section 2.5.1</link>.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><command>client-link-addr-option</command> - One extension defined
        to alleviate missing MAC issues is the client link-layer address option, defined
        in <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6939">RFC 6939</link>. This is
        an option that is inserted by a relay and contains information about a client's
        MAC address. This method requires a relay agent that supports the option and
        is configured to insert it. This method is useless for directly connected
        clients. This parameter can also be specified as <command>rfc6939</command>,
        which is an alias for <command>client-link-addr-option</command>.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><command>remote-id</command> -
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4649">RFC 4649</link>
        defines a remote-id option that is inserted by a relay agent. Depending
        on the relay agent configuration, the inserted option may convey the client's
        MAC address information. This parameter can also be specified as
        <command>rfc4649</command>, which is an alias for <command>remote-id</command>.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><command>subscriber-id</command> - Another option
        that is somewhat similar to the previous one is subscriber-id,
        defined in <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4580">RFC
        4580</link>. It, too, is inserted by a relay agent that is
        configured to insert it. This parameter can also be specified
        as <command>rfc4580</command>, which is an alias for
        <command>subscriber-id</command>. This method is currently not
        implemented.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><command>docsis-cmts</command> - Yet another possible source of MAC
        address information are the DOCSIS options inserted by a CMTS that acts
        as a DHCPv6 relay agent in cable networks. This method attempts to extract
        MAC address information from suboption 1026 (cm mac) of the vendor-specific option
        with vendor-id=4491. This vendor option is extracted from the relay-forward message,
        not the original client's message.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><command>docsis-modem</command> - The final possible source of MAC
        address information are the DOCSIS options inserted by the cable modem itself.
        This method attempts to extract MAC address information from suboption 36 (device id)
        of the vendor-specific option with vendor-id=4491. This vendor option is extracted from
        the original client's message, not from any relay options.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>Empty mac-sources is not allowed. If you do not want to specify it,
  either simply omit the mac-sources definition or specify it with the "any" value
  which is the default.</para>
  </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-decline">
      <title>Duplicate Addresses (DECLINE Support)</title>

      <para>The DHCPv6 server is configured with a certain pool of
      addresses that it is expected to hand out to DHCPv6 clients.
      It is assumed that the server is authoritative and has complete
      jurisdiction over those addresses. However, for various
      reasons, such as misconfiguration or a faulty client implementation
      that retains its address beyond the valid lifetime, there may be
      devices connected that use those addresses without the server's
      approval or knowledge.</para>

      <para>Such an unwelcome event can be detected
      by legitimate clients (using Duplicate Address Detection) and
      reported to the DHCPv6 server using a DHCPDECLINE message. The server
      will do a sanity check (to see whether the client declining an address really
      was supposed to use it), and then will conduct a clean-up operation
      and confirm it by sending back a REPLY message. Any DNS entries
      related to that address will be removed, the fact will be logged,
      and hooks will be triggered. After that is complete, the address
      will be marked as declined (which indicates that it is used by
      an unknown entity and thus not available for assignment)
      and a probation time will be set on it. Unless otherwise
      configured, the probation period lasts 24 hours; after that
      period, the server will recover the lease (i.e. put it back into
      the available state) and the address will be available for assignment
      again. It should be noted that if the underlying issue of a
      misconfigured device is not resolved, the duplicate-address
      scenario will repeat. If reconfigured correctly, this mechanism provides an
      opportunity to recover from such an event automatically, without
      any system administrator intervention.</para>

      <para>To configure the decline probation period to a value other
      than the default, the following syntax can be used:
<screen>
  "Dhcp6": {
    <userinput>"decline-probation-period": 3600</userinput>,
    "subnet6": [ ... ],
    ...
}
</screen>
      The parameter is expressed in seconds, so the example above will instruct
      the server to recycle declined leases after one hour.</para>

      <para>There are several statistics and hook points associated with the
      Decline handling procedure. The lease6_decline hook is triggered after the
      incoming DHCPDECLINE message has been sanitized and the server is about to decline
      the lease. The declined-addresses statistic is increased after the
      hook returns (both global and subnet-specific variants). (See
      <xref linkend="dhcp6-stats"/> and <xref linkend="hooks-libraries"/> for more details
      on DHCPv6 statistics and Kea hook points.)</para>

      <para>Once the probation time elapses, the declined lease is recovered
      using the standard expired-lease reclamation procedure, with several
      additional steps. In particular, both declined-addresses statistics
      (global and subnet-specific) are decreased. At the same time,
      reclaimed-declined-addresses statistics (again in two variants, global and
      subnet-specific) are increased.</para>

      <para>A note about statistics: The server does not decrease the
      assigned-addresses statistics when a DHCPDECLINE message is received and
      processed successfully. While technically a declined address is no longer
      assigned, the primary usage of the assigned-addresses statistic is to
      monitor pool utilization. Most people would forget to include
      declined-addresses in the calculation, and simply use
      assigned-addresses/total-addresses. This would cause a bias towards
      under-representing pool utilization. As this has a potential for major
      issues, we decided not to decrease assigned-addresses immediately after
      receiving DHCPDECLINE, but to do it later when Kea recovers the address back to
      the available pool.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-stats">
      <title>Statistics in the DHCPv6 Server</title>
      <note>
        <para>This section describes DHCPv6-specific statistics. For a general
        overview and usage of statistics, see <xref linkend="stats"/>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>
        The DHCPv6 server supports the following statistics:
      </para>
        <table frame="all" xml:id="dhcp6-statistics">
          <title>DHCPv6 Statistics</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="statistic" align="center"/>
          <colspec colname="type" align="center"/>
          <colspec colname="description" align="left"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Statistic</entry>
              <entry>Data Type</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of DHCPv6 packets received. This includes all packets:
              valid, bogus, corrupted, rejected, etc. This statistic is expected
              to grow rapidly.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-receive-drop</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of incoming packets that were dropped. The exact reason
              for dropping packets is logged, but the most common reasons may
              be: an unacceptable or not supported packet type is received, direct responses
              are forbidden, the server-id sent by the client does not match the
              server's server-id, or the packet is malformed.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-parse-failed</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of incoming packets that could not be parsed.
              A non-zero value of this statistic indicates that the server
              received a malformed or truncated packet. This may indicate problems
              in your network, faulty clients, faulty relay agents, or a bug in the
              server.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-solicit-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>
                Number of SOLICIT packets received. This statistic is expected
                to grow; its increase means that clients that just booted
                started their configuration process and their initial packets
                reached your Kea server.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-advertise-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>
                Number of ADVERTISE packets received. Advertise packets are sent
                by the server and the server is never expected to receive them. A non-zero
                value of this statistic indicates an error occurring in the network.
                One likely cause would be a misbehaving relay agent that incorrectly
                forwards ADVERTISE messages towards the server, rather than back to the
                clients.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-request-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of DHCPREQUEST packets received. This statistic
                is expected to grow. Its increase means that clients that just booted
                received the server's response (DHCPADVERTISE) and accepted it, and are now
                requesting an address (DHCPREQUEST).
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-reply-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of REPLY packets received. This statistic is
              expected to remain zero at all times, as REPLY packets are sent by
              the server and the server is never expected to receive
              them. A non-zero value indicates an error. One likely cause would be
              a misbehaving relay agent that incorrectly forwards REPLY messages
              towards the server, rather than back to the clients.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-renew-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of RENEW packets received. This statistic
                is expected to grow; its increase means that clients received their
                addresses and prefixes and are trying to renew them.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-rebind-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of REBIND packets received. A non-zero value
              indicates that clients didn't receive responses to their RENEW messages
              (through the regular lease-renewal mechanism) and are attempting to find any server
              that is able to take over their leases. It may mean that some servers'
              REPLY messages never reached the clients.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-release-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of RELEASE packets received. This statistic is expected
              to grow when a device is being shut down in the network; it
              indicates that the address or prefix assigned is reported as no longer
              needed. Note that many devices, especially wireless, do not send RELEASE
              packets either because of design choice or due to the client moving out
              of range.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
            <entry>pkt6-decline-received</entry>
            <entry>integer</entry>
            <entry>
              Number of DECLINE packets received. This statistic is expected to
              remain close to zero. Its increase means that a client leased an
              address, but discovered that the address is currently used by an
              unknown device in your network. If this statistic is growing, it
              may indicate a misconfigured server or devices that have statically
              assigned conflicting addresses.
            </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-infrequest-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>
                Number of INFORMATION-REQUEST packets received. This statistic
                is expected to grow if there are devices that are using
                stateless DHCPv6. INFORMATION-REQUEST messages are used by
                clients that request stateless configuration, i.e. options
                and parameters other than addresses or prefixes.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-dhcpv4-query-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>
                Number of DHCPv4-QUERY packets received. This
                statistic is expected to grow if there are devices
                that are using DHCPv4-over-DHCPv6. DHCPv4-QUERY
                messages are used by DHCPv4 clients on an IPv6-only
                line which encapsulates the requests over DHCPv6.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-dhcpv4-response-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>
                Number of DHCPv4-RESPONSE packets received. This
                statistic is expected to remain zero at all times, as
                DHCPv4-RESPONSE packets are sent by the server and the
                server is never expected to receive them. A non-zero
                value indicates an error. One likely cause would be a
                misbehaving relay agent that incorrectly forwards
                DHCPv4-RESPONSE message towards the server rather than
                back to the clients.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-unknown-received</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of packets received of an unknown type. A non-zero
              value of this statistic indicates that the server received a
              packet that it wasn't able to recognize; either it had an unsupported
              type or was possibly malformed.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-sent</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of DHCPv6 packets sent. This statistic is expected
              to grow every time the server transmits a packet. In general, it
              should roughly match pkt6-received, as most incoming packets cause
              the server to respond. There are exceptions (e.g. server receiving a
              REQUEST with server-id matching other server), so do not worry if
              it is less than pkt6-received.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-advertise-sent</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of ADVERTISE packets sent. This statistic is
              expected to grow in most cases after a SOLICIT is processed. There
              are certain uncommon, but valid, cases where incoming SOLICIT packets are
              dropped, but in general this statistic is expected to be close to
              pkt6-solicit-received.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-reply-sent</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of REPLY packets sent. This statistic is expected to
              grow in most cases after a SOLICIT (with rapid-commit), REQUEST,
              RENEW, REBIND, RELEASE, DECLINE, or INFORMATION-REQUEST is
              processed. There are certain cases where there is no response.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pkt6-dhcpv4-response-sent</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of DHCPv4-RESPONSE packets sent. This
              statistic is expected to grow in most cases after a
              DHCPv4-QUERY is processed. There are certain cases where
              there is no response.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
            <entry>subnet[id].total-nas</entry>
            <entry>integer</entry>
            <entry>
            Total number of NA addresses available for
            DHCPv6 management for a given subnet; in other words, this is the sum
            of all addresses in all configured pools. This statistic changes only
            during configuration changes. Note that it does not take into account any
            addresses that may be reserved due to host reservation. The
            <emphasis>id</emphasis> is the subnet-id of a given subnet. This
            statistic is exposed for each subnet separately, and is
            reset during a reconfiguration event.
            </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
            <entry>subnet[id].assigned-nas</entry>
            <entry>integer</entry>
            <entry>
            Number of NA addresses in a given subnet that
            are assigned. It increases every time a new lease is allocated
            (as a result of receiving a REQUEST message) and is decreased every time a
            lease is released (a RELEASE message is received) or expires. The
            <emphasis>id</emphasis> is the subnet-id of a given subnet. This
            statistic is exposed for each subnet separately, and is
            reset during a reconfiguration event.
            </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
            <entry>subnet[id].total-pds</entry>
            <entry>integer</entry>
            <entry>
            Total number of PD prefixes available for
            DHCPv6 management for a given subnet; in other words, this is the sum
            of all prefixes in all configured pools. This statistic changes only
            during configuration changes. Note it does not take into account any
            prefixes that may be reserved due to host reservation. The
            <emphasis>id</emphasis> is the subnet-id of a given subnet. This
            statistic is exposed for each subnet separately, and is
            reset during a reconfiguration event.
            </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
            <entry>subnet[id].assigned-pds</entry>
            <entry>integer</entry>
            <entry>
            Number of PD prefixes in a given subnet that
            are assigned. It increases every time a new lease is allocated
            (as a result of receiving a REQUEST message) and is decreased every time a
            lease is released (a RELEASE message is received) or expires. The
            <emphasis>id</emphasis> is the subnet-id of a given subnet. This statistic
            is exposed for each subnet separately, and is reset during a
            reconfiguration event.
            </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>reclaimed-leases</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry> Number of expired leases that have been
              reclaimed since server startup. It is incremented each time an expired
              lease is reclaimed (counting both NA and PD reclamations) and is reset
              when the server is reconfigured.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>subnet[id].reclaimed-leases</entry>
              <entry>integer</entry>
              <entry>Number of expired leases associated with
              a given subnet (<emphasis>"id"</emphasis> is the subnet-id) that have
              been reclaimed since server startup. It is incremented each time an expired
              lease is reclaimed (counting both NA and PD reclamations) and is reset
              when the server is reconfigured.
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
            <entry>declined-addresses</entry>
            <entry>integer</entry>
            <entry>
              Number of IPv6 addresses that are
              currently declined; a count of the number of leases
              currently unavailable. Once a lease is recovered, this
              statistic will be decreased; ideally, this statistic should be
              zero. If this statistic is non-zero or increasing,
              a network administrator should investigate whether there is
              a misbehaving device in the network. This is a global statistic
              that covers all subnets.
            </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
            <entry>subnet[id].declined-addresses</entry>
            <entry>integer</entry>
            <entry>
              Number of IPv6 addresses that are
              currently declined in a given subnet; a count of the
              number of leases currently unavailable. Once a lease is
              recovered, this statistic will be decreased; ideally, this
              statistic should be zero. If this statistic is
              non-zero or increasing, a network administrator should
              investigate whether there is a misbehaving device in the network. The
              <emphasis>id</emphasis> is the subnet-id of a given subnet. This
              statistic is exposed for each subnet separately.
            </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
            <entry>reclaimed-declined-addresses</entry>
            <entry>integer</entry>
            <entry>
              Number of IPv6 addresses that were
              declined, but have now been recovered. Unlike
              declined-addresses, this statistic never decreases. It can be used
              as a long-term indicator of how many actual valid Declines were
              processed and recovered from. This is a global statistic that
              covers all subnets.
            </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
            <entry>subnet[id].reclaimed-declined-addresses</entry>
            <entry>integer</entry>
            <entry>
              Number of IPv6 addresses that were
              declined, but have now been recovered. Unlike
              declined-addresses, this statistic never decreases. It can be used
              as a long-term indicator of how many actual valid Declines were
              processed and recovered from. The
              <emphasis>id</emphasis> is the subnet-id of a given subnet. This
              statistic is exposed for each subnet separately.
            </entry>
            </row>

        </tbody>
        </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-ctrl-channel">
      <title>Management API for the DHCPv6 Server</title>
      <para>
        The management API allows the issuing of specific
        management commands, such as statistics retrieval, reconfiguration, or shutdown.
        For more details, see <xref linkend="ctrl-channel"/>. Currently, the only
        supported communication channel type is UNIX stream socket. By default there
        are no sockets open; to instruct Kea to open a socket, the following entry
        in the configuration file can be used:
<screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "control-socket": {
        "socket-type": "unix",
        "socket-name": <userinput>"/path/to/the/unix/socket"</userinput>
    },

    "subnet6": [
        ...
    ],
    ...
}
</screen>
      </para>

      <para>
        The length of the path specified by the <command>socket-name</command>
        parameter is restricted by the maximum length for the UNIX socket name
        on your operating system, i.e. the size of the <command>sun_path</command>
        field in the <command>sockaddr_un</command> structure, decreased by 1.
        This value varies on different operating systems between 91 and 107
        characters. Typical values are 107 on Linux and 103 on FreeBSD.
      </para>

      <para>
        Communication over the control channel is conducted using JSON structures.
        See the <uri
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
        xlink:href="https://jenkins.isc.org/job/Kea_doc/doxygen/d2/d96/ctrlSocket.html">Control Channel section in the Kea Developer's Guide</uri> for more
        details.
      </para>

      <para>The DHCPv6 server supports the following operational commands:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>build-report</listitem>
            <listitem>config-get</listitem>
            <listitem>config-reload</listitem>
            <listitem>config-set</listitem>
            <listitem>config-test</listitem>
            <listitem>config-write</listitem>
            <listitem>dhcp-disable</listitem>
            <listitem>dhcp-enable</listitem>
            <listitem>leases-reclaim</listitem>
            <listitem>list-commands</listitem>
            <listitem>shutdown</listitem>
            <listitem>version-get</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
         as described in <xref linkend="commands-common"/>. In addition,
         it supports the following statistics-related commands:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>statistic-get</listitem>
            <listitem>statistic-reset</listitem>
            <listitem>statistic-remove</listitem>
            <listitem>statistic-get-all</listitem>
            <listitem>statistic-reset-all</listitem>
            <listitem>statistic-remove-all</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        as described in <xref linkend="command-stats"/>.
      </para>

    </section>

      <section id="dhcp6-user-contexts">
        <title>User Contexts in IPv6</title>
        <para>
          Kea allows loading hook libraries that sometimes could benefit from
          additional parameters. If such a parameter is specific to the whole
          library, it is typically defined as a parameter for the hook library.
          However, sometimes there is a need to specify parameters that are
          different for each pool.
        </para>

        <para>
          User contexts can store arbitrary data as long as it has valid JSON
          syntax and its top level element is a map (i.e. the data must be
          enclosed in curly brackets). However, some hook libraries may expect specific
          formatting; please consult the specific hook library
          documentation for details.
        </para>

        <para>
          User contexts can be specified at global scope,
          shared network, subnet, pool, client class, option data, or
          definition level, and via host reservation. One other useful
          usage is the ability to store comments or descriptions.
        </para>

        <para>
          Let's consider a lightweight 4over6 deployment as an example. It is an
          IPv6 transition technology that allows mapping IPv6 prefixes into full
          or partial IPv4 addresses. In the DHCP context, these are specific
          parameters that are supposed to be delivered to clients in the form of
          additional options. Values of these options are correlated to
          delegated prefixes, so it is reasonable to keep these parameters
          together with the PD pool. On the other hand, lightweight 4over6 is
          not a commonly used feature, so it is not a part of the base Kea
          code. The solution to this problem is to use user context. For each PD
          pool that is expected to be used for lightweight 4over6, a user context
          with extra parameters is defined. Those extra parameters will be used
          by a hook library that would be loaded only when dynamic calculation of
          the lightweight 4over6 option is actually needed. An example
          configuration looks as follows:
          <screen>
"Dhcp6": {
    "subnet6": [ {
        "pd-pools": [
        {
            "prefix":  "2001:db8::",
            "prefix-len": 56,
            "delegated-len": 64,

            // This is a pool specific context.
            <userinput>"user-context": {
                "threshold-percent": 85,
                "v4-network": "192.168.0.0/16",
                "v4-overflow": "10.0.0.0/16",
                "lw4over6-sharing-ratio": 64,
                "lw4over6-v4-pool": "192.0.2.0/24",
                "lw4over6-sysports-exclude": true,
                "lw4over6-bind-prefix-len": 56
            }</userinput>
        } ],
        "subnet": "2001:db8::/32",

        // This is a subnet specific context. You can put any type of
        // information here as long as it is a valid JSON.
        <userinput>"user-context": {
            "comment": "Those v4-v6 migration technologies are tricky.",
            "experimental": true,
            "billing-department": 42,
            "contact-points": [ "Alice", "Bob" ]
        }</userinput>
    } ],
    ...
}</screen>
        </para>

        <para>
          Kea does not interpret or use the content of the user context;
          it simply stores it, making it available to the hook
          libraries. It is up to each hook library to extract the information
          and use it.
          The parser translates a "comment" entry into a user context
          with the entry, which allows a comment to be attached inside the
          configuration itself.
        </para>
        <para>
          For more background information, see <xref linkend="user-context"/>.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-std">
      <title>Supported DHCPv6 Standards</title>
      <para>The following standards are currently
      supported:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3315">RFC 3315</link>:
            Supported messages are SOLICIT,
            ADVERTISE, REQUEST, RELEASE, RENEW, REBIND, INFORMATION-REQUEST,
            CONFIRM and REPLY.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>IPv6 Prefix Options for
            Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) version 6</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3633">RFC 3633</link>:
            Supported options are IA_PD and
            IA_PREFIX. Also supported is the status code NoPrefixAvail.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>DNS Configuration options for Dynamic Host
            Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3646">RFC 3646</link>:
            Supported option is DNS_SERVERS.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>The Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)
            Relay Agent Remote-ID Option</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4649">RFC 4649</link>:
            REMOTE-ID option is supported.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>The Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6) Client
            Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) Option</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4704">RFC 4704</link>:
            Supported option is CLIENT_FQDN.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)
            Option for Dual-Stack Lite</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6334">RFC 6334</link>:
            the AFTR-Name DHCPv6 Option is supported.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>Relay-Supplied DHCP Options</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6422">RFC 6422</link>:
            Full functionality is supported: OPTION_RSOO, ability of the server
            to echo back the options, checks whether an option is RSOO-enabled,
            ability to mark additional options as RSOO-enabled.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>Prefix Exclude Option for DHCPv6-based Prefix
            Delegation</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6603">RFC
            6603</link>: Prefix Exclude option is supported.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>Client Link-Layer Address Option in
            DHCPv6</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6939">RFC
            6939</link>: Supported option is client link-layer
            address option.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>Issues and Recommendations with Multiple
            Stateful DHCPv6 Options</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7550">RFC
            7550</link>: All recommendations related to the DHCPv6 server
            operation are supported.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>DHCPv6 Options for Configuration of Softwire
            Address and Port-Mapped Clients</emphasis>,
            <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7598">RFC
            7598</ulink>: All options indicated in this specification are
            supported by the DHCPv6 server.</simpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><emphasis>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)</emphasis>,
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link>:
            New DHCPv6 protocol specification which obsoletes RFC 3315, RFC 3633, RFC 3736, RFC 4242, RFC 7083,
            RFC 7283, and RFC 7550</simpara>
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dhcp6-limit">
      <title>DHCPv6 Server Limitations</title>
      <para> These are the current limitations of the DHCPv6 server
      software. Most of them are reflections of the current stage of
      development and should be treated as <quote>not implemented
      yet</quote>, rather than actual limitations.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            The server will allocate, renew, or rebind a maximum of one lease
            for a particular IA option (IA_NA or IA_PD) sent by a client.
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8415">RFC 8415</link>
            allows for multiple addresses or prefixes to be allocated for a single IA.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Temporary addresses are not supported.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            Client reconfiguration (RECONFIGURE) is not yet supported.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="dhcp6-srv-examples">
      <title>Kea DHCPv6 server examples</title>

      <para>
        A collection of simple-to-use examples for the DHCPv6 component of Kea is
        available with the source files, located in the doc/examples/kea6
        directory.
      </para>

    </section>

  </chapter>
