<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;" >
]>

<chapter id="faq">
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

  <para>This chapter contains a number of frequently asked questions and
  troubleshooting tips. It currently lacks content, but it is expected to grow
  over time.</para>

    <!-- Note: you may be tempted to put in questions here that concern current
    missing features or known issues type of stuff. Please do not do that.
    This section should only contain questions that will still be valid in
    at least 2 years. If you have something short term, please consider putting
    it in the known issues list. -->

  <section id="faq-generic">
    <title>Generic Frequently Asked Questions</title>

    <section id="q1-generic">
      <title>Where did the Kea name came from?</title>

      <para>Kea is the name of a high mountain parrot living in New Zealand.
      See this <ulink url="https://lists.isc.org/pipermail/kea-users/2014-October/000032.html" />
      for an extended answer.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="q2-generic">
      <title>Feature X is not supported yet. When/if will it be available?</title>

      <para>Kea is developed by a small team of engineers. Our resources are
      limited, so we need to prioritize requests. The complexity of a new
      feature (how difficult it is to implement a feature and how likely it
      would break something that already works), amount of work required and
      expected popularity (i.e. how many users would actually benefit from it)
      are three leading factors. We sometimes also have contractual obligations.
      </para>

      <para> Simply stating that you'd like feature X is useful. We try to
      implement features that are actively requested first, but the reality
      is that we have more requests than we can handle, so some of them must
      be postponed, at least in the near future. So is your request likely to
      be rejected? Not at all. You can do many things to greatly improve the
      chances of your request being fulfilled. First, it helps to explain why you
      need a feature. If your explanation is reasonable and there are likely
      other users that would benefit from it, the chances for Kea developers
      to put this task on a roadmap is better. Saying that you are willing
      to participate in tests (e.g. test engineering drops when they become
      available) is also helpful.</para>

      <para>Another thing you can do to greatly improve the chances of a feature
      to appear is to actually develop it on your own and submit a patch.
      That's an avenue that people often forget about. Kea is open source
      software and we do accept patches. There are certain requirements, like
      code quality, comments, unit-tests, documentation, etc., but we have
      accepted a significant number of patches in the past, so it's doable.
      Accepted contributions range from minor documentation corrections to
      significant new features, like support for a new database type. Before
      considering writing and submitting a patch, make sure you read
      the Contributor's Guide in <ulink url="http://git.kea.isc.org/~tester/kea/doxygen/">Kea Developer's Guide</ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>Kea is developed by ISC, which is a non-profit organization.
      You may consider signing a development contract with us. In the past
      we did implement certain features due to contractual obligations.
      With additional funds we are able to put extra engineering efforts
      into Kea development. We can reshuffle our schedule or add extra
      hands to the team if needed. Please keep in mind that Kea is
      open source software and its principle goal is to provide a good DHCP
      solution that can be used by everyone. In other words, we may
      refuse a contract that would tie the solution to specific proprietary
      technology or make it unusable for other users. Also, we strive to
      make Kea a reference implementation, so if your proposal significantly
      violates a RFC, we may have a problem with that. Nevertheless, please
      talk to us and we may be able to find a solution.</para>

      <para>Finally, Kea has a <ulink url="http://kea.isc.org/roadmap">public
      roadmap</ulink>, with releases happening several times each year. We tend
      to not modify features for the current milestone, unless there are very good
      reasons to do so. Therefore "I'd like a featury X in 6 months" is much
      better received than "I'd like a feature X now".</para>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="faq-dhcp4">
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions about DHCPv4</title>

    <section iq="q1-dhcp4">
      <title>I set up a firewall, but the Kea server still receives the traffic. Why?</title>

      <para>Any DHCPv4 server must be able to receive from and send traffic to
      hosts that don't have an IPv4 address assigned yet. That is typically not
      possible with regular UDP sockets, therefore the Kea DHCPv4 server uses raw
      sockets by default. Raw sockets mean that the incoming packets are received
      as raw Ethernet frames, thus bypassing the whole kernel IP stack, including
      any firewalling rules your kernel may provide.</para>

      <para>If you do not want the server to use raw sockets, it is possible to
      configure the Kea DHCPv4 server to use UDP sockets instead. See <command>dhcp-socket-type</command>
      described in <xref linkend="dhcp4-interface-configuration" />. However,
      using UDP sockets has certain limitations. In particular, they may not allow
      for sending responses directly to clients without IPv4 addresses assigned.
      That's ok, if all your traffic is coming through relay agents.</para>
    </section>

  </section> <!-- end of DHCPv4 FAQ section -->

  <section id="faq-dhcp6">
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions about DHCPv6</title>

    <section iq="q1-dhcp6">
      <title>Kea DHCPv6 doesn't seem to get incoming traffic. I checked with tcpdump (or other traffic
      capture software) that the incoming traffic is reaching the box. What's wrong?</title>

      <para>Please check whether your OS has any IPv6 filtering rules. Many
      operating systems are shipped with firewalls that discard incoming IPv6
      traffic by default. In particular, many Linux distributions do that. Please
      check the output of the following command:
  <screen>
# <userinput>ip6tables -L -n</userinput></screen>
      One common mistake in this area is to use <command>iptables</command> tool,
      which lists IPv4 firewall rules only.
      </para>
    </section>

  </section> <!-- end of DHCPv6 FAQ section -->


  </chapter>
