<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2018 Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
-->

    <section xml:id="high-availability-library">
      <title>ha: High Availability</title>
      <para>
        This section describes the High Availability hooks library, which can be
        loaded on a pair of DHCPv4 or DHCPv6 servers to increase reliability of
        the DHCP service in case of outage of one of the servers. This library
        used to be only available to ISC customers, but is now part of
        the open source Kea, available to all users.

        <note>
          <para>This library may only be loaded by <command>kea-dhcp4</command>
          or <command>kea-dhcp6</command> process.
          </para>
        </note>
      </para>
      <para>
        High Availability (HA) of the DHCP service is provided by running multiple
        cooperating server instances. If any of these instances becomes
        unavailable for whatever reason (DHCP software crash, Control Agent
        software crash, power outage, hardware failure), a surviving
        server instance can continue providing the reliable service to the clients. Many
        DHCP servers implementations include "DHCP Failover" protocol, which most
        significant features are: communication between the servers, partner
        failure detection and leases synchronization between the servers.
        However, the DHCPv4 failover standardization process was never completed
        at IETF. The DHCPv6 failover standard (RFC 8156) was published, but it
        is complex, difficult to use, has significant operational constraints
        and is different than its v4 counterpart.
        Although it may be useful for some users to use a "standard" failover
        protocol, it seems that most of the Kea users are simply interested in
        a working solution which guarantees high availability of the DHCP
        service. Therefore, Kea HA hook library derives major concepts from the
        DHCP Failover protocol but uses its own solutions for communication,
        configuration and its own state machine, which greatly simplifies its
        implementation and generally better fits into Kea. Also, it provides the
        same features in both DHCPv4 and DHCPv6. This document purposely
        uses the term "High Availability" rather than "Failover" to emphasize that
        it is not the Failover protocol implementation.
      </para>
      <para>
        The following sections describe the configuration and operation of the Kea
        HA hook library.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Supported Configurations</title>
        <para>The Kea HA hook library supports two configurations also known as HA
        modes: load balancing and hot standby. In the load balancing mode, there
        are two servers responding to the DHCP requests. The load balancing function
        is implemented as described in RFC3074, with each server responding to
        1/2 of received DHCP queries. When one of the servers allocates a lease
        for a client, it notifies the partner server over the control channel
        (RESTful API), so as the partner can save the lease information in its
        own database. If the communication with the partner is unsuccessful,
        the DHCP query is dropped and the response is not returned to the DHCP
        client. If the lease update is successful, the response is returned to
        the DHCP client by the server which has allocated the lease. By
        exchanging the lease updates, both servers get a copy of all leases
        allocated by the entire HA setup and any of the servers can be switched
        to handle the entire DHCP traffic if its partner becomes unavailable.</para>

        <para>In the load balancing configuration, one of the servers must be
        designated as "primary" and the other server is designated as "secondary".
        Functionally, there is no difference between the two during the normal
        operation. This distniction is required when the two servers are
        started at (nearly) the same time and have to synchronize their
        lease databases. The primary server synchronizes the database first.
        The secondary server waits for the primary server to complete the
        lease database synchronization before it starts the synchronization.
        </para>

        <para>In the hot standby configuration one of the servers is designated as
        "primary" and the second server is designated as "secondary". During the
        normal operation, the primary server is the only one that responds to
        the DHCP requests. The secodary server receives lease updates from the
        primary over the control channel. However, it does not respond to any
        DHCP queries as long as the primary is running or, more accurately,
        until the secondary considers the primary to be offline. When the
        secondary server detects the failure of the primary, it starts
        responding to all DHCP queries.
        </para>

        <para>In the configurations described above, the primary, secondary and
        standby are referred to as "active" servers, because they receive
        lease updates and can automatically react to the partner's failures by
        responding to the DHCP queries which would normally be handled by the
        partner. The HA hook library supports another server type (role) -
        backup server. The use of the backup servers is optional. They can be used
        in both load balancing and hot standby setup, in addition to the active
        servers. There is no limit on the number of backup servers in the HA
        setup. However, the presence of the backup servers increases latency
        of the DHCP responses, because not only do active servers send lease
        updates to each other, but also to the backup servers.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Clocks on Active Servers</title>
        <para>Synchronized clocks are essential for the HA setup to operate
        reliably. The servers share lease information via lease updates and
        during synchronization of the databases. The lease information includes
        the time when the lease has been allocated and when it expires. Some
        clock skew between the servers participating the HA setup would usually
        exist. This is acceptable as long as the clock skew is relatively low,
        comparing to the lease lifetimes. However, if the clock skew becomes too
        high, the different notions of time for the lease expiration by different
        servers may cause the HA system to malfuction. For example, one server
        may consider a valid lease to be expired. As a consequence, the lease
        reclamation process may remove a name associated with this lease from
        the DNS, even though the lease may later get renewed by a client.</para>

        <para>Each active server monitors the clock skew by comparing its current
        time with the time returned by its partner in response to the heartbeat
        command. This gives a good approximation of the clock skew, although it
        doesn't take into account the time between sending the response by the
        partner and receiving this response by the server which sent the
        heartbeat command. If the clock skew exceeds 30 seconds, a warning log
        message is issued. The administrator may correct this problem by
        synchronizing the clocks (e.g. using NTP). The servers should notice
        the clock skew correction and stop issuing the warning</para>

        <para>If the clock skew is not corrected and it exceeds 60 seconds, the
        HA service on each of the servers is terminated, i.e. the state
        machine enters the <command>terminated</command> state. The servers
        will continue to respond to the DHCP clients (as in the load-balancing
        or hot-standby mode), but will neither exchange lease updates nor
        heartbeats and their lease databases will diverge. In this case, the
        administrator should synchronize the clocks and restart the servers.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ha-server-states">
        <title>Server States</title>
        <para id="command-ha-heartbeat">The DHCP server operating
        within an HA setup runs a state machine
        and the state of the server can be retrieved by its peers using the
        <command>ha-heartbeat</command> command sent over the RESTful API. If
        the partner server doesn't respond to the <command>ha-heartbeat</command>
        command longer than configured amount of time, the communication is
        considered interrupted and the server may (depending on the configuration)
        use additional measures (desribed further in this document) to verify if
        the partner is still operating. If it finds that the partner is not
        operating, the server transitions to the <command>partner-down</command>
        state to handle the entire DHCP traffic directed to the system.</para>

        <para>In this case, the surviving server continues to send the
        <command>ha-heartbeat</command> command to detect when the partner wakes
        up. The partner synchronizes the lease database and when it is finally
        ready to operate, the surviving server returns to the normal operation,
        i.e. <command>load-balancing</command> or <command>hot-standby</command>
        state.</para>

        <para>The following is the list of all possible states into which the
        servers may transition:

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem><para><command>backup</command> - normal operation of the
          backup server. In this state it receives lease updates from the active
          servers.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>hot-standby</command> - normal operation of
          the active server running in the hot standby mode. Both primary and
          standby server are in this state during their normal operation.
          The primary server is responding to the DHCP queries and sends lease updates
          to the standby server and to the backup servers, if any backup servers
          are present.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>load-balancing</command> - normal operation
          of the active server running in the load balancing mode. Both primary
          and secondary server are in this state during their normal operation.
          Both servers are responding to the DHCP queries and send lease updates
          to each other and to the backup servers, if any backup servers are
          present.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>partner-down</command> - an active server
          transitions to this state after detecting that its partner (another
          active server) is offline. The server doesn't transition to this state
          if any of the backup servers is unavailable. In the <command>
          partner-down</command> state the server responds to all DHCP queries,
          so also those queries which are normally handled by the active server
          which is now unavailable.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>ready</command> - an active server transitions
          to this state after synchronizing its lease database with an active
          partner. This state is to indicate to the partner (likely being in the
          <command>partner-down</command> state that it may return to the
          normal operation. When it does, the server being in the <command>
          ready</command> state will also start normal operation.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>syncing</command> - an active server
          transitions to this state to fetch leases from the active partner
          and update the local lease database. When it this state, it
          issues the <command>dhcp-disable</command> to disable the DHCP
          service of the partner from which the leases are fetched. The DHCP
          servie is disabled for the maximum time of 60 seconds, after which
          it is automatically enabled, in case the syncing partner has died
          again failing to re-enable the service. If the synchronization is
          completed the syncing server issues the <command>dhcp-enable
          </command> to re-enable the DHCP service of the partner. The
          syncing operation is synchronous. The server is waiting for an
          answer from the partner and is not doing anything else while the
          leases synchronization takes place. A server which is configured
          to not synchronize its database with the partner, i.e. when the
          <command>sync-leases</command> configuration parameter is set to
          <command>false</command>, will never transition to this state.
          Instead, it will transition directly from the
          <command>waiting</command> to <command>ready</command> state.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>terminated</command> - an active server
          transitions to this state when the High Availability  hooks library
          is unable to further provide reliable service and a manual
          intervention of the administrator is required to correct the problem.
          It is envisaged that various issues with the HA setup may cause the
          server to transition to this state in the future. As of Kea 1.4.0
          release, the only issue causing the HA service to terminate is
          unacceptably high clock skew between the active servers, i.e. if the
          clocks on respective servers are more than 60 seconds apart.
          While in this state, the server will continue responding to the
          DHCP clients based on the HA mode selected (load balancing or
          hot standby), but the lease updates won't be exchanged and the
          heartbeats won't be sent. Once a server has entered the
          "terminated" state it will remain in this state until it is
          restarted. The administrator must correct the issue which caused
          this situation prior to restarting the server (e.g. synchronize clocks).
          Otherwise, the server will return to the "terminated" state as
          soon as it finds that the clock skew is still too high.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>waiting</command> - each started server
          instance enters this state. The backup server will transition
          directly from this state to the <command>backup</command> state.
          An active server will send heartbeat to its partner to check its
          state. If the partner appears to be unavailable the server will
          transition to the <command>partner-down</command>, otherwise it
          will transition to the <command>syncing</command> or
          <command>ready</command> state (depending on the setting of the
          <command>sync-leases</command> configuration parameter). If
          both servers appear to be in the <command>waiting</command>
          state (concurrent startup) the primary server will transition to
          the next state first. The secondary or standby server will remain
          in the <command>waiting</command> state until the primary
          transitions to the <command>ready</command> state.</para></listitem>.
        </itemizedlist></para>

        <note>
          <para>Currently, restarting the HA service being in the
          <command>terminated</command> state requires restarting the
          DHCP server or reloading its configuration. In the future, we will
          provide a command to restart the HA service.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Whether the server responds to the DHCP queries and which
        queries it responds to is a matter of the server's state, if no
        administrative action is performed to configure the server
        otherwise. The following table provides the default behavior for
        various states.</para>

        <para>The <command>DHCP Server Scopes</command> denotes what group
        of received DHCP queries the server responds to in the given state.
        The in-depth explanation what the scopes are can be found below.
        </para>

        <para>
          <table frame="all" xml:id="ha-default-states-behavior">
            <title>Default behavior of the server in various HA states</title>
            <tgroup cols="4">
              <colspec colname="state"/>
              <colspec colname="server type" align="center"/>
              <colspec colname="dhcp-service" align="center"/>
              <colspec colname="dhcp-service-scopes" align="center"/>
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>State</entry>
                  <entry>Server Type</entry>
                  <entry>DHCP Service</entry>
                  <entry>DHCP Service Scopes</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>backup</entry>
                  <entry>backup server</entry>
                  <entry>disabled</entry>
                  <entry>none</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>hot-standby</entry>
                  <entry>primary or standby (hot standby mode)</entry>
                  <entry>enabled</entry>
                  <entry><command>HA_server1</command> if primary, none otherwise</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>load-balancing</entry>
                  <entry>primary or secondary (load balancing mode)</entry>
                  <entry>enabled</entry>
                  <entry><command>HA_server1</command> or <command>HA_server2</command></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>partner-down</entry>
                  <entry>active server</entry>
                  <entry>enabled</entry>
                  <entry>all scopes</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>ready</entry>
                  <entry>active server</entry>
                  <entry>disabled</entry>
                  <entry>none</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>syncing</entry>
                  <entry>active server</entry>
                  <entry>disabled</entry>
                  <entry>none</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>terminated</entry>
                  <entry>active server</entry>
                  <entry>enabled</entry>
                  <entry>same as in the load-balancing or hot-standby state</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>waiting</entry>
                  <entry>any server</entry>
                  <entry>disabled</entry>
                  <entry>none</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
        </para>

        <para>The DHCP service scopes require some explanation. The HA
        configuration must specify a unique name for each server within
        the HA setup. This document uses the following convention within
        provided examples: <command>server1</command> for a primary server,
        <command>server2</command> for the secondary or standby server and
        <command>server3</command> for the backup server. In the real life
        any names can be used as long as they remain unique.</para>

        <para>In the load balancing mode there are two scopes named after
        the active servers: <command>HA_server1</command> and <command>
        HA_server2</command>. The DHCP queries load balanced to the
        <command>server1</command> belong to the <command>HA_server1</command>
        scope and the queries load balanced to the <command>server2</command>
        belong to the <command>HA_server2</command> scope. If any of the
        servers is in the <command>partner-down</command> state, it is
        responsible for serving both scopes.</para>

        <para>In the hot standby mode, there is only one scope <command>
        HA_server1</command> because only the <command>server1</command>
        is responding to the DHCP queries. If that server becomes unavailable,
        the <command>server2</command> becomes responsible for this scope.
        </para>

        <para>The backup servers do not have their own scopes. In some
        cases they can be used to respond to the queries belonging to
        the scopes of the active servers. Also, a server which is neither
        in the partner-down state nor in the normal operation serves
        no scopes.</para>

        <para>The scope names can be used to associate pools, subnets
        and networks with certain servers, so as only these servers
        can allocate addresses or prefixes from those pools, subnets
        or network. This is done via the client classification mechanism
        (see below).</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ha-scope-transition">
        <title>Scope Transition in Partner Down Case</title>
        <para>When one of the servers finds that its partner is unavailble,
        it will start serving clients from its own scope and the scope of the
        partner which is considered unavailable. This is straight forward
        for the new clients, i.e. sending DHCPDISCOVER (DHCPv4) or Solicit
        (DHCPv6), because those requests are not sent to any particular server.
        The available server will respond to all such queries when it is
        in the <command>partner-down</command> state.</para>

        <para>When the client is renewing a lease, it will send its
        DHCPREQUEST (DHCPv4) or Renew (DHCPv6) message directly to the
        server which has allocated the lease being renewed. Because this
        server is unavailable, the client will not get any response. In
        that case, the client continues to use its lease and re-tries to
        renew until the rebind timer (T2) elapses. The client will now enter
        the rebinding phase, in which it will send DHCPREQUEST (DHCPv4) or
        Rebind (DHCPv6) message to any available server. The surviving
        server will receive the rebinding request and will (typically)
        extend the lifetime of the lease. The client will continue to
        contact that new server to renew its lease as appropriate.</para>

        <para>When the other server becomes available, both active servers
        will eventually transition to the <command>load-balancing</command>
        or <command>hot-standby</command> state, in which they will be
        responsible for their own scopes. Some clients belonging to the
        scope of the started server will be trying to renew their leases
        via the surviving server. This server will not respond to them
        anymore and the client will eventually transition back to the
        right server via rebinding mechanism again.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ha-load-balancing-config">
        <title>Load Balancing Configuration</title>
        <para>The following is the configuration snippet which enables
        high availability on the primary server within the load balancing
        configuration. The same configuration should be applied on the
        secondary and the backup server, with the only difference that
        the <command>this-server-name</command> should be set to
        <command>server2</command> and <command>server3</command>
        on those servers respectively.
<screen>
{
"Dhcp4": {

    ...

    "hooks-libraries": [
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_lease_cmds.so",
            "parameters": { }
        },
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_ha.so",
            "parameters": {
                "high-availability": [ {
                    "this-server-name": "server1",
                    "mode": "load-balancing",
                    "heartbeat-delay": 10000,
                    "max-response-delay": 10000,
                    "max-ack-delay": 5000,
                    "max-unacked-clients": 5,
                    "peers": [
                        {
                            "name": "server1",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.33:8080/",
                            "role": "primary",
                            "auto-failover": true
                        },
                        {
                            "name": "server2",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.66:8080/",
                            "role": "secondary",
                            "auto-failover": true
                        },
                        {
                            "name": "server3",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.99:8080/",
                            "role": "backup",
                            "auto-failover": false
                        }
                    ]
                } ]
            }
        }
    ],

    "subnet4": [
        {
            "subnet": "192.0.3.0/24",
            "pools": [
                {
                    "pool": "192.0.3.100 - 192.0.3.150",
                    "client-class": "HA_server1"
                },
                {
                    "pool": "192.0.3.200 - 192.0.3.250",
                    "client-class": "HA_server2"
                }
            ],

            "option-data": [
                {
                    "name": "routers",
                    "data": "192.0.3.1"
                }
            ],

            "relay": { "ip-address": "10.1.2.3" }
        }
    ],

    ...

}

}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para>Two hook libraries must be loaded to enable HA:
        <filename>libdhcp_lease_cmds.so</filename> and
        <filename>libdhcp_ha.so</filename>. The latter provides the
        implemenation of the HA feature. The former enables control
        commands required by HA to fetch and manipulate leases on the
        remote servers. In the example provided above, it is assumed that
        Kea libraries are installed in the <filename>/usr/lib</filename>
        directory. If Kea is not installed in the /usr directory, the
        hook libraries locations must be updated accordingly.
        </para>

        <para>The HA configuration is specified within the scope of the
        <filename>libdhcp_ha.so</filename>. Note that the top level
        parameter <command>high-availability</command> is a list, even
        though it currently contains only one entry. In the future this
        configuration is likely to be extended to contain more entries,
        if the particular server can participate in more than one
        HA relationships.</para>

        <para>The following are the global parameters which control the server's
        behavior with respect to HA:
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem><para><command>this-server-name</command> - is a unique
          identifier of the server within this HA setup. It must match with one
          of the servers specified within <command>peers</command> list.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>mode</command> - specifies a HA mode
          of operation. Currently supported modes are <command>load-balancing
          </command> and <command>hot-standby</command>.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>heartbeat-delay</command> - specifies
          a duration in milliseconds between the last heartbeat (or other command sent
          to the partner) and sending the next heartbeat. The heartbeats are sent
          periodically to gather the status of the partner and to verify whether
          the partner is still operating. The default value of this parameter is
          10000 ms.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>max-response-delay</command> - specifies a
          duration in milliseconds since the last successful communication with the
          partner, after which the server assumes that the communication with
          the partner is interrupted. This duration should be greater than
          the <command>heartbeat-delay</command>. Usually it is a greater than
          the duration of multiple <command>heartbeat-delay</command> values.
          When the server detects that the communication is interrupted, it
          may transition to the <command>partner-down</command> state (when
          <command>max-unacked-clients</command> is 0) or trigger failure
          detection procedure using the values of the two parameters below.
          The default value of this parameter is 60000.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>max-ack-delay</command> - is one of
          the parameters controlling partner failure detection. When the
          communication with the partner is interrupted, the server examines values
          of the <command>secs</command> field (DHCPv4) or <command>Elapsed Time
          </command> option (DHCPv6) which denote how long the DHCP client has been
          trying to communicate with the DHCP server. This parameter specifies the
          maximum time in milliseconds for the client to try to communicate with the
          DHCP server, after which this server assumes that the client failed to
          communicate with the DHCP server (is "unacked"). The default value of
          this parameter is 10000.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>max-unacked-clients</command> - specifies
          how many "unacked" clients are allowed (see <command>max-ack-delay</command>)
          before this server assumes that the partner is offline and transitions
          to the <command>partner-down</command> state. The special value of 0
          is allowed for this parameter which disables failure detection
          mechanism. In this case, the server which can't communicate with the
          partner over the control channel assumes that the partner server is
          down and transitions to the <command>partner-down</command> state
          immediately. The default value of this parameter is 10.</para>
          </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
          The values of <command>max-ack-delay</command> and
          <command>max-unacked-clients</command> must be selected carefully, taking
          into account specifics of the network in which DHCP servers are
          operating. Note that the server in question may not respond to some
          of the DHCP clients because these clients are not to be serviced
          by this server (per administrative policy). The server may also
          drop malformed queries from the clients. Therefore, selecting too
          low value for the <command>max-unacked-clients</command> may
          result in transitioning to the <command>partner-down</command>
          state even though the partner is still operating. On the other
          hand, selecting too high value may result in never transitioning
          to the <command>partner-down</command> state if the DHCP
          traffic in the network is very low (e.g. night time), because the
          number of distinct clients trying to communicate with the server
          could be lower than <command>max-unacked-clients</command>.
        </para>

        <para>In some cases it may be useful to disable the failure detection
        mechanism altogether, if the servers are located very close to each
        other and the network partitioning is unlikely, i.e. failure to
        respond to heartbeats is only possible when the partner is offline.
        In such cases, set the <command>max-unacked-clients</command> to 0.
        </para>

        <para>The <command>peers</command> parameter contains a list of servers
        within this HA setup. In this configuration it must contain at least
        one primary and one secondary server. It may also contain unlimited
        number of backup servers. In this example there is one backup server
        which receives lease updates from the active servers.</para>

        <para>There are the following parameters specified for each of the
        peers within this list:

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem><para><command>name</command> - specifies unique name for
          the server.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>url</command> - specifies URL to be used to
          contact this server over the control channel. Other servers use this
          URL to send control commands to that server.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>role</command> - denotes the role of the
          server in the HA setup. The following roles are supported in the
          load balancing configuration: <command>primary</command>,
          <command>secondary</command> and <command>backup</command>.
          There must be exactly one primary and one secondary server in the
          load balancing setup.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><command>auto-failover</command> - a boolean value
          which denotes whether the server detecting a partner's failure should
          automatically start serving partner's clients. The default value of
          this parameter is true.</para></listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>In our example configuration, both active servers can allocate
        leases from the subnet "192.0.3.0/24". This subnet contains two
        address pools: "192.0.3.100 - 192.0.3.150" and "192.0.3.200 - 192.0.3.250",
        which are associated with HA servers scopes using client classification.
        When the <command>server1</command> processes a DHCP query it will use
        the first pool for the lease allocation. Conversely, when the
        <command>server2</command> is processing the DHCP query it will use the
        second pool. When any of the servers is in the <command>partner-down
        </command> state, it can serve leases from both pools and it will
        select the pool which is appropriate for the received query. In
        other words, if the query would normally be processed by the
        <command>server2</command>, but this server is not available, the
        <command>server1</command> will allocate the lease from the pool of
        "192.0.3.200 - 192.0.3.250".
        </para>

      </section> <!-- end of ha-load-balancing-config -->

      <section xml:id="ha-load-balancing-advanced-config">
        <title>Load Balancing with Advanced Classification</title>
        <para>In the previous section we have provided an example which demonstrated
        the load balancing configuration with the client classification limited
        to the use of <command>HA_server1</command> and <command>HA_server2</command>
        classes, which are dynamically assigned to the received DHCP queries.
        In many cases it will be required to use HA in deployments which already
        use some client classification.
        </para>
        <para>
          Suppose there is a system which classifies devices into two groups:
          phones and laptops, based on some classification criteria specified in
          Kea configuration file. Both types of devices are allocated leases
          from different address pools. Introducing HA in the load balancing mode
          is expected to result in further split of each of those pools, so as
          each of the servers can allocate leases for some part of the phones
          and part of the laptops. This requires that each of the existing pools
          should be split between the <command>HA_server1</command> and
          <command>HA_server2</command>, so we end up with the following classes:

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><simpara>phones_server1</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>laptops_server1</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>phones_server2</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>laptops_server2</simpara></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>The corresponding server configuration using advanced classification
        (and <command>member</command> expression) is provided below. For brevity
        the HA hook library configuration has been removed from this example.
<screen>
{
"Dhcp4": {

    "client-classes": [
        {
            "name": "phones",
            "test": "substring(option[60].hex,0,6) == 'Aastra'",
        },
        {
            "name": "laptops",
            "test": "not member('phones')"
        },
        {
            "name": "phones_server1",
            "test": "member('phones') and member('HA_server1')"
        },
        {
            "name": "phones_server2",
            "test": "member('phones') and member('HA_server2')"
        },
        {
            "name": "laptops_server1",
            "test": "member('laptops') and member('HA_server1')"
        },
        {
            "name": "laptops_server2",
            "test": "member('laptops') and member('HA_server2')"
        }
    ],

    "hooks-libraries": [
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_lease_cmds.so",
            "parameters": { }
        },
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_ha.so",
            "parameters": {
                "high-availability": [ {

                    ...

                } ]
            }
        }
    ],

    "subnet4": [
        {
            "subnet": "192.0.3.0/24",
            "pools": [
                {
                    "pool": "192.0.3.100 - 192.0.3.125",
                    "client-class": "phones_server1"
                },
                {
                    "pool": "192.0.3.126 - 192.0.3.150",
                    "client-class": "laptops_server1"
                },
                {
                    "pool": "192.0.3.200 - 192.0.3.225",
                    "client-class": "phones_server2"
                },
                {
                    "pool": "192.0.3.226 - 192.0.3.250",
                    "client-class": "laptops_server2"
                }
            ],

            "option-data": [
                {
                    "name": "routers",
                    "data": "192.0.3.1"
                }
            ],

            "relay": { "ip-address": "10.1.2.3" }
        }
    ],

    ...

}

}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para>The configuration provided above splits the address range into
        four pools. Two pools are dedicated to server1 and two are dedicated for
        server2. Each server can assign leases to both phones and laptops.
        Both groups of devices are assigned addresses from different pools.
        The <command>HA_server1</command> and <command>HA_server2</command>
        are builtin classes (see <xref linkend="classification-using-vendor"/>)
        and they don't need to be declared. They are assigned dynamically by
        the HA hook library as a result of load balancing algorithm. The
        <command>phones_*</command> and <command>laptop_*</command> evaluate to
        "true" when the query belongs to a given combination of other classes,
        e.g. <command>HA_server1</command> and <command>phones</command>.
        The pool will be selected accordingly as a result of such evaluation.
        </para>

        <para>Consult <xref linkend="classify"/> for details on how to use
        <command>member</command> expression and about class dependencies.</para>

      </section> <!-- end of ha-load-balancing-advanced-config -->

      <section xml:id="ha-hot-standby-config">
        <title>Hot Standby Configuration</title>
        <para>The following is the example configuration of the primary server
        in the hot standby configuration:
<screen>
{
"Dhcp4": {

    ...

    "hooks-libraries": [
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_lease_cmds.so",
            "parameters": { }
        },
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_ha.so",
            "parameters": {
                "high-availability": [ {
                    "this-server-name": "server1",
                    "mode": "hot-standby",
                    "heartbeat-delay": 10000,
                    "max-response-delay": 10000,
                    "max-ack-delay": 5000,
                    "max-unacked-clients": 5,
                    "peers": [
                        {
                            "name": "server1",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.33:8080/",
                            "role": "primary",
                            "auto-failover": true
                        },
                        {
                            "name": "server2",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.66:8080/",
                            "role": "standby",
                            "auto-failover": true
                        },
                        {
                            "name": "server3",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.99:8080/",
                            "role": "backup",
                            "auto-failover": false
                        }
                    ]
                } ]
            }
        }
    ],

    "subnet4": [
        {
            "subnet": "192.0.3.0/24",
            "pools": [
                {
                    "pool": "192.0.3.100 - 192.0.3.250",
                    "client-class": "HA_server1"
                }
            ],

            "option-data": [
                {
                    "name": "routers",
                    "data": "192.0.3.1"
                }
            ],

            "relay": { "ip-address": "10.1.2.3" }
        }
    ],

    ...

}

}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para>This configuration is very similar to the load balancing
        configuration described <xref linkend="ha-load-balancing-config"/>,
        with a few notable differences.</para>

        <para>The <command>mode</command> is now set to <command>hot-standby</command>,
        in which only one server is responding to the DHCP clients.
        If the primary server is online, the primary server is responding to
        all DHCP queries. The <command>standby</command> server takes over the
        entire DHCP traffic when it discovers that the primary is unavailable.
        </para>

        <para>In this mode, the non-primary active server is called
        <command>standby</command> and that's what the role of the second
        active server is set to.</para>

        <para>Finally, because there is always one server responding to the
        DHCP queries, there is only one scope <command>HA_server1</command>
        in use within pools definitions. In fact, the <command>client-class</command>
        parameter could be removed from this configuration without harm,
        because there are no conflicts in lease allocations by different
        servers as they do not allocate leases concurrently. The
        <command>client-class</command> is left in this example mostly for
        demonstration purposes, to highlight the differences between the
        hot standby and load balancing mode of operation.</para>
      </section> <!-- end of ha-hot-standby-config -->

      <section xml:id="ha-sharing-lease-info">
        <title>Lease Information Sharing</title>
        <para>An HA enabled server informs its active partner about allocated
        or renewed leases by sending appropriate control commands. The partner
        updates the lease information in its own database. When the server starts
        up for the first time or recovers after a failure it synchronizes its
        lease database with the partner. These two mechanisms  guarantee
        consistency of the lease information between the servers and allow for
        designating one of the servers to handle the entire DHCP traffic in
        case the other server becomes unavailable.</para>

        <para>In some cases, though, it is desired to disable lease updates
        and/or database synchronization between the active servers if the
        exchange of information about the allocated leases is performed
        using some other mechanism. Kea supports various types of databases
        to be used as a storage for leases, e.g. MySQL, Postgres, Cassandra.
        Those databases include builtin solutions for data replication which
        are often used by Kea users to provide redundancy.</para>

        <para>The HA hook library supports such scenarios by allowing to
        disable lease updates over the control channel and/or lease database
        synchronization, leaving the server to rely on the database replication
        mechanism. This is controlled by the two boolean parameters:
        <command>send-lease-updates</command> and <command>sync-leases</command>,
        which values default to true:

<screen>
{
"Dhcp4": {

    ...

    "hooks-libraries": [
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_lease_cmds.so",
            "parameters": { }
        },
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_ha.so",
            "parameters": {
                "high-availability": [ {
                    "this-server-name": "server1",
                    "mode": "load-balancing",
                    "send-lease-updates": false,
                    "sync-leases": false,
                    "peers": [
                        {
                            "name": "server1",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.33:8080/",
                            "role": "primary"
                        },
                        {
                            "name": "server2",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.66:8080/",
                            "role": "secondary"
                        }
                    ]
                } ]
            }
        }
    ],

    ...

}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para>
          In the most typical use case, both parameters are set to the same
          value, i.e. both are <command>false</command> if the database
          replication is in use, or both are <command>true</command> otherwise.
          Introducing two separate parameters to control lease updates and
          lease database synchronization is aimed at possible special use
          cases, e.g. synchronization is performed by copying a lease file
          (therefore the <command>sync-leases</command> is set to
          <command>false</command>), but lease updates should be conducted
          as usual (<command>send-lease-updates</command> set to
          <command>true</command>). It should be noted that Kea doesn't
          natively support such use case, but users may develop their own
          scripts and tools around Kea to provide such mechanisms. The HA
          hooks library configuration is designed to maximize the administration
          flexibility.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ha-syncing-page-limit">
        <title>Controlling Lease Page Size Limit</title>
        <para>An HA enabled server initiates synchronization of the lease
        database after down time or upon receiving <command>ha-sync</command>
        command. The server uses commands described in
        <xref linkend="lease-get-page-cmds"/> to fetch leases from the
        partner server (lease queries). The size of the results page
        (maximum number of leases to be returned in a single response to one
        of these commands) can be controlled via HA hooks library configuration.
        Increasing the page size decreases the number of lease queries sent to
        the partner server, but it causes the partner server to generate
        larger responses, which lengthens transmission time as well as
        memory and CPU utilization on both servers. Decreasing the
        page size helps to decrease resources utilization but requires
        more lease queries to be issued to fetch the entire lease
        database.</para>
        <para>The default value of the <command>sync-page-limit</command>
        controlling the page size is 10000. This means that the entire
        lease database can be fetched with a single command if the
        size of this database is equal or lower than 10000.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ha-syncing-timeouts">
        <title>Discussion about Timeouts</title>
        <para>In deployments with large number of clients connected to the
        network, lease database synchronization after the server failure
        may be a time consuming operation. The synchronizing server needs
        to gather all leases from the partner which yields a large response
        over the RESTful interface. The server receives leases using the
        paging mechanism described in <xref linkend="ha-syncing-page-limit"/>.
        Before the page of leases is fetched, the synchronizing server
        sends a <command>dhcp-disable</command> command to disable the DHCP
        service on the partner server. If the service is already disabled, this
        command will reset the timeout for the DHCP service being disabled.
        This timeout value is by default set to 60 seconds. If fetching a
        single page of leases takes longer, the partner server will assume that
        the synchronizing server died and will resume its DHCP service.
        The connection of the synchronizing server with its partner is also
        guarded with the timeout. If the synchronization of a single page
        of leases takes longer than 60 seconds the synchronizing server
        terminates the connection and the synchronization fails.
        Both timeout values are controlled by a single configuration
        parameter <command>sync-timeout</command>. The following
        configuration snippet deminstrates how to modify the timeout for
        automatic re-enabling of the DHCP service on the partner server
        and the timeout for fetching a single page of leases from 60 seconds
        to 90 seconds:
<screen>
{
"Dhcp4": {

    ...

    "hooks-libraries": [
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_lease_cmds.so",
            "parameters": { }
        },
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_ha.so",
            "parameters": {
                "high-availability": [ {
                    "this-server-name": "server1",
                    "mode": "load-balancing",
                    "sync-timeout": 90000,
                    "peers": [
                        {
                            "name": "server1",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.33:8080/",
                            "role": "primary"
                        },
                        {
                            "name": "server2",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.66:8080/",
                            "role": "secondary"
                        }
                    ]
                } ]
            }
        }
    ],

    ...

}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para>
          It is important to note that extending this value may sometimes
          be insufficient to prevent issues with timeouts during
          lease database synchronization. The control commands travel via
          Control Agent, which also monitors incoming (with synchronizing
          server) and outgoing (with DHCP server) connections for timeouts.
          The DHCP server also monitors the connection from the Control
          Agent for timeouts. Those timeouts can't be currently modified
          via configuration. Extending these timeouts is only possible by
          modifing them in the Kea code and recompiling the server. The
          relevant constants are located in the Kea sources:
          <filename>src/lib/config/timeouts.h</filename>.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ha-pause-state-machine">
        <title>Pausing HA State Machine</title>
        <para>The high availability state machine includes many different
        states described in detail in <xref linkend="ha-server-states"/>.
        The server enters each state when certain conditions are met, most
        often taking into account the partner server's state. In some states
        the server performs specific actions, e.g. synchronization of the
        lease database in the <command>syncing</command> state or responding
        to DHCP queries according to the configured mode of operation in the
        <command>load-balancing</command> and <command>hot-standby</command>
        states.
        </para>
        <para>
          By default, transitions between the states are performed
          automatically and the server administrator has no direct control
          when the transitions take place and, in most cases, the
          administrator doesn't need such control. In some situations,
          however, the administrator may want to "pause" the HA state
          machine in a selected state to perform some additional administrative
          actions before the server transitions to the next state.
        </para>

        <para>Consider a server failure which results in a loss of the entire
        lease database. Typically, the server will rebuild its lease database
        when it enters the <command>syncing</command> state by querying
        the partner server for leases, but it is possible that the
        partner was also experiencing a failure and lacks lease information.
        In this case, it may be required to reconstruct lease databases on
        both servers from some external source, e.g. a backup server. If the
        lease database is going to be reconstructed via RESTful API, the
        servers should be started in the initial, i.e. <command>waiting</command>
        state and remain in this state while leases are being added. In
        particular, the servers should not attempt to synchronize their lease
        databases nor start serving DHCP clients.
        </para>

        <para>The HA hooks library provides configuration parameters and a
        command to control when the HA state machine should be paused and
        resumed. The following configuration will cause the HA state machine
        to pause in the <command>waiting</command> state after server startup.
<screen>
"Dhcp4": {

    ...

    "hooks-libraries": [
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_lease_cmds.so",
            "parameters": { }
        },
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_ha.so",
            "parameters": {
                "high-availability": [ {
                    "this-server-name": "server1",
                    "mode": "load-balancing",
                    "peers": [
                        {
                            "name": "server1",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.33:8080/",
                            "role": "primary"
                        },
                        {
                            "name": "server2",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.66:8080/",
                            "role": "secondary"
                        }
                    ],
                    "state-machine": {
                        "states":  [
                            {
                                "state": "waiting",
                                "pause": "once"
                            }
                        ]
                    }
                } ]
            }
        }
    ],

    ...

}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para>The <command>pause</command> parameter value <command>once</command>
        denotes that the state machine should be paused upon the first transition
        to the <command>waiting</command> state. Later transitions to this state
        won't cause the state machine to pause. Two other supported values of the
        <command>pause</command> parameter are: <command>always</command> and
        <command>never</command>. The latter is the default value for each state,
        which instructs the server to never pause the state machine.
        </para>

        <para>In order to "unpause" the state machine the <command>ha-continue</command>
        command must be sent to the paused server. This command does not take
        any arguments. See <xref linkend="ha-control-commands"/> for details
        about commands specific for HA hooks library.
        </para>

        <para>It is possible to configure the state machine to pause in more than
        one state. Consider the following configuration.
<screen>
"Dhcp4": {

    ...

    "hooks-libraries": [
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_lease_cmds.so",
            "parameters": { }
        },
        {
            "library": "/usr/lib/hooks/libdhcp_ha.so",
            "parameters": {
                "high-availability": [ {
                    "this-server-name": "server1",
                    "mode": "load-balancing",
                    "peers": [
                        {
                            "name": "server1",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.33:8080/",
                            "role": "primary"
                        },
                        {
                            "name": "server2",
                            "url": "http://192.168.56.66:8080/",
                            "role": "secondary"
                        }
                    ],
                    "state-machine": {
                        "states": [
                            {
                                "state": "ready",
                                "pause": "always"
                            },
                            {
                                "state": "partner-down",
                                "pause": "once"
                            }
                        ]
                    }
                } ]
            }
        }
    ],

    ...

}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para>This configuration instructs the server to pause the state
        machine every time it transitions to the <command>ready</command> state
        and upon the first transition to the <command>partner-down</command>
        state.</para>

        <para>Refer to the <xref linkend="ha-server-states"/> for a complete of
        list of server states. The state machine can be paused in any of the
        supported states, however it is not practical for the
        <command>backup</command> and <command>terminated</command> states because
        the server never transitions out of these states anyway.
        </para>

        <note><para>In the <command>syncing</command> state the server is paused
        before it makes an attempt to synchronize lease database with a partner.
        In order to pause the state machine after lease database synchronization,
        use the <command>ready</command> state instead.
        </para></note>

        <note><para>The state of the HA state machine depends on the state of the
        cooperating server. Therefore, it must be taken into account that
        pausing the state machine of one server may affect the operation of the
        partner server. For example: if the primary server is paused in the
        <command>waiting</command> state the partner server will also remain in
        the <command>waiting</command> state until the state machine of the
        primary server is resumed and that server transitions to the
        <command>ready</command> state.</para></note>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ha-ctrl-agent-config">
        <title>Control Agent Configuration</title>
        <para>The <xref linkend="kea-ctrl-agent"/> describes in detail the
        Kea deamon which provides RESTful interface to control Kea servers.
        The same functionality is used by High Availability hook library to
        establish communication between the HA peers. Therefore, the HA
        library requires that Control Agent is started for each DHCP
        instance within HA setup. If the Control Agent is not started
        the peers will not be able to communicate with the particular DHCP
        server (even if the DHCP server itself is online) and may eventually
        consider this server to be offline.
        </para>

        <para>The following is the example configuration for the CA running
        on the same machine as the primary server. This configuration is
        valid for both load balancing and hot standby cases presented in
        previous sections.

<screen>
{
"Control-agent": {
    "http-host": "192.168.56.33",
    "http-port": 8080,

    "control-sockets": {
        "dhcp4": {
            "socket-type": "unix",
            "socket-name": "/tmp/kea-dhcp4-ctrl.sock"
        },
        "dhcp6": {
            "socket-type": "unix",
            "socket-name": "/tmp/kea-dhcp6-ctrl.sock"
        }
    }
}
}
</screen>
        </para>
      </section> <!-- end of ha-ctrl-agent-config -->

      <section xml:id="ha-control-commands">
        <title>Control Commands for High Availability</title>
        <para>Even though the HA hook library is designed to automatically
        resolve issues with DHCP service interruptions by redirecting the
        DHCP traffic to a surviving server and synchronizing the lease
        database when required, it may be useful for the administrator to
        have control over the server behavior. In particular, it may be
        useful be able to trigger lease database synchronization on demand.
        It may also be useful to manually set the HA scopes that are being
        served.</para>

        <para>Note that the backup server can sometimes be used to handle
        the DHCP traffic in case if both active servers are down. The backup
        servers do not perform failover function automatically. Hence, in
        order to use the backup server to respond to the DHCP queries,
        the server administrator must enable this function manually.
        </para>

        <para>The following sections describe commands supported by the
        HA hook library which are available for the administrator.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="command-ha-sync">
          <title>ha-sync command</title>
          <para>The <command>ha-sync</command> is issued to instruct the
          server to synchronize its local lease database with the
          selected peer. The server fetches all leases from the peer and
          updates those locally stored leases which are older comparing to
          those fetched. It also creates new leases when any of those
          fetched do not exist in the local database. All leases that
          are not returned by the peer but are in the local database are
          preserved. The database synchronization is unidirectional, i.e.
          only the database on the server to which the command has been
          sent is updated. In order to synchronize the peer's database a
          separate <command>ha-sync</command> has to be issued to that
          peer.</para>

          <para>The database synchronization may be triggered for
          both active and backup server type. The <command>ha-sync</command>
          has the following structure (DHCPv4 server case):
<screen>
{
    "command": "ha-sync",
    "service": [ "dhcp4 "],
    "arguments": {
        "server-name": "server2",
        "max-period": 60
    }
}
</screen>
          </para>

          <para>
            When the server receives this command it first disables the
            DHCP service of the server from which it will be fetching leases,
            i.e. sends <command>dhcp-disable</command> command to that server.
            The <command>max-period</command> parameter specifies the maximum
            duration (in seconds) for which the DHCP service should be disabled.
            If the DHCP service is successfully disabled, the synchronizing
            server will fetch leases from the remote server by issuing one or
            more <command>lease4-get-page</command> commands. When the lease
            database synchronization is complete, the synchronizing server sends
            the <command>dhcp-enable</command> to the peer to re-enable its
            DHCP service.
          </para>

          <para>The <command>max-period</command> value should be sufficiently
          long to guarantee that it doesn't elapse before the synchronization
          is completed. Otherwise, the DHCP server will automatically enable
          its DHCP function while the synchronization is still in progress.
          If the DHCP server subsequently allocates any leases during the
          synchronization, those new (or updated) leases will not be fetched
          by the synchronizing server leading to database inconsistencies.
          </para>
        </section> <!-- ha-sync-command -->

        <section xml:id="command-ha-scopes">
          <title>ha-scopes command</title>
          <para>This command allows for modifying the HA scopes that the
          server is serving. Consult <xref linkend="ha-load-balancing-config"/>
          and <xref linkend="ha-hot-standby-config"/> to learn what scopes
          are available for different HA modes of operation. The
          <command>ha-scopes</command> command has the following structure
          (DHCPv4 server case):
<screen>
{
    "command": "ha-scopes",
    "service": [ "dhcp4" ],
    "arguments": {
        "scopes": [ "HA_server1", "HA_server2" ]
    }
}
</screen>
          </para>

          <para>This command configures the server to handle traffic from
          both <command>HA_server1</command> and <command>HA_server2</command>
          scopes. In order to disable all scopes specify an empty list:

<screen>
{
    "command": "ha-scopes",
    "service": [ "dhcp4 "],
    "arguments": {
        "scopes": [ ]
    }
}
</screen>
          </para>
        </section> <!-- ha-scopes-command -->

        <section xml:id="command-ha-continue">
        <title>ha-continue command</title>
        <para>This command is used to resume the operation of the paused HA
        state machine as described in the <xref linkend="ha-pause-state-machine"/>.
        It takes no arguments, so the command structure is as simple as:
<screen>
{
    "command": "ha-continue"
}
</screen>
      </para>
        </section> <!-- ha-continue-command -->

      </section> <!-- ha-control-commands -->

    </section> <!-- end of high-availability-library -->
