<section xml:id="hooks-stat-cmds">
  <title>stat_cmds: Supplemental Statistics Commands</title>
  <para>
    This library provides additional statistics commands for
    retrieving lease statistics from Kea DHCP servers. These commands
    were added to address an issue with obtaining accurate lease
    statistics in deployments running multiple Kea servers that use a
    shared lease backend. The in-memory statistics kept by individual
    servers only track lease changes made by that server; thus, in a
    deployment with multiple servers (e.g. two kea-dhcp6 servers using the
    same PostgreSQL database for lease storage), these statistics are incomplete.
    The MySQL and PostgreSQL backends were modified in Kea to track
    lease allocation changes as they occur via database triggers. Additionally,
    all four lease backends were extended to support retrieving lease
    statistics for all subnets, a single subnet, or a range of subnets.
    Finally, this library was constructed to provide commands for retrieving
    these statistics.

    <note>
      <para>This library may only be loaded by the <command>kea-dhcp4</command>
      or the <command>kea-dhcp6</command> process.
      </para>
    </note>
  </para>

  <para>
    The commands currently provided by this library are:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>stat-lease4-get</command> - fetches DHCPv4 lease statistics</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>stat-lease6-get</command> - fetches DHCPv6 lease statistics</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
    The Stat commands library is part of the open source code and is
    available to every Kea user.
  </para>

  <para>
    All commands use JSON syntax and can be issued directly to
    the servers via either the control channel (see <xref linkend="ctrl-channel"/>)
    or the Control Agent (see <xref linkend="kea-ctrl-agent"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
    This library may be loaded by both kea-dhcp4 and kea-dhcp6 servers.
    It is loaded in the same way as other libraries and currently has
    no parameters:
  </para>
<para>
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { <userinput>
    "hooks-libraries": [
        {
            "library": "/path/libdhcp_stat_cmds.so"
        }
        ...
    ] </userinput>
}
</screen>
</para>

  <para>
    In a deployment with multiple Kea DHCP servers sharing a common lease
    storage, it may be loaded by any or all of the servers. However, one
    thing to keep in mind is that a server's response to a stat-lease{4/6}-get
    command will only contain data for subnets known to that server. In
    other words, if a subnet does not appear in a server's configuration, Kea
    will not retrieve statistics for it.
 </para>

<section id="command-stat-lease4-get">
  <title>stat-lease4-get, stat-lease6-get Commands</title>
    <para id="command-stat-lease6-get">
      The <command>stat-lease4-get</command> and <command>stat-lease6-get</command>
      commands fetch lease statistics for a range of known subnets. The
      range of subnets is determined through the use of optional command
      input parameters:
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><command>subnet-id</command> - The ID of the subnet for which
            lease statistics should be fetched. Use this to get statistics for
            a single subnet. If the subnet does not exist, the command result
            code will be 3 (i.e. CONTROL_RESULT_EMPTY).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><command>subnet-range</command> - A pair of subnet IDs which
            describe an inclusive range of subnets for which statistics should
            be retrieved. Note that fuzzy values are supported, thus allowing
            for a query for statistics using approximate ID values. If the
            range does not include any known subnets, the command result code
            will be 3 (i.e. CONTROL_RESULT_EMPTY).
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><command>first-subnet-id</command> - The ID of the first
                subnet in the range.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><command>last-subnet-id</command> - The ID of the last
                subnet in the range.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        The use of subnet-id and subnet-range are mutually exclusive.
        If no parameters are given, the result will contain data for all
        known subnets. Note that in configurations with large numbers of
        subnets, this can result in a large response.
    </para>
    <para>
      The following command would fetch lease statistics for all known subnets from a kea-dhcp4 server:
<screen>
{
  "command": "stat-lease4-get"
}
</screen>
    </para>
    <para>
        The following command would fetch lease statistcis for subnet ID 10 from a kea-dhcp6 server:
<screen>
{
  "command": "stat-lease6-get",
  "arguments": {
    "subnet-id" : 10
  }
}
</screen>
    </para>
    <para>
        The following command would fetch lease statistics for all subnets from subnet IDs 10 through 50 from a kea-dhcp4 server:
<screen>
{
  "command": "stat-lease4-get",
  "arguments": {
    "subnet-range" {
      "first-subnet-id": 10,
      "last-subnet-id": 50,
    }
  }
}
</screen>
    </para>

    <para>
      The response to either command will contain three elements:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><command>result</command> - a numeric value indicating the outcome of the
          command where:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><simpara><command>0</command> - the command was successful;</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara><command>1</command> - an error occurred, an explanation will
            be the "text" element;</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara><command>2</command> - the fetch found no matching data</simpara></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><command>text</command> - an explanation of the command outcome. When the command
      succeeds it will contain the command name along with the number of rows returned.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><command>arguments</command> - a map containing the data returned by the
          command as the element "result-set", which is patterned after SQL statement responses:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><command>columns</command> - a list of text column labels
            The columns returned for DHCPv4 are:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><simpara><command>subnet-id</command> - ID of the subnet.</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara><command>total-addresses</command> - total number of addresses
              available for DHCPv4 management in the subnet. In other words, this is the sum of all
              addresses in all the configured pools in the subnet.</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara><command>assigned-addresses</command> - number of addresses
              in the subnet that are currently assigned to a client.</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara><command>declined-addresses</command> - number of addresses
              in the subnet that are currently declined and are thus unavailable for assignment.
              </simpara></listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
          <listitem><para>The columns returned for DHCPv6 are:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><simpara><command>subnet-id</command> - ID of the subnet.</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara><command>total-nas</command> - number of NA addresses available
              for DHCPv6 management in the subnet. In other words, this is the sum of all
              the NA addresses in the all configured NA pools in the subnet.</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara><command>assigned-nas</command> - number of NA addresses in a
              the subnet that are currently assigned to a client.</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara><command>declined-nas</command> - number of NA addresses that
              are currently declined and are thus unavailable for assignment.</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara><command>total-pds</command> - total number of prefixes available
              of DHCPv6 management in the subnet. In other words, this is the sum of all prefixes
              in all the configured prefix pools in the subnet.</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara><command>assigned-pds</command> - number of prefixes in the subnet
              that are currently assigned to a client.</simpara></listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>rows</command> - a list of rows, one per subnet ID. Each row
            contains a data value corresponding to and in the same order as each column
            listed in "columns" for a given subnet.
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>timestamp</command> - textual date and time the data was fetched,
            expressed as GMT.</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
      The response to a DHCPv4 command might look as follows:
<screen>
  {
    "result": 0,
    "text": "stat-lease4-get: 2 rows found",
    "arguments": {
      "result-set": {
        "columns": [ "subnet-id", "total-addresses", "assigned-addresses", "declined-addresses" ]
        "rows": [
          [ 10, 256, 111, 0 ],
          [ 20, 4098, 2034, 4 ]
        ],
      "timestamp": "2018-05-04 15:03:37.000000"
      }
    }
  }
</screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      The response to a DHCPv6 command might look as follows (subnet 10 has no
      prefix pools, subnet 20 has no NA pools, and subnet 30 has both NA and PD
      pools):
<screen>
  {
    "result": 0,
    "text": "stat-lease6-get: 2 rows found",
    "arguments": {
      "result-set": {
        "columns": [ "subnet-id", "total-nas", "assigned-nas", "declined-nas", "total-pds", "assigned-pds" ]
        "rows": [
          [ 10, 4096, 2400, 3, 0, 0],
          [ 20, 0, 0, 0, 1048, 233 ]
          [ 30, 256, 60, 0, 1048, 15 ]
        ],
      "timestamp": "2018-05-04 15:03:37.000000"
      }
    }
  }
</screen>
    </para>

</section>
</section>
