<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2018-2019 Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, you can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
 -
 - This license applies to the documentation itself, not the software.
-->

<!-- need this include to make the &keaversion; macro work -->
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % keaversion SYSTEM "version.ent">
%keaversion;
]>

<section xml:id="hooks-radius">
  <title>radius: RADIUS Server Support</title>
  <para>
    The RADIUS hook library allows Kea to interact with two types of
    RADIUS servers: access and accounting. Although the most common
    DHCP and RADIUS integration is done on the DHCP relay-agent level
    (DHCP clients send DHCP packets to DHCP relays; those relays contact
    the RADIUS server and depending on the response either send the packet
    to the DHCP server or drop it), it does require DHCP relay
    hardware to support RADIUS communication. Also, even if the relay
    has the necessary support, it is often not flexible enough to send and
    receive additional RADIUS attributes. As such, the alternative
    looks more appealing: to extend the DHCP server to talk to RADIUS
    directly. That is the goal this library intends to fulfill.

    <note>
      <para>This library may only be loaded by the <command>kea-dhcp4</command>
      or the <command>kea-dhcp6</command> process.
      </para>
    </note>
  </para>
  <para>
    The major feature of the hook library is the ability to use RADIUS
    authorization. When a DHCP packet is received, the Kea server
    sends an Access-Request to the RADIUS server and waits for
    a response. The server then sends back either an Access-Accept
    with specific client attributes, or an Access-Reject. There are two
    cases supported here: first, the Access-Accept includes a
    Framed-IP-Address (for DHCPv4) or Framed-IPv6-Address (for
    DHCPv6), which will be interpreted by Kea as an instruction to
    assign that specified IPv4 or IPv6 address. This effectively
    means RADIUS can act as an address-reservation database.
  </para>
  <para>
    The second case supported is the ability to assign clients to
    specific pools based on a RADIUS response. In this case, the RADIUS
    server sends back an Access-Accept with Framed-Pool (IPv4) or
    Framed-IPv6-Pool (IPv6). In both cases, Kea interprets those
    attributes as client classes. With the addition of the
    ability to limit access to pools to specific classes (see <xref
    linkend="classification-pools"/>), RADIUS can be used to force the client
    to be assigned a dynamic address from a specific pool. Furthermore,
    the same mechanism can be used to control what kind of options the
    client will get if there are DHCP options specified for a
    particular class.
  </para>

  <section id="hooks-radius-install">
    <title>Compilation and Installation of the RADIUS Hook</title>
    <para>
      The following section describes how to compile and install the
      software on CentOS 7.0. Other systems may differ slightly.
    </para>

    <para>
      STEP 1: Install dependencies
    </para>
    <para>
      Several tools are needed to build dependencies and Kea
      itself. The following commands should install them:
<screen>
$ sudo rpm -Uvh https://dl.fedoraproject.org/pub/epel/epel-release-latest-7.noarch.rpm
$ sudo yum install gcc-g++ openssl-devel log4cplus-devel wget git
</screen>
    </para>

    <para>
      STEP 2: FreeRADIUS installation
    </para>
      <para>
      The Kea RADIUS hook library uses the FreeRADIUS client library to
      conduct RADIUS communication. Unfortunately, the standard
      1.1.7 release available from the project website
      <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xlink:href="http://freeradius.org/sub_projects/">http://freeradius.org/sub_projects/</uri>
      has several serious deficiencies; ISC engineers observed a segmentation
      fault during testing. Also, the base version of the library does
      not offer asynchronous transmissions, which are essential for
      effective accounting implementation. Both of these issues
      were addressed by ISC engineers, and the changes have been
      reported to the FreeRADIUS client project. Acceptance of those
      changes is outside of ISC's control, so until those
      are processed, it is strongly recommended to use the FreeRADIUS
      client with ISC's patches. To download and compile this version, please use
      the following steps:
<screen>
$ git clone https://github.com/fxdupont/freeradius-client.git
$ cd freeradius-client/
$ git checkout iscdev
$ ./configure
$ make
$ sudo make install
</screen>

      You may pass additional parameters to the configure script, if you need
      to. Once installed, the FreeRADIUS client will be installed in
      /usr/local. This is the default path where Kea will be looking for
      it. You may install it in a different directory; if you choose to do
      so, make sure you add that path to the configure script when compiling Kea.
      </para>

      <para>
        STEP 3: Install recent BOOST version
      </para>

      <para>
        Kea requires a reasonably recent Boost version. Unfortunately,
        the version available in CentOS 7 is too old, so a
        newer Boost version is necessary. Furthermore, CentOS 7 has an
        old version of the g++ compiler that does not handle the latest Boost
        versions. Fortunately, Boost 1.65 meets both requirements; it is both
        recent enough for Kea and able to be compiled using
        the g++ 4.8 version in CentOS.
      </para>
      <para>
        To download and compile Boost 1.65, please use the following
        commands:
<screen>
$ wget -nd https://dl.bintray.com/boostorg/release/1.65.1/source/boost_1_65_1.tar.gz
$ tar zxvf boost_1_65_1.tar.gz
$ cd boost_1_65_1/
$ ./bootstrap.sh
$ ./b2 --without-python
$ sudo ./b2 install
</screen>
        Note that the b2 script may optionally take extra parameters; one
        of them specifies the destination path where the sources are to
        be compiled.
      </para>

      <para>
        STEP 4: Compile and install Kea
      </para>

      <para>
        Obtain the Kea sources either by downloading them from the git repository or extracting the tarball:
<screen>
# Use one of those commands to obtain the Kea sources:

# Choice 1: get from github
$ git clone https://github.com/isc-projects/kea

# Get a tarball and extract it
$ tar zxvf kea-&keaversion;.tar.gz
</screen>

The next step is to extract the premium Kea package that contains the RADIUS repository
into the Kea sources. After the tarball is extracted, the Kea sources should have
a premium/ subdirectory.

<screen>
  $ cd kea
  $ tar zxvf ../kea-premium-radius-&keaversion;.tar.gz
</screen>

Once this is done, verify that the Kea sources look similar to this:
<screen>
$ ls -l
total 952
-rw-r--r--   1 thomson  staff    6192 Apr 25 17:38 AUTHORS
-rw-r--r--   1 thomson  staff   29227 Apr 25 17:38 COPYING
-rw-r--r--   1 thomson  staff  360298 Apr 25 20:00 ChangeLog
-rw-r--r--   1 thomson  staff     645 Apr 25 17:38 INSTALL
-rw-r--r--   1 thomson  staff    5015 Apr 25 17:38 Makefile.am
-rw-r--r--   1 thomson  staff     587 Apr 25 17:38 README
drwxr-xr-x   5 thomson  staff     170 Apr 26 19:04 compatcheck
-rw-r--r--   1 thomson  staff   62323 Apr 25 17:38 configure.ac
drwxr-xr-x  12 thomson  staff     408 Apr 26 19:04 doc
drwxr-xr-x   7 thomson  staff     238 Apr 25 17:38 examples
drwxr-xr-x   5 thomson  staff     170 Apr 26 19:04 ext
drwxr-xr-x   8 thomson  staff     272 Apr 26 19:04 m4macros
drwxr-xr-x  20 thomson  staff     680 Apr 26 11:22 <userinput>premium</userinput>
drwxr-xr-x  10 thomson  staff     340 Apr 26 19:04 src
drwxr-xr-x  14 thomson  staff     476 Apr 26 19:04 tools
</screen>

The makefiles must be regenerated using autoreconf.</para>

<para>The next step is to configure Kea, and there are several essential steps necessary here.
Running autoreconf -if is necessary to compile the premium package that contains
RADIUS. Also, the --with-freeradius option is necessary to tell Kea where the FreeRADIUS
client sources can be found. Also, since the non-standard Boost is used, the path
to it must be specified.</para>

<screen>
$ autoreconf -i
$ ./configure --with-freeradius=/path/to/freeradius --with-boost-include=/path/to/boost --with-boost-lib-dir=/path/to/boost/state/lib
</screen>

<para>
For example, assuming the FreeRADIUS client was installed in the default directory (/usr/local)
and the Boost 1.65 sources were compiled in /home/thomson/devel/boost1_65_1, the configure path
should look as follows:</para>

<screen>
./configure --with-freeradius=/usr/local \
            --with-boost-include=/home/thomson/devel/boost_1_65_1 \
            --with-boost-lib-dir=/home/thomson/devel/boost_1_65_1/stage/lib
</screen>

<para>
  After some checks, the configure script should print a report similar to the
  following:

<screen>

       Kea source configure results:
    -=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-

Package:
  Name:              kea
  Version:           &keaversion;
  Extended version:  &keaversion; (tarball)
  OS Family:         Linux

  Hooks directory:   /usr/local/lib/hooks
  Premium hooks:     yes
  Included Hooks:    forensic_log flex_id host_cmds subnet_cmds radius host_cache

C++ Compiler:
  CXX:             g++ --std=c++11
  CXX_VERSION:     g++ (GCC) 4.8.5 20150623 (Red Hat 4.8.5-16)
  CXX_STANDARD:    201103
  DEFS:            -DHAVE_CONFIG_H
  CPPFLAGS:         -DOS_LINUX  -DBOOST_ASIO_HEADER_ONLY
  CXXFLAGS:        -g -O2
  LDFLAGS:          -lpthread
  KEA_CXXFLAGS:     -Wall -Wextra -Wnon-virtual-dtor -Wwrite-strings -Woverloaded-virtual -Wno-sign-compare -pthread -Wno-missing-field-initializers -fPIC

Python:
  PYTHON_VERSION:  not needed (because kea-shell is disabled)

Boost:
  BOOST_VERSION:   1.65.1
  BOOST_INCLUDES:  -I/home/thomson/devel/boost_1_65_1
  BOOST_LIBS:      -L/home/thomson/devel/boost_1_65_1/stage/lib  -lboost_system

OpenSSL:
  CRYPTO_VERSION:  OpenSSL 1.0.2k  26 Jan 2017
  CRYPTO_CFLAGS:
  CRYPTO_INCLUDES:
  CRYPTO_LDFLAGS:
  CRYPTO_LIBS:     -lcrypto

Botan: no

Log4cplus:
  LOG4CPLUS_VERSION:  1.1.3
  LOG4CPLUS_INCLUDES: -I/usr/include
  LOG4CPLUS_LIBS:     -L/usr/lib -L/usr/lib64 -llog4cplus

Flex/bison:
  FLEX:  flex
  BISON: bison -y

MySQL:
  no

PostgreSQL:
  no

Cassandra CQL:
  no
Google Test:
  no
Google Benchmark:
  no

FreeRADIUS client:
  FREERADIUS_INCLUDE:    -I/usr/local/include
  FREERADIUS_LIB:        -L/usr/local/lib -lfreeradius-client
  FREERADIUS_DICTIONARY: /usr/local/etc/radiusclient/dictionary

Developer:
  Enable Debugging:       no
  Google Tests:           no
  Valgrind:               not found
  C++ Code Coverage:      no
  Logger checks:          no
  Generate Documentation: no
  Parser Generation:      no
  Kea-shell:              no
  Perfdhcp:               no
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Please make sure that your compilation has the following:

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>RADIUS listed in Included Hooks;</listitem>
  <listitem>FreeRADIUS client directories printed and pointing to the right
  directories;</listitem>
  <listitem>Boost version at least 1.65.1. The versions available
  in CentOS 7 (1.48 and and 1.53) are too old.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

<para>
  Once your configuration is complete, compile Kea using make. If your system has
  more than one core, it is recommended that you use the "-j N" option to speed up the build.
  <screen>
    $ make -j5
    $ sudo make install</screen>

      </para>
  </section>


  <section id="hooks-radius-config">
    <title>RADIUS Hook Configuration</title>

    <para>
      The RADIUS hook is a library that has to be loaded by either DHCPv4 or
      DHCPv6 Kea servers. Unlike some other available hook libraries, this one
      takes many parameters. For example, this configuration
      could be used:

<screen>
  "Dhcp4": {

  // Your regular DHCPv4 configuration parameters here.

  "hooks-libraries": [
  {
      // Note that RADIUS requires host-cache for proper operation,
      // so that library is loaded as well.
      "library": "/usr/local/lib/hooks/libdhcp_host_cache.so"
  },
  {
      "library": "/usr/local/lib/hooks/libdhc_radius.so",
      "parameters": {

          // Specify where FreeRADIUS dictionary could be located
          "dictionary": "/usr/local/etc/freeradius/dictionary",

          // Specify which address to use to communicate with RADIUS servers
          "bindaddr": "*",

          // more RADIUS parameters here
      }
  } ]</screen>
    </para>

    <para>
      RADIUS is a complicated environment. As such, it's not really possible
      to provide a default configuration that would work out of the box.
      However, we do have one example that showcases some of the more
      common features. Please see doc/examples/kea4/hooks-radius.json in your
      Kea sources.
    </para>

    <para>
      The RADIUS hook library supports the following global configuration
      flags, which correspond to FreeRADIUS client library options:

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><simpara><command>bindaddr</command> (default "*") specifies
        the address to be used by the hook library in communication with RADIUS
        servers. The "*" special value tells the kernel to choose
        the address.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>canonical-mac-address</command> (default
      false) specifies whether MAC addresses in attributes follow the canonical
      RADIUS format (lowercase pairs of hexadecimal digits separated by
      '-').</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>client-id-pop0</command> (default false), used
      with flex-id, removes the leading zero (or pair of zeroes in DHCPv6) type in
      client-id (aka duid in DHCPv6). Implied by
      client-id-printable.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>client-id-printable</command> (default false)
      checks whether the client-id/duid content is printable and uses it as is
      instead of in hexadecimal. Implies client-id-pop0 and extract-duid as 0
      and 255 are not printable.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>deadtime</command> (default 0) is a mechanism
      to try unresponsive servers after responsive servers. Its value
      specifies the number of seconds after which a server is considered not to have answered,
      so 0 disables the mechanism. As the asynchronous communication does not
      use locks or atomics, it is recommended that you do not use this feature when running in this mode.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>dictionary</command> (default set by configure
      at build time) is the attribute and value dictionary. Note that it is a
      critical parameter.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>extract-duid</command> (default true) extracts
      the embedded duid from an RFC 4361-compliant DHCPv4 client-id. Implied by
      client-id-printable.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>identifier-type4</command> (default client-id)
      specifies the identifier type to build the User-Name attribute. It should
      be the same as the host identifier, and when the flex-id hook library is
      used the replace-client-id must be set to true; client-id will be used
      with client-id-pop0. </simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>identifier-type6</command> (default duid)
      specifies the identifier type to build the User-Name attribute. It should
      be the same as the host identifier, and when the flex-id hook library is
      used the replace-client-id must be set to true; duid will be used with
      client-id-pop0.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>realm</command> (default "") is the default
      realm.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>reselect-subnet-address</command> (default
      false) uses the Kea reserved address/RADIUS Framed-IP-Address or
      Framed-IPv6-Address to reselect subnets where the address is not in
      the subnet range.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>reselect-subnet-pool</command> (default
      false) uses the Kea client-class/RADIUS Frame-Pool to reselect
      subnets where no available pool can be found.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>retries</command> (default 3) is the number of
      retries before trying the next server. Note that it is not supported for
      asynchronous communication.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>session-history</command> (default "") is the
      name of the file providing persistent storage for accounting session
      history.</simpara></listitem>

      <listitem><simpara><command>timeout</command> (default 10) is the number
      of seconds during which a response is awaited.</simpara></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </para>

    <para> When <command>reselect-subnet-pool</command> or
    <command>reselect-subnet-address</command> is set to true at the
    reception of RADIUS Access-Accept, the selected subnet is checked
    against the client-class name or the reserved address; if it does
    not match, another subnet is selected among matching subnets.
    </para>

    <para>
      Two services are supported:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><simpara><command>access</command> - the authentication service </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><command>accounting</command> - the accounting service</simpara></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      Configuration of services is divided into two parts:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>servers that define RADIUS servers the library is expected to
          contact. Each server may have the following items specified:</simpara>
          <itemizedlist>

            <listitem><simpara><command>name</command>, which specifies the IP
            address of the server (it is possible to use a name which will be
            resolved, but it is not recommended).</simpara></listitem>

            <listitem><simpara><command>port</command> (default RADIUS
            authentication or accounting service), which specifies the UDP port
            of the server. Note that the FreeRADIUS client library by default
            uses ports 1812 (authorization) and 1813 (accounting). Some server implementations
            use 1645 (authorization) and 1646 (accounting). You may use the "port" parameter to
            adjust as needed.</simpara></listitem>

            <listitem><simpara><command>secret</command>, which authenticates
            messages.</simpara></listitem>

          </itemizedlist>
          <simpara>There may be up to eight servers. Note that when no server is
          specified, the service is disabled.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>attributes which define additional information that
          the Kea server will send to a RADIUS server. The parameter
          must be identified either by a name or type. Its value can
          be specified in one of three possible ways: data (which
          defines a plain text value), raw (which defines the value in
          hex), or expr (which defines an expression, which will be
          evaluated for each incoming packet independently).
          </simpara>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><simpara><command>name</command> of the
            attribute.</simpara></listitem>
            
            <listitem><simpara><command>type</command> of the attribute. Either the type
            or the name must be provided, and the attribute must be defined in the dictionary.</simpara></listitem>

            <listitem><simpara><command>data</command> is the first of three
            ways to specify the attribute content. The data entry is parsed by
            the FreeRADIUS library, so values defined in the dictionary of the
            attribute may be used.</simpara></listitem>

            <listitem><simpara><command>raw</command> is the second of three
            ways to specify the attribute content; it specifies the content in
            hexadecimal. Note that it does not work with integer-content attributes
            (date, integer, and IPv4 address); a string-content attribute
            (string, IPv6 address, and IPv6 prefix) is
            required.</simpara></listitem>

            <listitem><simpara><command>expr</command> is the last way to
            specify the attribute content. It specifies an evaluation expression
            which must return a not-empty string when evaluated with the DHCP
            query packet. Currently this is restricted to the access
            service. </simpara></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
<para>
  For example, to specify a single access server available on localhost that
  uses "xyz123" as a secret, and tell Kea to send three additional attributes
  (Password, Connect-Info, and Configuration-Token), the following snippet could
  be used:
  <screen>
"parameters": {

    // Other RADIUS parameters here

    "access": {

        // This starts the list of access servers
        "servers": [
        {
            // These are parameters for the first (and only) access server
            "name": "127.0.0.1",
            "port": 1812,
            "secret": "xyz123"
        }
        // Additional access servers could be specified here
        ],

        // This defines a list of additional attributes Kea will send to each
        // access server in Access-Request.
        "attributes": [
        {
            // This attribute is identified by name (must be present in the
            // dictionary) and has static value (i.e. the same value will be
            // sent to every server for every packet)
            "name": "Password",
            "data": "mysecretpassword"
        },
        {
            // It's also possible to specify an attribute using its type,
            // rather than a name. 77 is Connect-Info. The value is specified
            // using hex. Again, this is a static value. It will be sent the
            // same for every packet and to every server.
            "type": 77,
            "raw": "65666a6a71"
        },
        {
            // This example shows how an expression can be used to send dynamic
            // value. The expression (see Section 13) may take any value from
            // the incoming packet or even its metadata (e.g. the interface
            // it was received over from)
            "name": "Configuration-Token",
            "expr": "hexstring(pkt4.mac,':')"
        }
        ] // End of attributes
    } // End of access

    // Accounting parameters.
    "accounting": {
        // This starts the list of accounting servers
        "servers": [
        {
            // These are parameters for the first (and only) accounting server
            "name": "127.0.0.1",
            "port": 1813,
            "secret": "sekret"
        }
        // Additional accounting servers could be specified here
        ]
    }

}
</screen>
</para>

<para>For the RADIUS hook library to operate properly in DHCPv4, it is necessary
to also load the Host Cache hook library. The reason for this is somewhat
complex. In a typical deployment, the DHCP clients send their packets via
DHCP relay which inserts certain Relay Agent Information options, such as
circuit-id or remote-id. The values of those options are then used by the
Kea DHCP server to formulate the necessary attributes in the Access-Request message
sent to the RADIUS server. However, once the DHCP client gets its address, it
then renews by sending packets directly to the DHCP server. As a result, the
relays are not able to insert their RAI options and the DHCP server can't send the
Access-Request queries to the RADIUS server by using just the information from
incoming packets. Kea needs to keep the information received during the initial
Discover/Offer exchanges and use it again later when sending accounting
messages.</para>

<para>This mechanism is implemented based on user context in host reservations.
(See <xref linkend="user-context"/> for details about user context). The host
cache mechanism allows the information retrieved by RADIUS to be
stored and later used for sending accounting and access queries to the RADIUS
server. In other words, the host-cache mechanism is mandatory, unless you
do not want RADIUS communication for messages other than
Discover and the first Request from each client.</para>

</section>

</section>
