<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2018 Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
-->

    <section xml:id="class-cmds-library">
      <title>class_cmds: Class Commands</title>
      <para>
        This section describes the Class Commands hooks library, which exposes
        several control commands for manipulating client classes, being a part of
        the Kea DHCP servers' configurations, without the need to restart those
        servers. Using these commands it is possible to add, update, delete and
        list client classes configured for a given server.

        <note>
          <para>This library may only be loaded by <command>kea-dhcp4</command>
          or <command>kea-dhcp6</command> process.
          </para>
        </note>

        <para>The Class Commands hooks library is available to premium Kea
        customers only</para>
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>class-add command</title>
        <para>The <command>class-add</command> command is used to add a new client
        class to the DHCP server configuration. This class is appended at the
        end of the list of classes used by the server, i.e. this class may depend
        on any of the already configured client classes.</para>
        <para>The following example demonstrates how to add a new client class
        to the DHCPv4 server configuration:
<screen>
{
    "command": "class-add",
    "arguments": {
        "client-classes": [
            {
                "name": "ipxe_efi_x64",
                "test": "option[93].hex == 0x0009",
                "next-server": "192.0.2.254",
                "server-hostname": "hal9000",
                "boot-file-name": "/dev/null"
            }
        ]
    }
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
          Note that the <command>client-classes</command> parameter is a JSON list,
          but it allows only a single client class to be present. In the future this
          hooks library may be extended to support specification of multiple client
          classes within a single <command>class-add</command> command.
        </para>

        <para>
          The following is the example response to the <command>class-add</command>
          command:
<screen>
{
    "result": 0,
    "text": "Class 'ipxe_efi_x64' added."
}
</screen>
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>class-update command</title>
        <para>
          The <command>class-update</command> command is used to update an existing
          client class in the DHCP server configuration. If the client class with the
          given name doesn't exist, the server returns result code of 3. In such case,
          the server configuration is not modified (client class is not created). The
          <command>class-add</command> command must be used instead to create the new
          client class.
        </para>
        <para>
          The <command>class-update</command> command has the same arguments structure
          as <command>class-add</command> command:
<screen>
{
    "command": "class-update",
    "arguments": {
        "client-classes": [
            {
                "name": "ipxe_efi_x64",
                "test": "option[93].hex == 0x0017",
                "next-server": "0.0.0.0",
                "server-hostname": "xfce",
                "boot-file-name": "/dev/null"
            }
        ]
    }
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
          The following is the example response:
<screen>
{
    "result": 0,
    "text": "Class 'ipxe_efi_x64' updated."
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
          Any parameter of the client class can be modified with this command, except
          <command>name</command>. There is currently no way to rename the class,
          because the class name is used as a key for searching the class to be updated.
          In order to achieve similar effect to renaming the class, an existing class
          should be removed with <command>class-del</command> command and then added
          again with a different name using <command>class-add</command>. Note however,
          that the class with the new name will be added at the end of the list of
          configured classes.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>class-del command</title>
        <para>The <command>class-del</command> is used to remove a particular class
        from the server configuration. The class to be removed is identified by name.
        The class won't be removed if there are other classes dependening on it.
        In order to remove such class, the dependent classes must be removed first.</para>
        <para>The following is the example command removing
        <command>ipxe_efi_x64</command> class:
<screen>
{
    "command": "class-del",
    "arguments": {
        {
            "name": "ipxe_efi_x64"
        }
    }
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>The following is the sample response to the <command>class-del</command>
        command when the specified client class has been found:
<screen>
{
    "result": 0,
    "text": "Class 'ipxe_efi_x64' deleted."
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>If the class doesn't exist, the result of 3 is returned.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>class-list command</title>
        <para>The <command>class-list</command> is used to retrieve a list of all
        client classes. This command includes no arguments:
<screen>
{
    "command": "class-list"
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
          The following is the example response of the server including the list
          of client classes:
<screen>
{
    "result": 0,
    "text": "2 classes found",
    "arguments": {
        "client-classes": [
            {
                "name": "ipxe_efi_x64"
            },
            {
                "name": "pxeclient"
            }
        ]
    }
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
          Note that the returned list does not contain full class definitions, but
          merely class names. In order to retrieve full class information, the
          <command>class-get</command> command should be used.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>class-get command</title>
        <para>The <command>class-get</command> is used to retrieve detail information
        about specified class. The command structure is very simple:
<screen>
{
    "command": "class-get",
    "arguments": {
        "name": "pxeclient"
    }
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
          If the class with the specified name doesn't exist, the status code of 3
          is returned. If the specified client class exists, the class details are
          returned in the following format:
<screen>
{
    "result": 0,
    "text": "Class 'pxeclient' definition returned",
    "arguments": {
        "client-classes": [
            {
                "name": "pxeclient",
                "only-if-required": true,
                "test": "option[vendor-class-identifier].text == 'PXEClient'",
                "option-def": [
                    {
                        "name": "configfile",
                        "code": 209,
                        "type": "string"
                    }
                ],
                "option-data": [ ],
                "next-server": "0.0.0.0",
                "server-hostname": "xfce",
                "boot-file-name": "/dev/null"
            }
        ]
    }
}
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
          Note that the example above is DHCPv4 specific. The last three parameters
          are only returned by the DHCPv4 server and never returned by the DHCPv6
          server. Also, some of the parameters provided in this example may not be
          returned if they are not specified for the class. Specifically,
          <command>only-if-required</command>, <command>test</command> and the
          <command>option-def</command> are not returned if they are not specified
          for the class.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
