<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2018 Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
-->

      <section xml:id="lease-cmds">
        <title>lease_cmds: Lease Commands</title>
        <para>
          This section describes the hook library that offers a number of new
          commands used to manage leases. Kea provides a way to store lease
          information in several backends (memfile, MySQL, PostgreSQL and
          Cassandra). This library provides a unified interface that can
          manipulate leases in an unified, safe way. In particular, it allows
          things previously impossible: manipulate leases in memfile while Kea
          is running, sanity check changes, check lease existence and remove all
          leases belonging to specific subnet. It can also catch more obscure
          errors, like adding a lease with subnet-id that does not exist in the
          configuration or configuring a lease to use an address that is outside
          of the subnet to which it is supposed to belong.
          It provides a not programmatic way to manage user contexts
          associated to leases.

          <note>
            <para>This library may only be loaded by <command>kea-dhcp4</command>
            or <command>kea-dhcp6</command> process.
            </para>
          </note>
        </para>

        <para>There are many use cases when an administrative command may be
        useful: during migration between servers (possibly even between
        different vendors), when a certain network is being retired, when a
        device has been disconnected and the sysadmin knows for sure that it
        will not be coming back. The "get" queries may be useful for automating
        certain management and monitoring tasks. They can also act as
        preparatory steps for lease updates and removals.</para>

        <para>
          This library provides the following commands:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease4-add</command> - adds new IPv4 lease;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease6-add</command> - adds new IPv6 lease;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease4-get</command> - checks if an IPv4 lease with
              the specified parameters exists and returns it if it does;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease6-get</command> - checks if an IPv6 lease with
              the specified parameters exists and returns it if it does;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease4-get-all</command> - returns all IPv4 leases
              or IPv4 leases for specified subnets;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease6-get-all</command> - returns all IPv6 leases
              or IPv6 leases for specified subnets;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease4-get-page</command> - returns a page of all
              IPv4 leases; by iterating over pages it is possible to retrieve
              all leases in chunks;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease6-get-page</command> - returns a page of all
              IPv6 leases; by iterating over pages it is possible to retrieve
              all leases in chunks;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease4-del</command> - attempts to delete an IPv4
              lease with the specified parameters;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease6-del</command> - attempts to delete an IPv6
              lease with the specified parameters;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease4-update</command> - updates an IPv4 lease;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease6-update</command> - updates an IPv6 lease;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease4-wipe</command> - removes all leases from a
              specific IPv4 subnet or all subnets;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>lease6-wipe</command> - removes all leases from a
              specific IPv6 subnet or all subnets;</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

        </para>

        <para>Lease commands library is part of the open source code and is
        available to every Kea user.</para>

        <para>
          All commands are using JSON syntax. They can be issued either using
          control channel (see <xref linkend="ctrl-channel"/>) or via Control
          Agent (see <xref linkend="kea-ctrl-agent"/>).
        </para>

        <para>
          The library can be loaded in the same way as other hook libraries. It
          does not take any parameters. It supports both DHCPv4 and DHCPv6
          servers.
<screen>
"Dhcp6": { <userinput>
    "hooks-libraries": [
        {
            "library": "/path/libdhcp_lease_cmds.so"
        }
        ...
    ] </userinput>
}
</screen>
        </para>

        <section>
          <title>lease4-add, lease6-add commands</title>
        <para>
          <command>lease4-add</command> and <command>lease6-add</command>
          commands allow for the creation of a new lease. Typically Kea creates a lease
          on its own, when it first sees a new device. However, sometimes it may
          be convenient to create the lease administratively. The
          <command>lease4-add</command> command requires at least three
          parameters: an IPv4 address, a subnet-id and an identifier: hardware
          (MAC) address. The simplest successful call might look as follows:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease4-add",
    "arguments": {
        "subnet-id": 44,
        "ip-address": "192.0.2.202",
        "hw-address": "1a:1b:1c:1d:1e:1f"
    }
}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para><command>lease6-add</command> command requires four
        parameters: an IPv6 address, a subnet-id, and IAID value
        (identity association identifier, a value sent by clients) and
        a DUID:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease6-add",
    "arguments": {
        "subnet-id": 66,
        "ip-address": "2001:db8::3",
        "duid": "1a:1b:1c:1d:1e:1f:20:21:22:23:24",
        "iaid": 1234
    }
}</screen>

<command>lease6-add</command> can be also used to add leases for IPv6
prefixes. In this case there are two parameters that must be
specified: type (set to value of "IA_PD") and a prefix
length. The actual prefix is set using ip-address field. For example,
to configure a lease for prefix 2001:db8:abcd::/48, the following
command can be used:

<screen>
{
    "command": "lease6-add",
    "arguments": {
        "subnet-id": 66,
        "type": "IA_PD",
        "ip-address": "2001:db8:abcd::",
        "prefix-len": 48,
        "duid": "1a:1b:1c:1d:1e:1f:20:21:22:23:24",
        "iaid": 1234
    }
}</screen>

The commands can take a number of additional optional parameters:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>valid-lft</command> - specifies the lifetime of the
              lease, expressed in seconds. If not specified, the value
              configured in the subnet related to specified subnet-id is
              used.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>expire</command> - timestamp of the lease
              expiration time, expressed in unix format (seconds since 1 Jan
              1970). If not specified, the default value is now + valid
              lifetime.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>fqdn-fwd</command> - specifies whether the lease
              should be marked as if forward DNS update was conducted. Note this
              only affects the lease parameter and the actual DNS update will
              not be conducted at the lease insertion time. If configured, a DNS
              update to remove the A or AAAA records will be conducted when the
              lease is removed due to expiration or being released by a
              client. If not specified, the default value is false. Hostname
              parameter must be specified in fqdn-fwd is set to true.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>fqdn-rev</command> - specifies whether the lease
              should be marked as if reverse DNS update was conducted. Note this
              only affects the lease parameter and the actual DNS update will
              not be conducted at the lease insertion time. If configured, a DNS
              update to remove the PTR record will be conducted when the lease
              is removed due to expiration or being released by a client. If not
              specified, the default value is false. Hostname parameter must be
              specified in fqdn-fwd is set to true.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>hostname</command> - specifies the hostname to be
              associated with this lease. Its value must be non-empty if either
              fqdn-fwd or fwdn-rev are set to true. If not specified, the
              default value is an empty string.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>hw-address</command> - hardware (MAC) address can
              be optionally specified for IPv6 lease. It is mandatory parameter
              for IPv4 lease.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>client-id</command> - client identifier is an
              optional parameter that can be specified for IPv4 lease.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>preferred-lft</command> - Preferred lifetime is an
              optional parameter for IPv6 leases. If not specified, the value
              configured for the subnet corresponding to the specified subnet-id
              is used. This parameter is not used in IPv4.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><command>user-context</command> - specifies the user
              context to be associated with this lease. It must be a
              JSON map.</para>
              </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>Here's an example of more complex lease addition:

<screen>
{
    "command": "lease6-add",
    "arguments": {
        "subnet-id": 66,
        "ip-address": "2001:db8::3",
        "duid": "01:02:03:04:05:06:07:08",
        "iaid": 1234,
        "hw-address": "1a:1b:1c:1d:1e:1f",
        "preferred-lft": 500,
        "valid-lft": 1000,
        "expire": 12345678,
        "fqdn-fwd": true,
        "fqdn-rev": true,
        "hostname": "urania.example.org",
        "user-context": { "version": 1 }
    }
}
</screen>
        </para>

        <para>
          The command returns a status that indicates either a success (result
          0) or a failure (result 1). Failed command always includes text
          parameter that explains the cause of failure. Example results:
          <screen>{ "result": 0, "text": "Lease added." }</screen> Example failure:
          <screen>{ "result": 1, "text": "missing parameter 'ip-address' (&lt;string&gt;:3:19)" }</screen>
        </para>


        <section>
          <title>lease4-get, lease6-get commands</title>
          <para><command>lease4-get</command> or <command>lease6-get</command>
          can be used to query the lease database and retrieve existing
          leases. There are two types of parameters the
          <command>lease4-get</command> supports: (address) or (subnet-id,
          identifier-type, identifier). There are two types for
          <command>lease6-get</command>: (address,type) or (subnet-id,
          identifier-type, identifier, IAID, type). The first type of query is
          used when the address (either IPv4 or IPv6) is known, but the details
          of the lease aren't. One common use case of this type of query is to
          find out whether a given address is being used or not. The second
          query uses identifiers. Currently supported identifiers for leases are:
          "hw-address" (IPv4 only), "client-id" (IPv4 only) and "duid" (IPv6 only).
          </para>

          <para>
            An example <command>lease4-get</command> command for getting a lease
            by an IPv4 address looks as follows:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease4-get",
    "arguments": {
        "ip-address": "192.0.2.1"
    }
}
</screen>
          </para>

          <para>An example of the <command>lease6-get</command> query
          looks as follows:
<screen>
{
  "command": "lease6-get",
  "arguments": {
    "ip-address": "2001:db8:1234:ab::",
    "type": "IA_PD"
  }
}</screen>
          </para>

          <para>An example query by "hw-address" for IPv4 lease looks
          as follows:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease4-get",
    "arguments": {
        "identifier-type": "hw-address",
        "identifier": "08:08:08:08:08:08",
        "subnet-id": 44
    }
}</screen>

          </para>

          <para>An example query by "client-id" for IPv4 lease looks
          as follows:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease4-get",
    "arguments": {
        "identifier-type": "client-id",
        "identifier": "01:01:02:03:04:05:06",
        "subnet-id": 44
    }
}</screen>

          </para>

          <para>An example query by (subnet-id, identifier-type,
          identifier, iaid, type) for IPv6 lease looks as follows:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease4-get",
    "arguments": {
        "identifier-type": "duid",
        "identifier": "08:08:08:08:08:08",
        "iaid": 1234567,
        "type": "IA_NA",
        "subnet-id": 44
    }
}</screen>
The type is an optional parameter. Supported values are: IA_NA
(non-temporary address) and IA_PD (IPv6 prefix) are supported.
If not specified, IA_NA is assumed.
          </para>

          <para><command>leaseX-get</command> returns a result that indicates a
          result of the operation and lease details, if found. It has one of the
          following values: 0 (success), 1 (error) or 2 (empty). The empty
          result means that a query has been completed properly, but the object
          (a lease in this case) has not been found. The lease parameters, if
          found, are returned as arguments.
          </para>

          <para>
An example result returned when the host was found:
<screen>{
  "arguments": {
    "client-id": "42:42:42:42:42:42:42:42",
    "cltt": 12345678,
    "fqdn-fwd": false,
    "fqdn-rev": true,
    "hostname": "myhost.example.com.",
    "hw-address": "08:08:08:08:08:08",
    "ip-address": "192.0.2.1",
    "state": 0,
    "subnet-id": 44,
    "valid-lft": 3600
  },
  "result": 0,
  "text": "IPv4 lease found."
}</screen>
</para>

        </section>

        <section>
          <title>lease4-get-all, lease6-get-all commands</title>
          <para><command>lease4-get-all</command> and
          <command>lease6-get-all</command> are used to retrieve all
          IPv4 or IPv6 leases or all leases for the specified set of
          subnets. All leases are returned when there are no arguments
          specified with the command as in the following example:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease4-get-all"
}
</screen>
          </para>

          <para>If the arguments are provided, it is expected that they contain
          "subnets" parameter, being a list of subnet identifiers for which the
          leases should be returned. For example, in order to retrieve all IPv6
          leases belonging to the subnets with identifiers 1, 2, 3 and 4:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease6-get-all",
    "arguments": {
        "subnets": [ 1, 2, 3, 4 ]
    }
}
</screen>
          </para>

          <para>
            The returned response contains a detailed list of leases in the
            following format:
<screen>{
    "arguments": {
        "leases": [
            {
                "cltt": 12345678,
                "duid": "42:42:42:42:42:42:42:42",
                "fqdn-fwd": false,
                "fqdn-rev": true,
                "hostname": "myhost.example.com.",
                "hw-address": "08:08:08:08:08:08",
                "iaid": 1,
                "ip-address": "2001:db8:2::1",
                "preferred-lft": 500,
                "state": 0,
                "subnet-id": 44,
                "type": "IA_NA",
                "valid-lft": 3600
            },
            {
                "cltt": 12345678,
                "duid": "21:21:21:21:21:21:21:21",
                "fqdn-fwd": false,
                "fqdn-rev": true,
                "hostname": "",
                "iaid": 1,
                "ip-address": "2001:db8:0:0:2::",
                "preferred-lft": 500,
                "prefix-len": 80,
                "state": 0,
                "subnet-id": 44,
                "type": "IA_PD",
                "valid-lft": 3600
            }
        ]
    },
    "result": 0,
    "text": "2 IPv6 lease(s) found."
}</screen>
          </para>

          <warning>
            <para>The <command>lease4-get-all</command> and
            <command>lease6-get-all</command> commands may result in very
            large responses. This may have negative impact on the DHCP server
            responsiveness while the response is generated and transmitted
            over the control channel, as the server imposes no restriction
            on the number of leases returned as a result of this command.
            </para>
          </warning>

        </section>

        <section>
          <title>lease4-get-page, lease6-get-page commands</title>
          <para>The <command>lease4-get-all</command> and
          <command>lease6-get-all</command> commands may result in very
          large responses. Generating such a response may consume CPU bandwith
          as well as memory. It may even cause the server to become
          unresponsive. In case of large lease databases it is usually better
          to retrieve leases in chunks, using paging mechanism. The
          <command>lease4-get-page</command> and <command>lease6-get-page</command>
          implement paging mechanism for DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 servers respectively.
          The following command retrieves first 1024 IPv4 leases:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease4-get-page",
    "arguments": {
        "from": "start",
        "limit": 1024
    }
}
</screen>
          </para>

          <para>The keyword <command>start</command> denotes that the first page
          of leases should be retrieved. Alternatively, an IPv4 zero address
          can be specified to retrieve the first page:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease4-get-page",
    "arguments": {
        "from": "0.0.0.0",
        "limit": 1024
    }
}
</screen>
          </para>

          <para>Similaraly, the IPv6 zero address can be specified in the
          <command>lease6-get-page</command> command:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease6-get-page",
    "arguments": {
        "from": "::",
        "limit": 6
    }
}
</screen>
          </para>

          <para>The response has the following structure:
<screen>
{
    "arguments": {
        "leases": [
            {
                "ip-address": "2001:db8:2::1",
                ...
            },
            {
                "ip-address": "2001:db8:2::9",
                ...
            },
            {
                "ip-address": "2001:db8:3::1",
                ...
            },
            {
                "ip-address": "2001:db8:5::3",
                ...
            }
            {
                "ip-address": "2001:db8:4::1",
                ...
            },
            {
                "ip-address": "2001:db8:2::7",
                ...
            }

        ],
        "count": 6
    },
    "result": 0,
    "text": "6 IPv6 lease(s) found."
}
</screen>

          </para>

          <para>Note that the leases' details were excluded from the response above
          for brevity.</para>

          <para>Generally, the returned list isn't sorted in any particular order.
          Some lease database backends may sort leases in ascending order of addresses,
          but the controlling client must not rely on this behavior. In case of
          highly distributed databases, such as Cassandra, ordering may be inefficient
          or even impossible.</para>

          <para>The <command>count</command> parameter contains a number of returned
          leases on the page.
          </para>

          <para>In order to fetch next page the client must use the last address
          of the current page as an input to the next
          <command>lease4-get-page</command> or <command>lease6-get-page</command>
          command call. In this example it is going to be:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease6-get-page",
    "arguments": {
        "from": "2001:db8:2::7",
        "count": 6
    }
}
</screen>
            because the 2001:db8:2::7 is the last address on the current page.
          </para>

          <para>The client may assume that it has reached the last page when the
          <command>count</command> value is lower than specified in the command,
          including the case when the <command>count</command> is equal to 0,
          which means that no leases were found.
          </para>

        </section>

        <section>
          <title>lease4-del, lease6-del commands</title>
          <para><command>leaseX-del</command> can be used to delete a lease from
          the lease database. There are two types of parameters this command
          supports, similar to leaseX-get commands: (address) for both v4 and
          v6, (subnet-id, identifier-type, identifier) for v4 and (subnet-id,
          identifier-type, identifier, type, IAID) for v6. The first type of
          query is used when the address (either IPv4 or IPv6) is known, but the
          details of the lease are not. One common use case of this type of query
          is to remove a lease (e.g. you want a specific address to no longer be
          used, no matter who may use it). The second query uses
          identifiers. For maximum flexibility, this interface uses identifiers
          as a pair of values: type and the actual identifier. Currently
          supported identifiers are "hw-address" (IPv4 only), "client-id"
          (IPv4 only) and "duid" (IPv6 only), but additional types may be added
          in the future. </para>

          <para>
            An example command for deleting a host reservation by address looks
            as follows:
<screen>
{
    "command": "lease4-del",
    "arguments": {
        "ip-address": "192.0.2.202"
    }
}</screen>

An example IPv4 lease deletion by "hw-address" looks as follows:

<screen>{
  "command": "lease4-del",
  "arguments": {
    "identifier": "08:08:08:08:08:08",
    "identifier-type": "hw-address",
    "subnet-id": 44
  }
}</screen>
          </para>

          <para><command>leaseX-del</command> returns a result that
          indicates a outcome of the operation. It has one of the
          following values: 0 (success), 1 (error) or 3 (empty). The
          empty result means that a query has been completed properly,
          but the object (a lease in this case) has not been found.
          </para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>lease4-update, lease6-update commands</title>
          <para><command>lease4-update</command> and
          <command>lease6-update</command> commands can be used to update
          existing leases. Since all lease database backends are indexed by IP
          addresses, it is not possible to update an address. All other fields
          may be updated. If an address needs to be changed, please use
          <command>leaseX-del</command> followed by
          <command>leaseX-add</command> commands.</para>

          <para>The optional boolean parameter "force-create" specifies
          if the lease should be created if it doesn't exist in the database.
          It defaults to false, which indicates that the lease is not created
          if it doesn't exist. In such case, an error is returned as a result
          of trying to update a non-existing lease. If the "force-create" parameter
          is set to true and the updated lease doesn't exist, the new lease is
          created as a result of receiving the <command>leaseX-update</command>.
          </para>

          <para>
            An example command updating IPv4 lease looks as follows:
<screen>{
  "command": "lease4-update",
  "arguments": {
    "ip-address": "192.0.2.1",
    "hostname": "newhostname.example.org",
    "hw-address": "1a:1b:1c:1d:1e:1f",
    "subnet-id": 44,
    "force-create": true
  }
}</screen>
          </para>

          <para>
            An example command updating IPv6 lease looks as follows:
<screen>{
  "command": "lease6-update",
  "arguments": {
    "ip-address": "2001:db8::1",
    "duid": "88:88:88:88:88:88:88:88",
    "iaid": 7654321,
    "hostname": "newhostname.example.org",
    "subnet-id": 66,
    "force-create": false
  }
}</screen>
          </para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>lease4-wipe, lease6-wipe commands</title>
          <para><command>lease4-wipe</command> and
          <command>lease6-wipe</command> are designed to remove all
          leases associated with a given subnet. This administrative
          task is expected to be used when existing subnet is being
          retired. Note that the leases are not properly expired,
          there are no DNS updates conducted, no log messages and
          hooks are not called for leases being removed.</para>

          <para>An example of <command>lease4-wipe</command> looks as follows:
<screen>{
  "command": "lease4-wipe",
  "arguments": {
    "subnet-id": 44
  }
}</screen>
          </para>

          <para>An example of <command>lease6-wipe</command> looks as follows:
<screen>{
  "command": "lease6-wipe",
  "arguments": {
    "subnet-id": 66
  }
}</screen>
          </para>

          <para>The commands return a textual description of the
          number of leases removed and 0 (success) status code if any
          leases were removed and 2 (empty) if there were no
          leases. Status code 1 (error) may be returned in case the
          parameters are incorrect or some other exception is
          encountered.</para>

          <para>The subnet-id 0 has special meaning. It tells Kea to
          delete leases from all configured subnets. Also, the
          subnet-id parameter may be omitted. If not specified, leases
          from all subnets are wiped.</para>

          <para>Note: not all backends support this command.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
