<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2018 Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
-->
<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="kea-netconf">
  <title>YANG/NETCONF Support</title>

  <section xml:id="netconf-overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>Kea 1.5.0 introduced an optional support for YANG/NETCONF
    interface with the new <command>kea-netconf</command>
    Netconf agent. </para>

    <para>This bare bones documentation is a work in progress. Its
    current purpose is to let engineers joining the project or perhaps
    advanced early adopters to get up to speed quickly.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="netconf-install">
    <title>Installing NETCONF Dependencies</title>

    <para>Note that to get NETCONF capabilities Kea uses Sysrepo software, which has many
    dependencies. Unfortunately, many of them are not available as packages, so some need
    to be compiled manually.</para>

    <para>The following installation instruction was tested on Ubuntu 18.04.</para>

    <para>STEP 1. Install dependencies. Note that some of those dependencies are likely to
    be present in your system already.

<screen>
$ sudo apt-get install git cmake build-essential bison flex libpcre3-dev libev-dev libavl-dev libprotobuf-c-dev protobuf-c-compiler swig
</screen>

    </para>

    <para>STEP 2. Install libyang. Download libyang from
    <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xlink:href="https://github.com/CESNET/libyang/releases" />. The version used
    during Kea development was 0.16-r1.

<screen>
    libyang-0.16-r1.tar.gz
    cd libyang-0.16-r1
    mkdir build
    cd build
    cmake ..
    make
    sudo make install
</screen>

    For detailed build instructions, see
    <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xlink:href="https://github.com/CESNET/libyang" /></para>

    <para<Please note that libyang building requires a gcc version at
    least 4.9 so on some environments like CentOS 7.5 the system
    compiler cannot be used.</para>

    <para>STEP 3. Install syrepo. Download sysrepo from
    <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xlink:href="https://github.com/sysrepo/sysrepo/releases" />.
    The version used during Kea development was 0.7.5.

<screen>
tar zxvf sysrepo-0.7.5.tar.gz
cd sysrepo-0.7.5
mkdir build
cd build
cmake -DCMAKE_BUILD_TYPE=Debug -DGEN_LANGUAGE_BINDINGS=ON -DGEN_CPP_BINDINGS=ON \
      -DGEN_PYTHON_BINDINGS=OFF -DGEN_LUA_BINDINGS=OFF -DENABLE_TESTS=OFF ..
make
sudo make install
</screen>

For detailed instructions, see Build &amp; Installation Steps Section on the project page
located at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xlink:href="https://github.com/sysrepo/sysrepo" />.
</para>
</section>

  <section>
    <title>Quick sysrepo overview</title>
    <para>
    This section covers a rather brief overview of a subset of available
    functionality in sysrepo. For more complete document, see sysrepo homepage.
    You may also want to take a look at
    <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xlink:href="https://github.com/isc-projects/kea-yang">notes made during a series of IETF
    Hackathons</uri>.
    </para>

    <para>
      List currently installed YANG modules:
<screen>
  $ sysrepoctl -l
</screen>

After installation the result should be similar to this:
<screen>
Sysrepo schema directory: /home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang/
Sysrepo data directory:   /home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/data/
(Do not alter contents of these directories manually)

Module Name                | Revision   | Conformance | Data Owner          | Permissions | Submodules                    | Enabled Features
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
ietf-netconf-notifications | 2012-02-06 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
ietf-netconf               | 2011-06-01 | Imported    |                     |             |                               |
ietf-netconf-acm           | 2012-02-22 | Imported    |                     |             |                               |
nc-notifications           | 2008-07-14 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
notifications              | 2008-07-14 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
turing-machine             | 2013-12-27 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
iana-if-type               | 2014-05-08 | Installed   |                     |             |                               |
ietf-interfaces            | 2014-05-08 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
ietf-ip                    | 2014-06-16 | Installed   |                     |             |                               |
</screen>
    </para>

    <para>
Installing Kea YANG modules. There are two major modules that Kea is able to
support: kea-dhcp4-server and kea-dhcp6-server. Note that while there is an
active effort at DHC working group at IETF to develop an DHCPv6 YANG model,
similar initiative for DHCPv4 died long time ago. As such, Kea uses its own
dedicated models for DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 but partially supports the IETF model
for DHCPv6. Those three models have extra
models as dependencies. The dependency models are also provided in
src/lib/libyang/models. To install models, do the following:

<screen>
cd src/lib/yang/models
sudo sysrepoctl -i -s /home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang -s . -g ietf-dhcpv6-server.yang
sudo sysrepoctl -i -s /home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang -s . -g kea-dhcp4-server.yang
sudo sysrepoctl -i -s /home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang -s . -g kea-dhcp6-server.yang
</screen>

Note the first -s parameter specifies the location of your YANG schema
repository. You can check it with sysrepoctl -l. This is a parameter that is
configured during sysrepo compilation and is detected by Kea configure
under the SYSREPO_REPO name.

The installation should look similar to the following:
<screen>
$ sudo sysrepoctl -i -s /home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang -s . -g ietf-dhcpv6-server.yang
Installing a new module from file 'ietf-dhcpv6-server.yang'...
Installing the YANG file to '/home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang/ietf-dhcpv6-server@2018-07-14.yang'...
Resolving dependency: 'ietf-dhcpv6-server' imports 'ietf-dhcpv6-options'...
Installing the YANG file to '/home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang/ietf-dhcpv6-options@2018-07-14.yang'...
Resolving dependency: 'ietf-dhcpv6-options' imports 'ietf-dhcpv6-types'...
Installing the YANG file to '/home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang/ietf-dhcpv6-types@2018-07-14.yang'...
Resolving dependency: 'ietf-dhcpv6-server' imports 'ietf-dhcpv6-types'...
Installing the YANG file to '/home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang/ietf-dhcpv6-types@2018-07-14.yang'...
Resolving dependency: 'ietf-dhcpv6-server' imports 'ietf-interfaces'...
Schema of the module ietf-interfaces is already installed, skipping...
Installing data files for module 'ietf-dhcpv6-server'...
Resolving dependency: 'ietf-dhcpv6-server' imports 'ietf-dhcpv6-options'...
Skipping installation of data files for module 'ietf-dhcpv6-options'...
Resolving dependency: 'ietf-dhcpv6-options' imports 'ietf-dhcpv6-types'...
Skipping installation of data files for module 'ietf-dhcpv6-types'...
Resolving dependency: 'ietf-dhcpv6-server' imports 'ietf-dhcpv6-types'...
Skipping installation of data files for module 'ietf-dhcpv6-types'...
Resolving dependency: 'ietf-dhcpv6-server' imports 'ietf-interfaces'...
Installing data files for module 'ietf-interfaces'...
Notifying sysrepo about the change...
Install operation completed successfully.
</screen>

You can confirm whether the models are imported correctly by using sysrepoctl -l

<screen>
$ sysrepoctl -l
Sysrepo schema directory: /home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/yang/
Sysrepo data directory:   /home/thomson/devel/sysrepo-0.7.5/build/repository/data/
(Do not alter contents of these directories manually)

Module Name                | Revision   | Conformance | Data Owner          | Permissions | Submodules                    | Enabled Features
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
ietf-netconf-notifications | 2012-02-06 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
ietf-netconf               | 2011-06-01 | Imported    |                     |             |                               |
ietf-netconf-acm           | 2012-02-22 | Imported    |                     |             |                               |
nc-notifications           | 2008-07-14 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
notifications              | 2008-07-14 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
turing-machine             | 2013-12-27 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
iana-if-type               | 2014-05-08 | Installed   |                     |             |                               |
ietf-interfaces            | 2014-05-08 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
ietf-ip                    | 2014-06-16 | Installed   |                     |             |                               |
kea-dhcp4-server           | 2018-07-14 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
kea-dhcp6-server           | 2018-07-14 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
ietf-dhcpv6-server         | 2018-03-04 | Installed   | root:root           | 666         |                               |
ietf-dhcpv6-options        | 2018-03-04 | Imported    |                     |             |                               |
ietf-dhcpv6-types          | 2018-01-30 | Imported    |                     |             |                               |
</screen>
</para>

  </section>

  <section xml:id="netconf-models">
    <title>Supported YANG models</title>

    <para>
      The currently the only supported models are
      <command>kea-dhcp4-server</command> and
      <command>kea-dhcp6-server</command>.
      There is partial support for <command>ietf-dhcpv6-server</command>,
      but the primary focus of testing was on Kea DHCP servers.
      Several other models
      (<command>kea-dhcp-ddns</command> and
      <command>kea-ctrl-agent</command>) are currently not supported. It is
      envisaged the situation to change in the future.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section xml:id="using-netconf">
    <title>Using the Netconf agent</title>

    <para>
      The Netconf agent follows this algorithm:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            Open a connection with the sysrepo enviroment and establish
            two sessions with the startup and running datastores.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            For each managed server get the initial configuration from
            the server through the control scoket.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            For each managed server get the YANG configuration from the
            startup datastore, translate it to JSON and load it onto
            the server being configured.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            For each managed server subscribe a module change callback
            using its model name.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            When a running configuration is changed, the callback tries
            to validate or load the updated configuration to the managed
            server.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="netconf-configuration">
    <title>Configuration</title>

    <para>
      The behavior described in <xref linkend="using-netconf"/> is
      controlled by a few configuration flags which can be set in
      the global scope or in a specific managed server scope.
      In the second case the value defined in managed server scope
      takes precedence.
      These flags are:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            The <command>boot-update</command> controls the initial
            configuration phase: when true (the default) the initial
            configuration retrieved from the classic Kea server JSON
            configuration file is loaded first, then the startup YANG
            model is loaded. This setting lets you define a control socket in
            your local JSON file and then download the configuration from YANG.
            When set to false, this phase is skipped.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            The <command>subscribe-changes</command> controls the
            module change subscription: when true (the default)
            a module change callback is subscribed, when false
            the phase is skipped and running configuration updates
            are disabled. When set to true, the running datastore is
            used to subscribe for changes.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            The <command>validate-changes</command> controls how Kea monitors
            the changes in Sysrepo configuration. Sysrepo offers two
            stages where Kea could interact: validation and
            application. The first one is called validation (or
            SR_EV_VERIFY event in Sysrepo naming convention). At this
            stage Kea will get the new configuration being committed
            and will verify it. If the configuration is incorrect for
            whatever reason, Kea servers will reject it, the error
            will be propagated back to the Sysrepo, which in will
            return an error to whoever tried to commit those
            changes. This step only takes place if validate-changes is
            set to true. There is also a second step called
            application (or SR_EV_APPLY event in Sysrepo naming
            convention), where the actual configuration is being
            applied. At this stage Kea can receive the configuration,
            but it is too late to signal back any errors, as the
            configuration has been comitted already.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      Other configuration flags are under study and may appear in future Kea
      versions. For instance for loading updated configurations directly in the
      validation callback so syntactically correct, but invalid configurations
      (such as overlapping subnets) can be rejected as soon as possible.
    </para>

    <para>
      The idea behind the initial configuration phase is to boot Kea servers
      with a minimal configuration which includes only a control socket making
      them manageable. For instance for the DHCPv4 server:
<screen>
{
    "Dhcp4": {
        "control-socket": {
            "socket-type": "unix",
            "socket-name": "/tmp/kea4-sock"
        }
    }
}
</screen>
      Note the alternative to boot with full configurations does not
      allow an easy track of changes or synchronization between the JSON
      and YANG sources of configurations. So it not really compatible with
      the YANG / Netconf configuration management paradigm where
      everything should be performed in YANG.
    </para>

    <para>
      With module change subscriptions enabled, the kea-netconf daemon will
      monitor any configuration changes as they appear in the sysrepo. Such
      changes can be done using <command>sysrepocfg</command> tool or remotely
      using any NETCONF client. For details, please see Sysrepo
      documentation. Those tools can be used to modify YANG configurations in
      the running datastore. Note committed configurations are only updated in
      the running datastore: to keep them between server reboots they must be
      copied to the startup datastore.
    </para>

    <para>
      When module changes are tracked (using
      <command>subscribe-changes</command> set to true) and the
      running configuration has changed
      (e.g. using <command>sysrepocfg</command> or any NETCONF client)
      the callback is called to validate the modified configuration
      (if <command>validate-changes</command> was not set to false)
      and a second time to apply it. If the validation failed the
      callback is still called again but with an ABORT (vs APPLY)
      event with rollback changes.
    </para>

    <para>
      The returned code of the callback on an APPLY event is ignored,
      i.e. it is too late to refuse a bad configuration.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are four ways in which a modified YANG configuration could
      possibly be incorrect:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            It can be not compliant with the schema, e.g. unknown entry,
            missing mandatory entry, value with a bad type or
            not matching a constraint.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            It can fail to be translated from YANG to JSON, e.g.
            invalid user context.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            It can fail Kea server sanity checks, e.g. out of subnet
            pool range or unsupported database type.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            Syntax is correct and pass server sanity checks but
            the configuration fails to be run, e.g. the configuration
            specifies database credentials, but the database refuses
            connection.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      The first case is handled by sysrepo. The second and third cases
      are handled by Netconf in the validation phase (if not disabled
      by setting <command>validate-changes</command> to true). The last
      case makes the application phase to fail without a sensible report
      to sysrepo.
    </para>

    <para>
      The managed Kea servers or agents are described in the
      <command>managed-servers</command> section. Each sub-section
      begins by the service name: <command>dhcp4</command>,
      <command>dhcp6</command>, <command>d2</command>
      (the DHCP-DDNS server does not support the control channel
      feature yet), and <command>ca</command> (the control agent).
    </para>

    <para>
      Each managed server entry contains optionally:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            <command>boot-update</command>,
            <command>subscribe-changes</command> and
            <command>validate-changes</command> control flags.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            <command>model</command> specifies the YANG model / module name.
            For each service the default is the corresponding Kea YANG model,
            e.g. for <userinput>"dhcp4"</userinput> it is
            <userinput>"kea-dhcp4-server"</userinput>.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            <command>control-socket</command> specifies the control
            socket for managing the service configuration.
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      A control socket is specified by:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            <command>socket-type</command>: the socket type is either
            <command>stdout</command> (the default. It is not really a socket,
            but it allows to run <command>kea-netconf</command> in debugging
            mode where everything is printed on stdout. Can be also useful to
            redirect the commands easily.), <command>unix</command> (standard
            direct server control channel, which uses UNIX sockets), and
            <command>http</command> (using a control agent, which accepts HTTP
            connections).
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            <command>socket-name</command>: the local socket name for
            the <command>unix</command> socket type (default empty string).
          </simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            <command>socket-url</command>: the HTTP URL for the
            <command>http</command> socket type (default
            <userinput>http://127.0.0.1:8000/</userinput>).
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      User contexts can store arbitrary data as long as it is valid JSON
      syntax and its top level element is a map (i.e. the data must be
      enclosed in curly brackets). They are accepted at the Netconf entry,
      i.e. below the toplevel, managed service entry and control socket
      entry scopes.
    </para>

    <para>
      Hooks libraries can be loaded by the Netconf agent just like
      other servers or agents. It currently supports no hook point,
      however. This is expected to change in the upcoming Kea
      releases. The <command>hooks-libraries</command> list
      contains the list of hooks libraries that should be loaded by Netconf,
      along with their configuration information specified with
      <command>parameters</command>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Please consult <xref linkend="logging"/> for the details how to
      configure logging. The Netconf's root logger's name is
      <command>kea-netconf</command> as given in the example above.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="netconf-example">
    <title>Kea-netconf Configuration Example</title>
    <para>
      The following example demonstrates the basic Netconf configuration.
      More examples are available in <command>doc/examples/netconf</command>
      directory in Kea sources.
    </para>
    <para>
<screen>
// This is a simple example of a configuration for Netconf.
// This server provides YANG interface for all Kea servers and agent.
{
    "Netconf":
    {
        // Control flags can be defined in the global scope or
        // in a managed server scope. Precedence are:
        // - use the default value (true)
        // - use the global value
        // - use the local value.
        // So this overwrites the default value:
        "boot-update": false,

        // This map specifies how each server is managed. For each server there
        // is a name of the YANG model to be used and the control channel.
        //
        // Currently three control channel types are supported:
        // "stdout" which output the configuration on the standard output,
        // "unix" which uses the local control channel supported by
        // "dhcp4" and "dhcp6" servers ("d2" support is not yet available),
        // and "http" which uses the Control agent "ca" to manage itself or
        // to forward commands to "dhcp4" or "dhcp6" (in the future also
        // to d2).
        "managed-servers":
        {
            // This is how Netconf can communicate with the DHCPv4 server.
            "dhcp4":
            {
                "comment": "DHCP4 server",
                "model": "kea-dhcp4-server",
                "control-socket":
                {
                    "socket-type": "unix",
                    "socket-name": "/tmp/kea4-ctrl-socket"
                }
            },

            // DHCPv6 parameters.
            "dhcp6":
            {
                "model": "kea-dhcp6-server",
                "control-socket":
                {
                    "socket-type": "unix",
                    "socket-name": "/tmp/kea6-ctrl-socket"
                }
            },

            // Currently the DHCP-DDNS (nicknamed D2) server does not support
            // command channel yet.
            "d2":
            {
                "model": "kea-dhcp-ddns",
                "control-socket":
                {
                    "socket-type": "stdout",
                    "user-context": { "in-use": false }
                }
            },

            // Of course the Control Agent (nicknamed CA) supports HTTP.
            "ca":
            {
                "model": "kea-ctrl-agent",
                "control-socket":
                {
                    "socket-type": "http",
                    "socket-url": "http://127.0.0.1:8000/"
                }
            }
        },

        // Netconf is able to load hook libraries that augment its operation.
        // Currently there are no hook points defined in kea-netconf
        // processing.
        "hooks-libraries": [
            // Hook libraries list may contain more than one library.
            {
                // The only necessary parameter is the library filename.
                "library": "/opt/local/netconf-commands.so",

                // Some libraries may support parameters. Make sure you
                // type this section carefully, as the kea-netconf does not
                // validate it (because the format is library specific).
                "parameters": {
                    "param1": "foo"
                }
            }
        ]

    },

    // Similar to other Kea components, Netconf also uses logging.
    "Logging":
    {
        "loggers": [
            {
                "name": "kea-netconf",
                "output_options": [
                    {
                        "output": "/var/log/kea-netconf.log",
                        // Several additional parameters are possible in
                        // addition to the typical output.
                        // Flush determines whether logger flushes output
                        //  to a file.
                        // Maxsize determines maximum filesize before
                        // the file is being rotated.
                        // Maxver specifies the maximum number of
                        //  rotated files being kept.
                        "flush": true,
                        "maxsize": 204800,
                        "maxver": 4
                    }
                ],
                "severity": "INFO",
                "debuglevel": 0
            }
        ]
    }
}
</screen>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="netconf-start-stop">
    <title>Starting and Stopping the Netconf Agent</title>
    <para>
<!-- no keactrl yet -->
      Netconf accepts the following command-line switches:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>-c <replaceable>file</replaceable></command> -
          specifies the configuration file.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>-d</command> - specifies whether the agent logging
          should be switched to debug/verbose mode. In verbose mode,
          the logging severity and debuglevel specified in the
          configuration file are ignored and "debug" severity and the
          maximum debuglevel (99) are assumed. The flag is convenient,
          for temporarily switching the server into maximum verbosity,
          e.g. when debugging.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>-t <replaceable>file</replaceable></command> -
          specifies the configuration file to be tested. Kea-netconf
          will attempt to load it, and will conduct sanity
          checks. Note that certain checks are possible only while
          running the actual server. The actual status is reported
          with exit code (0 = configuration looks ok, 1 = error
          encountered). Kea will print out log messages to standard
          output and error to standard error when testing
          configuration.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>-v</command> - prints out the Kea version and exits.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>-V</command> - prints out the Kea extended version
          with additional parameters and exits. The listing includes
          the versions of the libraries dynamically linked to Kea.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>-W</command> - prints out the Kea configuration
          report and exits. The report is a copy of the
          <filename>config.report</filename> file produced by
          <userinput>./configure</userinput>: it is embedded in the
          executable binary.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

</chapter>
