<!--
 - Copyright (C) 2017-2018 Internet Systems Consortium, Inc. ("ISC")
 -
 - This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
 - License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
 - file, you can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.
-->
<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="kea-shell">
  <title>The Kea Shell</title>

  <section xml:id="shell-overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>Kea 1.2.0 introduced the Control Agent (CA, see <xref linkend="kea-ctrl-agent"/>), which
    provides a RESTful control interface over HTTP. That API is typically expected to be used by
    various IPAMs and similar management systems. Nevertheless, there may be cases when an administrator wants
    to send a command to the CA directly. The Kea shell provides a way to do this. It is a simple
    command-line, scripting-friendly, text client that is able to connect to the CA, send it commands
    with parameters, retrieve the responses, and display them.</para>

    <para>As the primary purpose of the Kea shell is as a tool in a scripting environment,
    it is not interactive. However, with simple tricks it can be run manually.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="shell-usage">
    <title>Shell Usage</title>
    <para><command>kea-shell</command> is run as follows:
<screen>
kea-shell [--host hostname] [--port number] [--path path] [--timeout seconds] [--service service-name] [command]
</screen>
    where:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>--host <replaceable>hostname</replaceable></command> specifies the hostname
          of the CA. If not specified, "localhost" is used.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>--port <replaceable>number</replaceable></command> specifies the TCP port
          on which the CA listens. If not specified, 8000 is used.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>--path <replaceable>path</replaceable></command> specifies
          the path in the URL to connect to. If not specified, an
          empty path is used. As the CA listens at the empty path,
          this parameter is useful only with a reverse proxy.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>--timeout <replaceable>seconds</replaceable></command> specifies the
          timeout (in seconds) for the connection. If not given, 10 seconds is used.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>--service <replaceable>service-name</replaceable></command> specifies the
          target of a command. If not given, the CA will be used as the target. May be used more
          than once to specify multiple targets.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>


      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>command</command> specifies the command to be sent. If not specified,
          the <command>list-commands</command> command is used.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Other switches are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>-h</command> prints a help message.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <command>-v</command> prints the software version.
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Once started, the shell reads parameters for the command from standard input, which are
      expected to be in JSON format. When all have been read, the shell establishes a connection
      with the CA using HTTP, sends the command, and awaits a response. Once that is received,
      it is displayed on standard output.
    </para>

    <para>
      For a list of available commands, see <xref linkend="ctrl-channel"/>; additional commands
      may be provided by hook libraries. If you are unsure which commands are supported, use the
      <command>list-commands</command> command. It will instruct the CA to return a list of
      all supported commands.
    </para>

    <para>The following shows a simple example of usage:
<screen>
$ <userinput>kea-shell --host 192.0.2.1 --port 8001 --service dhcp4 list-commands</userinput>
^D
</screen>
    After the command line is entered, the program waits for command parameters to be entered.
    Since <command>list-commands</command> does not take any
    arguments, CTRL-D (represented in the above example by "^D") is pressed to indicate
    end-of-file and terminate the parameter input. The shell then contacts
    the CA and prints out the list of available commands returned for the service named <command>dhcp4</command>.
    </para>

    <para>It is envisaged that the Kea shell will be most frequently used in scripts; the next example
    shows a simple scripted execution. It sends the command "config-write" to the CA
    (the <command> --service </command> parameter hasn't been used), along
    with the parameters specified in param.json. The result will be stored in result.json.
<screen>
$ cat param.json
"filename": "my-config-file.json"
$ <userinput>cat param.json | kea-shell --host 192.0.2.1 config-write &gt; result.json</userinput>
</screen>
    </para>

    <para>When a reverse proxy is used to de-multiplex requests to different
    servers, the default empty path in the URL is not enough, so the
    <command> --path </command> parameter should be used. For instance,
    if requests to the "/kea" path are forwarded to the CA this can be used:
<screen>
$ <userinput>kea-shell --host 192.0.2.1 --port 8001 --path kea ...</userinput>
</screen>
    </para>

    <para>Kea shell requires Python to to be installed on the system. It has been tested with
    Python 2.7 and various versions
    of Python 3, up to 3.5. Since not every Kea deployment uses this feature and there are
    deployments that do not have Python, the Kea shell is not enabled by default. To use it,
    specify <command>--enable-shell</command> when running "configure" during the
    installation of Kea.</para>

    <para>The Kea shell is intended to serve more as a demonstration of the RESTful interface's
    capabilities (and, perhaps, an illustration for people interested in integrating their
    management environments with Kea) than as a serious management client. Do not expect it
    to be significantly expanded in the future. It is, and will remain, a simple tool.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
